<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><act name="act"><meta><identification source="#Laws-Africa"><FRBRWork><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/temporary-advertisements/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/temporary-advertisements"/><FRBRalias value="Control of Temporary Advertisements" name="title"/><FRBRdate date="2017" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/><FRBRcountry value="za-ec443"/><FRBRsubtype value="by-law"/><FRBRnumber value="temporary-advertisements"/></FRBRWork><FRBRExpression><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/temporary-advertisements/eng@2017-04-24/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/temporary-advertisements/eng@2017-04-24"/><FRBRdate date="2017-04-24" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/><FRBRlanguage language="eng"/></FRBRExpression><FRBRManifestation><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/temporary-advertisements/eng@2017-04-24/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/temporary-advertisements/eng@2017-04-24"/><FRBRdate date="2020-01-27" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/></FRBRManifestation></identification><publication number="3830" name="Eastern Cape Provincial Gazette" showAs="Eastern Cape Provincial Gazette" date="2017-04-24"/><references source="#Laws-Africa"><TLCOrganization showAs="Laws.Africa" eId="Laws-Africa" href="https://edit.laws.africa"/><TLCTerm showAs="street" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.street" eId="term-street"/><TLCTerm showAs="tariff" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.tariff" eId="term-tariff"/><TLCTerm showAs="election material" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.election_material" eId="term-election_material"/><TLCTerm showAs="commercial poster" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.commercial_poster" eId="term-commercial_poster"/><TLCTerm showAs="non-commercial poster" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.non_commercial_poster" eId="term-non_commercial_poster"/><TLCTerm showAs="banner" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.banner" eId="term-banner"/><TLCTerm showAs="control areas" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.control_areas" eId="term-control_areas"/><TLCTerm showAs="advertisement trailer" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.advertisement_trailer" eId="term-advertisement_trailer"/><TLCTerm showAs="public place" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.public_place" eId="term-public_place"/><TLCTerm showAs="advertising" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.advertising" eId="term-advertising"/><TLCTerm showAs="directional sign" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.directional_sign" eId="term-directional_sign"/><TLCTerm showAs="temporary advertisement" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.temporary_advertisement" eId="term-temporary_advertisement"/><TLCTerm showAs="municipality" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.municipality" eId="term-municipality"/><TLCTerm showAs="aerial sign" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.aerial_sign" eId="term-aerial_sign"/></references></meta><preface><p eId="preface__p_1">The Municipal Manager hereby publishes, in terms of Section 13 of the Local Government Municipal Systems Act, 2000 (<ref href="/akn/za/act/2000/32" eId="preface__p_1__ref_1">Act 32 of 2000</ref>) read with Section 162 of the <ref href="/akn/za/act/1996/constitution" eId="preface__p_1__ref_2">Constitution of the Republic of South Africa Act 1996</ref> (<ref href="/akn/za/act/1996/constitution" eId="preface__p_1__ref_3">Act 108 of 1996</ref>) the By-Laws in respect of the Control of Temporary Advertisements which by-laws shall come into operation on the date of publication thereof.</p></preface><body><section eId="sec_1"><num>1.</num><heading>Purpose</heading><content><p eId="sec_1__p_1">The purpose of these by-laws is to regulate, limit, prohibit, inspect, supervise and levy moneys with regard to the erection, display and use of temporary advertisements of whatever nature, on or visible from any <term refersTo="#term-street" eId="sec_1__p_1__term_1">street</term> or public space.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_2"><num>2.</num><heading>Definitions</heading><content><p eId="sec_2__p_1">For the purposes of these by-laws, unless the context otherwise indicates-</p><p refersTo="#term-advertisement_trailer" eId="sec_2__p_2">"<def refersTo="#term-advertisement_trailer" eId="sec_2__p_2__def_1">advertisement trailer</def>" means any trailer on which an advertisement sign is mounted with the sole purpose of displaying the advertisement to the public;</p><p refersTo="#term-advertising" eId="sec_2__p_3">"<def refersTo="#term-advertising" eId="sec_2__p_3__def_1">advertising</def>" means the act or process of notifying, warning, informing, making known or any other act of transferring information in a visible manner;</p><p refersTo="#term-aerial_sign" eId="sec_2__p_4">"<def refersTo="#term-aerial_sign" eId="sec_2__p_4__def_1">aerial sign</def>" means an aerial sign and includes any sign in the form of an air balloon or a sign which is displayed in the sky by means of balloons, searchlights, aeroplanes or similar aids;</p><p refersTo="#term-banner" eId="sec_2__p_5">"<def refersTo="#term-banner" eId="sec_2__p_5__def_1">banner</def>" means any flag-type <term refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_2__p_5__term_1">temporary advertisement</term> which is tied to poles with ropes or similar material;</p><p refersTo="#term-commercial_poster" eId="sec_2__p_6">"<def refersTo="#term-commercial_poster" eId="sec_2__p_6__def_1">commercial poster</def>" means any <term refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_2__p_6__term_1">temporary advertisement</term> of a commercial nature <term refersTo="#term-advertising" eId="sec_2__p_6__term_2">advertising</term> any event, meeting, gathering, activity, product, service or the sale of any goods;</p><p refersTo="#term-control_areas" eId="sec_2__p_7">"<def refersTo="#term-control_areas" eId="sec_2__p_7__def_1">control areas</def>" means those areas as determined by the <term refersTo="#term-municipality" eId="sec_2__p_7__term_1">municipality</term> from time to time in which degrees of <term refersTo="#term-advertising" eId="sec_2__p_7__term_2">advertising</term> control are applied in accordance with the visual sensitivity of such areas and traffic safety conditions;</p><p refersTo="#term-directional_sign" eId="sec_2__p_8">"<def refersTo="#term-directional_sign" eId="sec_2__p_8__def_1">directional sign</def>" means any sign with the purpose to make known or which indicates the route to and location of any meeting, gathering, event, exhibition, show house or any property which is for sale or to let, excluding any such sign erected by the <term refersTo="#term-municipality" eId="sec_2__p_8__term_1">municipality</term>;</p><p refersTo="#term-election_material" eId="sec_2__p_9">"<def refersTo="#term-election_material" eId="sec_2__p_9__def_1">election material</def>" means any advertisement or <term refersTo="#term-advertising" eId="sec_2__p_9__term_1">advertising</term> device which is displayed or is in any way whatsoever visible from a <term refersTo="#term-street" eId="sec_2__p_9__term_2">street</term> or any <term refersTo="#term-public_place" eId="sec_2__p_9__term_3">public place</term> and which is used in connection with a parliamentary or municipal election, referendum or plebiscite;</p><p refersTo="#term-municipality" eId="sec_2__p_10">"<def refersTo="#term-municipality" eId="sec_2__p_10__def_1">municipality</def>" means the Municipality of Mbizana established in terms of Section 12 of the Municipal Structures <ref href="/akn/za/act/1998/117" eId="sec_2__p_10__ref_1">Act, 117 of 1998</ref> and includes any political structure, political office bearer, councillor, duly authorised agent or any employee thereof acting in connection with these by-laws by virtue of a power vested in the municipality and delegated or sub-delegated to such political structure, political office bearer, councillor, agent or employee.</p><p refersTo="#term-non_commercial_poster" eId="sec_2__p_11">"<def refersTo="#term-non_commercial_poster" eId="sec_2__p_11__def_1">non-commercial poster</def>" means any <term refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_2__p_11__term_1">temporary advertisement</term> which is not of a commercial nature announcing or attracting public attention to any meeting, event, function, activity, show, market or undertaking of a sports, welfare, educational, political or religious nature or to the candidature of any person nominated for election to parliament, local government or any similar body or to a referendum;</p><p refersTo="#term-public_place" eId="sec_2__p_12">"<def refersTo="#term-public_place" eId="sec_2__p_12__def_1">public place</def>" includes any road, <term refersTo="#term-street" eId="sec_2__p_12__term_1">street</term>, thoroughfare, bridge, overhead bridge, subway, foot pavement, foot-path, sidewalk, lane, square, open space, garden, park or enclosed space vested in or under the control of the <term refersTo="#term-municipality" eId="sec_2__p_12__term_2">municipality</term>.</p><p refersTo="#term-street" eId="sec_2__p_13">"<def refersTo="#term-street" eId="sec_2__p_13__def_1">street</def>" includes any street, road or thoroughfare shown on the general plan of a township, agricultural holdings or other division of land or in respect of which the public have acquired a prescriptive or other right of way and includes a sidewalk adjacent to such a street, a traffic island, bridge or subway forming part of such a street.</p><p refersTo="#term-tariff" eId="sec_2__p_14">"<def refersTo="#term-tariff" eId="sec_2__p_14__def_1">tariff</def>" means any charge or deposit determined from time to time by Municipality in terms of section 10G (7) of the Local Government Transition Act, Second Amendment Act, 1996 (<ref href="/akn/za/act/1996/97" eId="sec_2__p_14__ref_1">Act No. 97 of 1996</ref>) or any other applicable law in respect of the display or any temporary advertisement in terms of these by-laws;</p><p refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_2__p_15">"<def refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_2__p_15__def_1">temporary advertisement</def>" means any visible representation of a word, name, letter, figure object, mark or symbol or of an abbreviation of a word or name, or of any combination of such elements with the object of transferring information including any <term refersTo="#term-non_commercial_poster" eId="sec_2__p_15__term_1">non-commercial poster</term>, <term refersTo="#term-commercial_poster" eId="sec_2__p_15__term_2">commercial poster</term>, <term refersTo="#term-banner" eId="sec_2__p_15__term_3">banner</term>, <term refersTo="#term-aerial_sign" eId="sec_2__p_15__term_4">aerial sign</term>, <term refersTo="#term-directional_sign" eId="sec_2__p_15__term_5">directional sign</term>, <term refersTo="#term-election_material" eId="sec_2__p_15__term_6">election material</term>, <term refersTo="#term-advertisement_trailer" eId="sec_2__p_15__term_7">advertisement trailer</term>, "For sale" or "Sold" sign which is not permanently fixed and where it is not intended to be permanently fixed.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_3"><num>3.</num><heading>Permission to display</heading><subsection eId="sec_3__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="sec_3__subsec_1__p_1">The Municipality shall from time to time define <term refersTo="#term-control_areas" eId="sec_3__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">control areas</term> and allocate the types of temporary advertisements which shall be allowed and/or prohibited in each of the aforesaid <term refersTo="#term-control_areas" eId="sec_3__subsec_1__p_1__term_2">control areas</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_3__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="sec_3__subsec_2__p_1">Unless the prior written approval of Municipality has been obtained, no person shall affix, attach, secure, place, display, distribute or have displayed or distributed or allow or permit the display or distribution of any <term refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_3__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">temporary advertisement</term> in or in view of any <term refersTo="#term-street" eId="sec_3__subsec_2__p_1__term_2">street</term> or <term refersTo="#term-public_place" eId="sec_3__subsec_2__p_1__term_3">public place</term> within the relevant control area where that type of <term refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_3__subsec_2__p_1__term_4">temporary advertisement</term> is allowed.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_3__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="sec_3__subsec_3__p_1">Where temporary advertisements are prohibited within the <term refersTo="#term-control_areas" eId="sec_3__subsec_3__p_1__term_1">control areas</term> as defined by Municipality, no person shall in or in view of any <term refersTo="#term-street" eId="sec_3__subsec_3__p_1__term_2">street</term> or <term refersTo="#term-public_place" eId="sec_3__subsec_3__p_1__term_3">public place</term> affix, attach, secure, place, display, distribute or have displayed or distributed or allow or permit the display or distribution of any <term refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_3__subsec_3__p_1__term_4">temporary advertisement</term>.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_4"><num>4.</num><heading>Manner of application to obtain permission</heading><content><p eId="sec_4__p_1">An application for permission to display or distribute a <term refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_4__p_1__term_1">temporary advertisement</term> shall be made on the prescribed application form and be accompanied by the applicable <term refersTo="#term-tariff" eId="sec_4__p_1__term_2">tariff</term> and deposit as determined by the Municipality plus a sketch plan or sample of the <term refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_4__p_1__term_3">temporary advertisement</term> if feasible as the case may be. Such sketch plan or sample shall contain sufficient detail describing the nature, dimensions, wording and method of affixation of the <term refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_4__p_1__term_4">temporary advertisement</term> to which it relates, provided that the Municipality shall, at all times, reserve the right to obtain such additional information as it may deem necessary from the applicant.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_5"><num>5.</num><heading>Approval in respect of the display of temporary advertisements</heading><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_1__p_1">If the Municipality, having considered an application referred to in Section 4, is satisfied that the application in question complies with the requirements of these by-laws and any other applicable law, it shall grant its approval in respect thereof.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><paragraph eId="sec_5__subsec_2__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_2__para_a__p_1">If the Municipality, having considered an application referred to in Section 4, is not so satisfied, it shall refuse to grant its approval in respect thereof and give the applicant written reasons for such refusal.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_5__subsec_2__para_b"><num>(b)</num><intro><p eId="sec_5__subsec_2__para_b__intro__p_1">If the Municipality, having considered an application referred to in Section 4, is satisfied that the <term refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_5__subsec_2__para_b__intro__p_1__term_1">temporary advertisement</term> to which the application in question relates-</p></intro><subparagraph eId="sec_5__subsec_2__para_b__subpara_i"><num>(i)</num><intro><p eId="sec_5__subsec_2__para_b__subpara_i__intro__p_1">is to be erected in such manner or will be of such nature or appearance that-</p></intro><subparagraph eId="sec_5__subsec_2__para_b__subpara_i__subpara_aa"><num>(aa)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_2__para_b__subpara_i__subpara_aa__p_1">the area in which it is to be erected will probably or in fact be disfigured thereby;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="sec_5__subsec_2__para_b__subpara_i__subpara_bb"><num>(bb)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_2__para_b__subpara_i__subpara_bb__p_1">it will probably or in fact be unsightly or objectionable;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="sec_5__subsec_2__para_b__subpara_i__subpara_cc"><num>(cc)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_2__para_b__subpara_i__subpara_cc__p_1">it will probably or in fact derogate from the value of adjoining or neighbouring properties;</p></content></subparagraph></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="sec_5__subsec_2__para_b__subpara_ii"><num>(ii)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_2__para_b__subpara_ii__p_1">will probably or in fact be dangerous to life or property,</p></content></subparagraph></paragraph><wrapUp><p eId="sec_5__subsec_2__wrapup__p_1">the Municipality must refuse to grant its approval in respect thereof and give the applicant written reasons for such refusal.</p></wrapUp></subsection></section><section eId="sec_6"><num>6.</num><heading>Deposits and charges</heading><content><p eId="sec_6__p_1">Whether or not permission therefore has been granted in terms of these by-laws, no <term refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_6__p_1__term_1">temporary advertisement</term> shall be erected or displayed, unless the prescribed <term refersTo="#term-tariff" eId="sec_6__p_1__term_2">tariff</term> or tariffs have been paid to Municipality by the applicant.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_7"><num>7.</num><heading>Refund of deposit</heading><intro><p eId="sec_7__intro__p_1">A deposit paid in terms of Section 6 shall be refunded to the applicant, subject to the provisions of Section 18, only when-</p></intro><subsection eId="sec_7__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="sec_7__subsec_1__p_1">all the temporary advertisements to which the deposit relates, have been removed to the satisfaction of Municipality; or</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_7__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="sec_7__subsec_2__p_1">an application for approval has been refused by Municipality.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_8"><num>8.</num><heading>Exempted advertisements</heading><subsection eId="sec_8__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="sec_8__subsec_1__intro__p_1">The following temporary advertisements are exempted from the provisions of these by-laws:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_8__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_8__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">Applications in terms of Municipality’s town-planning scheme or other legally prescribed advertisements regarding building or similar activities where such advertisements are erected within the boundaries of the site where the activities are taking place; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_8__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_8__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">temporary advertisements which are erected in or on business premises with the previously obtained permission of the owner or tenant of the building.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="sec_8__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><intro><p eId="sec_8__subsec_2__intro__p_1">A <term refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_8__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_1">temporary advertisement</term> of a newspaper or magazine which is offered for sale to the public at a specific time, is exempted from the other provisions of these by-laws, only if such display is undertaken-</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_8__subsec_2__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_8__subsec_2__para_a__p_1">on a stand or container, or place previously approved by Municipality; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_8__subsec_2__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_8__subsec_2__para_b__p_1">the sign only shows headlines of the newspaper or magazine concerned.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="sec_8__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="sec_8__subsec_3__p_1">The Municipality may, in its sole discretion, in writing deviate from or grant an exemption in respect of one or more of the provisions of these by-laws after an application in writing has been received for such exemption and it shall be lawful for the Municipality to impose such conditions as it may deem fit in granting such exemption.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_9"><num>9.</num><heading>Prohibited advertisements</heading><subsection eId="sec_9__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="sec_9__subsec_1__intro__p_1">No <term refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_9__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_1">temporary advertisement</term> which, in the opinion of Municipality-</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_9__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">is suggestive of anything indecent or which may prejudice the public morals;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_9__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">is blasphemous or offensive to the religious convictions or feelings of any inhabitant of the municipal area;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_9__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">brings any section of the inhabitants of the municipal area into ridicule or contempt;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_9__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">is harmful to the relations between persons or groups of persons;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_9__subsec_1__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_1__para_e__p_1">is prejudicial to the safety, general public welfare or the peace or the good order; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_9__subsec_1__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_1__para_f__p_1">is repugnant with any other law,</p></content></paragraph><wrapUp><p eId="sec_9__subsec_1__wrapup__p_1">shall be displayed or distributed in any form whatsoever.</p></wrapUp></subsection></section><section eId="sec_10"><num>10.</num><heading>General requirements regarding temporary advertisements</heading><subsection eId="sec_10__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="sec_10__subsec_1__p_1">No <term refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_10__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">temporary advertisement</term> shall be placed in such a position or be attached in such a manner that it may, in the discretion of the Municipality, be dangerous to vehicular traffic or pedestrians in a <term refersTo="#term-street" eId="sec_10__subsec_1__p_1__term_2">street</term> or in any other <term refersTo="#term-public_place" eId="sec_10__subsec_1__p_1__term_3">public place</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_10__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="sec_10__subsec_2__p_1">Every <term refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_10__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">temporary advertisement</term> shall be maintained by the owner or applicant in a good and safe condition at all times and to the satisfaction of Municipality.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_10__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="sec_10__subsec_3__p_1">No <term refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_10__subsec_3__p_1__term_1">temporary advertisement</term> shall be positioned in such a way that any road traffic sign or robot shall be obscured thereby.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_11"><num>11.</num><heading>General requirements regarding posters</heading><subsection eId="sec_11__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="sec_11__subsec_1__intro__p_1">Unless otherwise specifically specified in these by-laws, every commercial and <term refersTo="#term-non_commercial_poster" eId="sec_11__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_1">non-commercial poster</term> and <term refersTo="#term-election_material" eId="sec_11__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_2">election material</term> shall comply with the following requirements:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">The poster shall be affixed to a suitable and solid material, in such a way that it will not become totally or partially detached owing to wind or rain.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">Neither the material nor the poster itself may in extent exceed 600mm by 900mm.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">The poster shall be placed only on or against or be affixed to or against an electrical pole in a <term refersTo="#term-street" eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_c__p_1__term_1">street</term>.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">The poster shall be attached to electric poles with wire or string or any other material approved by the Municipality.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_e__p_1">The top end of all posters which are fixed to an electrical pole in a <term refersTo="#term-street" eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_e__p_1__term_1">street</term>, shall not be closer than 1,5m of the conductors.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_f__p_1">No poster shall be erected lower than 2m from ground level on <term refersTo="#term-street" eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_f__p_1__term_1">street</term> corners.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_g"><num>(g)</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_g__p_1">No poster shall be erected on or against or affixed to or against any tree, road traffic sign or robot pole.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_h"><num>(h)</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_h__p_1">No poster shall be displayed for a longer period than between fourteen days prior to the day on which the activity to which the poster relates begins to three days after the day of such activity.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_i__p_1">A sticker for control purposes shall be issued by the Municipality for each poster, excluding <term refersTo="#term-election_material" eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_i__p_1__term_1">election material</term>, and the applicant himself shall affix such sticker to each of the approved posters.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_j"><num>(j)</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_j__p_1">With the exception of <term refersTo="#term-election_material" eId="sec_11__subsec_1__para_j__p_1__term_1">election material</term>, not more than one hundred posters in respect of any meeting, event, function, activity, show, market or undertaking shall be displayed at any one particular time.</p></content></paragraph></subsection></section><section eId="sec_12"><num>12.</num><heading>Election material</heading><subsection eId="sec_12__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="sec_12__subsec_1__intro__p_1">In respect of any <term refersTo="#term-election_material" eId="sec_12__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_1">election material</term>, the following further conditions and/or requirements shall be compiled with:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_12__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><intro><p eId="sec_12__subsec_1__para_a__intro__p_1">No <term refersTo="#term-election_material" eId="sec_12__subsec_1__para_a__intro__p_1__term_1">election material</term> shall be displayed for longer than a period stretching from the announcement of the election, referendum or plebiscite to the end of the fourth day after midnight of the election day or the polling day; provided that nothing contained in this section shall have any bearing on specific <term refersTo="#term-election_material" eId="sec_12__subsec_1__para_a__intro__p_1__term_2">election material</term> regarding such election which is-</p></intro><subparagraph eId="sec_12__subsec_1__para_a__subpara_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="sec_12__subsec_1__para_a__subpara_i__p_1">displayed in or on a private motor vehicle which is parked or driven in a <term refersTo="#term-street" eId="sec_12__subsec_1__para_a__subpara_i__p_1__term_1">street</term> or in another <term refersTo="#term-public_place" eId="sec_12__subsec_1__para_a__subpara_i__p_1__term_2">public place</term>;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="sec_12__subsec_1__para_a__subpara_ii"><num>(ii)</num><content><p eId="sec_12__subsec_1__para_a__subpara_ii__p_1">erected on the premises of the polling station as determined by the Returning Officer on the day before an election, by-election, referendum or plebiscite and which is to be removed not later than the day following the election.</p></content></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="sec_12__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="sec_12__subsec_2__p_1">No. <term refersTo="#term-election_material" eId="sec_12__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">election material</term> by political parties shall be erected or affixed on the premises of a polling station at a position determined by the Returning Officer earlier than a day prior to the election day concerned and such material shall be removed on the day following the election day by political parties responsible for same.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_12__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><intro><p eId="sec_12__subsec_3__intro__p_1">Not more than the number of posters as indicated hereunder shall be displayed at any one particular time with regard to a parliamentary or municipal election, referendum or plebiscite:</p><p eId="sec_12__subsec_3__intro__p_2">Parliamentary election: 1 500 per party.</p><p eId="sec_12__subsec_3__intro__p_3">Municipal election: 300 per candidate per ward and 1 500 per party.</p><p eId="sec_12__subsec_3__intro__p_4">Referendum: 1 500 per party.</p><p eId="sec_12__subsec_3__intro__p_5">Plebiscite:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_12__subsec_3__para_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="sec_12__subsec_3__para_i__p_1">Municipal: 1500 per party.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_12__subsec_3__para_ii"><num>(ii)</num><content><p eId="sec_12__subsec_3__para_ii__p_1">Parliamentary: 1 500 per party.</p></content></paragraph></subsection></section><section eId="sec_13"><num>13.</num><heading>Banners</heading><subsection eId="sec_13__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="sec_13__subsec_1__intro__p_1">With regard to banners, the following further conditions and/or requirements shall be complied with:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">The Municipality shall from time to time determine such sites where banners may be displayed.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">Only one <term refersTo="#term-banner" eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_1">banner</term> may be displayed per determined site.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-municipality" eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_c__p_1__term_1">municipality</term> shall allocate a specific site to successful applicants for a period of seven days, provided that the period of allocations shall not overlap.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-municipality" eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_1">municipality</term> shall have the right to remove any <term refersTo="#term-banner" eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_2">banner</term> which becomes unsightly, untidy or which is torn or damaged on account of wind or for any other reason, and, as a result becomes dangerous to the public and the <term refersTo="#term-municipality" eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_3">municipality</term> shall not be obliged to refund to the applicant any tariffs paid in respect of a <term refersTo="#term-banner" eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_4">banner</term> so removed.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_e__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-banner" eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_e__p_1__term_1">banner</term> shall, in extent not exceed 1m x 8m and shall be made of a material acceptable to the <term refersTo="#term-municipality" eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_e__p_1__term_2">municipality</term>.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_f__p_1">Only one <term refersTo="#term-banner" eId="sec_13__subsec_1__para_f__p_1__term_1">banner</term> may be erected per candidate or per party during a parliamentary election, referendum or plebiscite irrespective of the number of determined sites.</p></content></paragraph></subsection></section><section eId="sec_14"><num>14.</num><heading>Aerial signs</heading><subsection eId="sec_14__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="sec_14__subsec_1__intro__p_1">With regard to aerial signs, the following further conditions and/or requirements shall be complied with:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_14__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_14__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">The mooring-ropes must be tied in such a way that no road traffic sign, surrounding construction or overhead electricity lines will be damaged or affected.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_14__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_14__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">The erection of the <term refersTo="#term-aerial_sign" eId="sec_14__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_1">aerial sign</term> shall be in the discretion of the Municipality and the Municipality shall retain the right to withdraw its permission, should the <term refersTo="#term-aerial_sign" eId="sec_14__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_2">aerial sign</term> become unsightly or untidy or dangerous to the public and request the owner or applicant to remove same, at his or her own cost, if the sign has already been erected.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_14__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_14__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">Should the owner or applicant fail or refuse to remove the <term refersTo="#term-aerial_sign" eId="sec_14__subsec_1__para_c__p_1__term_1">aerial sign</term> referred to in subsection (b) the Municipality shall be entitled to remove same and recover the cost of removal from the owner or applicant as the case may be.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_14__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_14__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">The Municipality shall not be obliged to refund to the applicant any tariffs paid in respect of an <term refersTo="#term-aerial_sign" eId="sec_14__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_1">aerial sign</term> removed in terms of this section.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_14__subsec_1__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="sec_14__subsec_1__para_e__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-aerial_sign" eId="sec_14__subsec_1__para_e__p_1__term_1">aerial sign</term> may be displayed for a maximum period of twenty one days before the date of the activity to which it relates and shall be removed within 48 hours after such activity has ended.</p></content></paragraph></subsection></section><section eId="sec_15"><num>15.</num><heading>"For Sale" and "Sold" signs</heading><subsection eId="sec_15__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="sec_15__subsec_1__intro__p_1">With regard to "For Sale" and "Sold" signs of fixed property the following further conditions and/or requirements shall be complied with:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_15__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_15__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">The sign shall, in extent, not exceed 600 mm × 450mm.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_15__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_15__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">The sign shall be erected or attached within or on the boundaries of any site or erf.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="sec_15__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="sec_15__subsec_2__p_1">The person who erects a "For Sale" and "Sold" sign on a site or erf is, notwithstanding the provisions of Section 6, exempted from the requirement relating to the obtaining of the prior written approval from Municipality in terms of these by-laws as well as from the obligation to pay any <term refersTo="#term-tariff" eId="sec_15__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">tariff</term> to the Municipality in terms of these by-laws .</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_16"><num>16.</num><heading>Directional signs</heading><subsection eId="sec_16__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="sec_16__subsec_1__intro__p_1">With regard to directional signs, the following further conditions and/or requirements shall be complied with:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_16__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_16__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">A maximum of twenty (20) directional signs in respect of any specific meeting, gathering, event, exhibition, show house or any property which is for sale or to let may be exhibited at any one time.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_16__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_16__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">No directional sign may be exhibited for more than seven days before and two days after the occurrence of the event to which it relates.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_16__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_16__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">No directional sign shall be erected in such a way that the free movement of pedestrians on a pavement may be obstructed thereby.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="sec_16__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="sec_16__subsec_2__p_1">The person who erects a directional sign is, notwithstanding the provisions of Section 6 exempted from the requirement to obtain the prior written approval of Municipality and also from the obligation to pay any tariff to the Municipality in terms of these by-laws.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_17"><num>17.</num><heading>Advertisement trailers</heading><subsection eId="sec_17__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="sec_17__subsec_1__intro__p_1">With regard to advertisement trailers, the following further conditions and/or requirements shall be complied with:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">The Municipality shall from time to time determine specific parking bays for the parking of advertisement trailers on municipal and/or private property.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-advertisement_trailer" eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_1">advertisement trailer</term> may only be parked on the designated parking bay determined by Municipality, and only one <term refersTo="#term-advertisement_trailer" eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_2">advertisement trailer</term> may be parked on one parking bay.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-advertisement_trailer" eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_c__p_1__term_1">advertisement trailer</term> may be parked on one specific parking bay for a maximum period of seven days.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-advertisement_trailer" eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_1">advertisement trailer</term> shall be properly secured in order to withstand strong winds and weather conditions.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_e__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-advertisement_trailer" eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_e__p_1__term_1">advertisement trailer</term> shall not be towed for the sole purpose of displaying the advertisement sign, which is mounted on the trailer, to the public during the movement and may only be towed to and from the designated parking bay.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_f__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-advertisement_trailer" eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_f__p_1__term_1">advertisement trailer</term> shall not be towed in any public <term refersTo="#term-street" eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_f__p_1__term_2">street</term> if, in the opinion of Municipality, it will probably or in fact cause a hindrance to or an obstruction to any traffic in such <term refersTo="#term-street" eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_f__p_1__term_3">street</term>.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_g"><num>(g)</num><content><p eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_g__p_1">The advertisement sign on an <term refersTo="#term-advertisement_trailer" eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_g__p_1__term_1">advertisement trailer</term> shall not be self illuminated.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_h"><num>(h)</num><content><p eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_h__p_1">The design and construction of any <term refersTo="#term-advertisement_trailer" eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_h__p_1__term_1">advertisement trailer</term> shall conform to the requirements of the Road Traffic Act, 1989 (<ref href="/akn/za/act/1989/29" eId="sec_17__subsec_1__para_h__p_1__ref_1">Act No. 29 of 1989</ref>), and SABS Standards for trailers.</p></content></paragraph></subsection></section><section eId="sec_18"><num>18.</num><heading>Failure to remove signs</heading><content><p eId="sec_18__p_1">Any person who, after he has displayed or caused to be displayed any <term refersTo="#term-temporary_advertisement" eId="sec_18__p_1__term_1">temporary advertisement</term>, fails to remove it or have it removed after the permission therefor has lapsed or is withdrawn in terms of these by-laws, commits an offence and, apart from any fine which he has to pay in terms of Section 21 of these by-laws, shall also forfeit the deposit paid by him to the <term refersTo="#term-municipality" eId="sec_18__p_1__term_2">municipality</term> in terms of these by-laws.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_19"><num>19.</num><heading>Damage to municipal property</heading><content><p eId="sec_19__p_1">No damage shall be caused to any tree, electrical pole or any municipal property or services as a result of the erection and or display of any temporary <term refersTo="#term-advertising" eId="sec_19__p_1__term_1">advertising</term> sign in terms of these by-laws and any person who causes such damage or negligently fails to prevent such damage from occurring shall guilty of an offence and, apart from the fine imposed upon him in terms of these by-laws, shall be responsible for the repair, at his own expense and to the satisfaction of the Municipality of such damage; provided that Municipality may repair such damage and recover the cost thereof from such person.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_20"><num>20.</num><heading>Exemption from liability</heading><content><p eId="sec_20__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-municipality" eId="sec_20__p_1__term_1">municipality</term> shall not be responsible for any loss, damage, injury or death to anything or any person in respect of any action taken by such person or the Municipality in terms of these by-laws.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_21"><num>21.</num><heading>Offences and penalties</heading><subsection eId="sec_21__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="sec_21__subsec_1__intro__p_1">Any person who:-</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_21__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_21__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">contravenes any of the provisions of these By-laws or fails to comply therewith, or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_21__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_21__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">contravenes or fails to comply with any order made hereunder or any notice served in connection herewith,</p></content></paragraph><hcontainer name="hcontainer" eId="sec_21__subsec_1__hcontainer_1"><content><p eId="sec_21__subsec_1__hcontainer_1__p_1">shall be guilty of an offence and upon conviction be liable to -</p></content></hcontainer><paragraph eId="sec_21__subsec_1__para_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="sec_21__subsec_1__para_i__p_1">a fine or imprisonment for a period not exceeding six months or to such imprisonment without the option of a fine or to both such fine and such imprisonment and,</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_21__subsec_1__para_ii"><num>(ii)</num><content><p eId="sec_21__subsec_1__para_ii__p_1">in the case of a continuing offence, to an additional fine or an additional period of imprisonment of 10 days or to such additional imprisonment without the option of a fine or to both such additional fine and imprisonment for each day on which such offence is continued and,</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_21__subsec_1__para_iii"><num>(iii)</num><content><p eId="sec_21__subsec_1__para_iii__p_1">a further amount equal to any costs and expenses found by the court to have been incurred by the <term refersTo="#term-municipality" eId="sec_21__subsec_1__para_iii__p_1__term_1">municipality</term> as a result of such contravention or failure.</p></content></paragraph></subsection></section><section eId="sec_22"><num>22.</num><heading>Repeal of By-Laws</heading><content><p eId="sec_22__p_1">Any other by-laws adopted by the <term refersTo="#term-municipality" eId="sec_22__p_1__term_1">municipality</term> or a <term refersTo="#term-municipality" eId="sec_22__p_1__term_2">municipality</term> now comprising an administrative unit of the <term refersTo="#term-municipality" eId="sec_22__p_1__term_3">municipality</term> and relating to the control of temporary advertisements are, from the date of promulgation of these by-laws, repealed.</p></content></section></body></act></akomaNtoso>