<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><act name="act"><meta><identification source="#Laws-Africa"><FRBRWork><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/ward-committees/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/ward-committees"/><FRBRalias value="Ward Committees" name="title"/><FRBRdate date="2017" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/><FRBRcountry value="za-ec443"/><FRBRsubtype value="by-law"/><FRBRnumber value="ward-committees"/></FRBRWork><FRBRExpression><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/ward-committees/eng@2017-04-24/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/ward-committees/eng@2017-04-24"/><FRBRdate date="2017-04-24" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/><FRBRlanguage language="eng"/></FRBRExpression><FRBRManifestation><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/ward-committees/eng@2017-04-24/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/ward-committees/eng@2017-04-24"/><FRBRdate date="2020-01-27" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/></FRBRManifestation></identification><publication number="3830" name="Eastern Cape Provincial Gazette" showAs="Eastern Cape Provincial Gazette" date="2017-04-24"/><references source="#Laws-Africa"><TLCOrganization showAs="Laws.Africa" eId="Laws-Africa" href="https://edit.laws.africa"/></references></meta><preface><p eId="preface__p_1">The Municipal Manager hereby publishes, in terms of Section 13 of the Local Government Municipal Systems Act, 2000 (<ref href="/akn/za/act/2000/32" eId="preface__p_1__ref_1">Act 32 of 2000</ref>) read with Section 162 of the <ref href="/akn/za/act/1996/constitution" eId="preface__p_1__ref_2">Constitution of the Republic of South Africa Act 1996</ref> (<ref href="/akn/za/act/1996/constitution" eId="preface__p_1__ref_3">Act 108 of 1996</ref>) the By-Laws Relating to Ward Committees which shall come into operation on the date of publication thereof.</p></preface><body><section eId="sec_1"><num>1.</num><heading>Definition</heading><content><p eId="sec_1__p_1">Any word or phrase in this notice shall have the same meaning assigned to it in the Local Government: Municipal Structures Act, <ref href="/akn/za/act/1998/117" eId="sec_1__p_1__ref_1">Act 117 of 1998</ref>.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_2"><num>2.</num><heading>Preamble</heading><content><p eId="sec_2__p_1">AND WHEREAS the Municipal Structures <ref href="/akn/za/act/1998/117" eId="sec_2__p_1__ref_1">Act, No. 117 of 1998</ref>, was enacted by parliament of the Republic of South Africa on the 18th December 1998 to provide for the establishment of Municipalities in accordance with the requirements relating to categories and types of Municipalities, to establish criteria for determining the category of Municipalities to be established in an area, to define the types of Municipalities that may be established in an area, to define the types of Municipalities that may be established within each category, to provide for appropriate electoral systems, and to provide for matters connected therewith.</p><p eId="sec_2__p_2">AND WHEREAS the aforementioned Act makes provision for the establishment of Ward Committees.</p><p eId="sec_2__p_3">AND WHEREAS the Mbizana Municipality is obliged, in terms of its founding proclamation promulgated in terms of Section 12 of the aforementioned Act to establish Ward Committees in all its Wards.</p><p eId="sec_2__p_4">This notice shall serve as an Establishment Notice for Ward Committees in the Mbizana Local Municipality.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_3"><num>3.</num><heading>Provisions of the Act</heading><content><p eId="sec_3__p_1">This notice is published pursuant to the provision of Section 72 (1) of the Local Government: Structures Act, 1998 which provides that only metropolitan and Local Municipalities of the types mentioned in Section 8 (c), (d), (g) and 9 (b), (d) and (f) of the Act may have Ward Committees, the object of which is to enhance participatory democracy in local government</p></content></section><section eId="sec_4"><num>4.</num><heading>Establishment Notice</heading><subsection eId="sec_4__subsec_4-1"><num>4.1</num><content><p eId="sec_4__subsec_4-1__p_1">To provide for the establishment of _______ Wards, from Ward 1 to ____ within the Municipality of Mbizana.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_4__subsec_4-2"><num>4.2</num><content><p eId="sec_4__subsec_4-2__p_1">The established Ward Committees will serve as legally constituted, specialist consultative bodies within each ward in the Municipality of Mbizana.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_5"><num>5.</num><heading>Functions and powers of ward committees</heading><intro><p eId="sec_5__intro__p_1">The functions and powers of Ward Committees shall be as follows:</p></intro><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_5-1"><num>5.1</num><intro><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5-1__intro__p_1">Subject to the provisions of Section 74 of Local Government: Municipal Structures Act, 1998, Ward Committees may make recommendation on any matter including but not limited to matters identified in Section 156 of the Constitution affecting their wards:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_5__subsec_5-1__para_5-1-1"><num>5.1.1</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5-1__para_5-1-1__p_1">to their respective Ward Councillors;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_5__subsec_5-1__para_5-1-2"><num>5.1.2</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5-1__para_5-1-2__p_1">through their respective Ward Councillors to the Council of the municipality or any duly authorised Committee or office bearer thereof.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_5-2"><num>5.2</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5-2__p_1">To encourage and promote the Masakhane campaign in their Wards.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_5-3"><num>5.3</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5-3__p_1">To deliminate and chair zonal meetings.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_5-4"><num>5.4</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5-4__p_1">To co-ordinate the work of community development forums.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_5-5"><num>5.5</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5-5__p_1">To create a functional communication channel and co-operative partnership between the Municipality and the community within their Wards.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_5-6"><num>5.6</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5-6__p_1">To ensure contact between the Municipality and community through the use of ward residents’ and zonal meetings.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_5-7"><num>5.7</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5-7__p_1">To encourage and recommend best measures for the improvement of municipal services and the payment of service charges.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_5-8"><num>5.8</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5-8__p_1">To educate residents about municipal property in Wards.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_5-9"><num>5.9</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5-9__p_1">To create harmonious relationships between residents of a Ward, Ward Councillors, geographic communities and the Municipality.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_5-10"><num>5.10</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5-10__p_1">To facilitate public participation in the process of drafting Integrated Development Plans and the Land Development Objectives of the Municipality.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_5-11"><num>5.11</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5-11__p_1">To act as advisory bodies on the implementation of Council policies affecting Wards.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_5-12"><num>5.12</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5-12__p_1">To serve as official specialised participatory structures of the Municipality.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_5-13"><num>5.13</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5-13__p_1">To receive and record complaints from communities within Wards and provide feedback on Council's responses thereto.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_5-14"><num>5.14</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5-14__p_1">To execute such other functions as may be delegated to them by the Municipality from time to time in terms of Section 32 (1) (a) (iv) of the Local Government: Municipal Structures Act, 1998 with the object of enhancing participatory democracy in the municipality.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_6"><num>6.</num><heading>Functions of the Municipality</heading><intro><p eId="sec_6__intro__p_1">The Council of the Municipality:</p></intro><subsection eId="sec_6__subsec_6-1"><num>6.1</num><content><p eId="sec_6__subsec_6-1__p_1">Shall make administrative arrangements including the provision of a secretariat or secretariats where necessary to enable Ward Committees to perform their functions and exercise their powers efficiently and effectively.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_6__subsec_6-2"><num>6.2</num><content><p eId="sec_6__subsec_6-2__p_1">Will be politically and administratively accountable through the Mayor for the smooth functioning of Ward Committees in conjunction with Ward Councillor and the secretariat of such Committees.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_6__subsec_6-3"><num>6.3</num><content><p eId="sec_6__subsec_6-3__p_1">Will assist a Ward Committee secretariat or secretariats with meeting venues and other logistics as may be required from time to time.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_6__subsec_6-4"><num>6.4</num><content><p eId="sec_6__subsec_6-4__p_1">Will provide members of Ward Committees and a Ward Committee secretariat or secretariats with adequate stationery and office equipment to enable them to perform their duties efficiently and effectively and to ensure proper minute and record keeping.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_6__subsec_6-5"><num>6.5</num><content><p eId="sec_6__subsec_6-5__p_1">Will be responsible for the administration of elections and by-elections for members of Ward Committees.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_7"><num>7.</num><heading>Application of rules</heading><intro><p eId="sec_7__intro__p_1">In terms of Section 73 (3) (a) of the Local Government: Municipal Structures Act, the Municipality must make rules regulating the procedure to elect members of a Ward Committee taking into account the need-</p><p eId="sec_7__intro__p_2">- for women to be equitably represented in a Ward Committee; and</p><p eId="sec_7__intro__p_3">- for a diversity of interests in a Ward to be represented on a Ward Committee-</p><p eId="sec_7__intro__p_4">and to this end-</p></intro><subsection eId="sec_7__subsec_7-1"><num>7.1</num><content><p eId="sec_7__subsec_7-1__p_1">The Council shall, by resolution, but subject to Clause 8 and after consultation with Ward Councillors determine the interest groups who qualify for representation in Ward Committees.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_7__subsec_7-1_2"><num>7.1</num><content><p eId="sec_7__subsec_7-1_2__p_1">The Ward Councillor after discussion with the Mayor, Municipal Manager and the official responsible for Ward Committees, shall cause to be published a notice in the local press calling upon various interest groups recognised by the Council in Wards to forward their nominations for members of Ward Committees to the Municipal Manager on the prescribed form within a period of fourteen days from the date of first publication of the notice.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_7__subsec_7-2"><num>7.2</num><content><p eId="sec_7__subsec_7-2__p_1">Within 21 days after expiry of the period referred to in Clause 7.1, the Ward Councillor shall call a general meeting of all residents registered as voters in a Ward for which he or she has been elected for the purpose of electing by majority vote of all such registered voters present at such meeting, the nominees who will represent the various interest groups in Ward Committees.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_7__subsec_7-3"><num>7.3</num><content><p eId="sec_7__subsec_7-3__p_1">An elected nominee shall confirm his/her availability to serve in a Ward Committee by signing an approved acceptance of form.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_7__subsec_7-4"><num>7.4</num><content><p eId="sec_7__subsec_7-4__p_1">The Ward Councillor shall preside over the meeting referred to in Clause 7.2 above.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_7__subsec_7-5"><num>7.5</num><content><p eId="sec_7__subsec_7-5__p_1">Upon being elected a Member of a Ward Committee, each member shall be given a copy of the Code of Conduct for Councillors contained in Schedule 1 of the Municipal Systems Act 2000 and shall sign a declaration to the effect that he understands its contents and agrees to be bound by its provisions.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_8"><num>8.</num><heading>Composition of Ward Committees</heading><subsection eId="sec_8__subsec_8-1"><num>8.1</num><content><p eId="sec_8__subsec_8-1__p_1">Representation on Ward Committees shall not be according to party political affiliation and shall include religious, youth, civic, education, sport, culture, business, welfare and women's organisations.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_8__subsec_8-2"><num>8.2</num><content><p eId="sec_8__subsec_8-2__p_1">In areas where there are many similar interest groups, a need may exist to cluster them in order to ensure the broadest representation in Ward Committees.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_8__subsec_8-3"><num>8.3</num><content><p eId="sec_8__subsec_8-3__p_1">Ward Committees may form sub-committees in accordance with the Committees of Council or as their local circumstances may require.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_9"><num>9.</num><heading>Meeting Procedures</heading><subsection eId="sec_9__subsec_9-1"><num>9.1</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-1__p_1">The members of the Ward Committee shall meet at least once per quarter and shall report details of their activities and their recommendations on matters referred to them to the Municipal Manager through their Ward Councillor at least quarterly or when required by the Municipal Manager.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_9__subsec_9-2"><num>9.2</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-2__p_1">A Ward Councillor shall chair meetings of the Ward Committee for which he or she is responsible.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_9__subsec_9-3"><num>9.3</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-3__p_1">In the event where a Ward Councillor is not available to chair a meeting of a Ward Committee, the Committee shall nominate from amongst its members an interim chairperson for the particular meeting.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_9__subsec_9-4"><num>9.4</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-4__p_1">The Ward Committees shall elect its secretary from among its members and such secretary shall keep records of documents, agenda and minutes, consult with the Ward Councillor, call Ward Committee and Ward Residents’ meetings provided that the Council may, itself, provide secretarial services to Ward Committees.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_9__subsec_9-5"><num>9.5</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-5__p_1">A member who is absent from three consecutive meetings without first obtaining leave of absence from a Ward Committee shall be disqualified as a member thereof.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6"><num>9.6</num><intro><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__intro__p_1">The Order of business at and quorum for meetings of Ward Committees shall be as follows:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_a__p_1">Opening.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_b__p_1">Applications for leave of absence.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_c__p_1">Minutes of the previous meeting.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_d__p_1">Reports of the members.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_e__p_1">Reports of the chairperson.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_f__p_1">Reports of the Municipal Manager</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_g"><num>(g)</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_g__p_1">Future course of action.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_h"><num>(h)</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_h__p_1">Date of next meeting.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-6__para_i__p_1">Closure</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="sec_9__subsec_9-7"><num>9.7</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-7__p_1">All decisions of Ward Committee shall be adopted by a majority vote of the members present.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_9__subsec_9-8"><num>9.8</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-8__p_1">The quorum for a meeting a Ward Committee shall be a majority of its members. The Chairperson of a Committee shall not, however, be regarded as a member of a Ward Committee for the purpose of determining a quorum.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_9__subsec_9-9"><num>9.9</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-9__p_1">All matters requiring a decision or recommendation from a Ward Committee will be referred to the Secretariat thereof in writing by the Municipal Manager or his/her nominee.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_9__subsec_9-10"><num>9.10</num><content><p eId="sec_9__subsec_9-10__p_1">Meetings of Ward Committees shall, with the necessary adjustments, be conducted in accordance with the Standing Rules of Order adopted by the Council.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_10"><num>10.</num><heading>Term of Office of Members</heading><subsection eId="sec_10__subsec_10-1"><num>10.1</num><content><p eId="sec_10__subsec_10-1__p_1">The term of office of a member of a Ward Committee shall be a period of two years.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_10__subsec_10-2"><num>10.2</num><content><p eId="sec_10__subsec_10-2__p_1">The Council may after consultation with community organisations and interest groups represented in Ward Committee, extend the period of office of Ward Committees for such period as the Council may determine, provided that such period shall not exceed the period of office of the Council itself.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_11"><num>11.</num><heading>Vacancies</heading><subsection eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1"><num>11.1</num><intro><p eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1__intro__p_1">A vacancy in a Ward Committee shall arise if a member thereof:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1__para_11-1-1"><num>11.1.1</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1__para_11-1-1__p_1">Dies.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1__para_11-1-2"><num>11.1.2</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1__para_11-1-2__p_1">Is dismissed in accordance with the resolution of the Ward Committee or by the Mayor in consultation with the Ward Councillor on the grounds that such member has contravened the Code of Conduct for Councillors contained in Schedule 1 of the Municipal Systems Act 2000 provided that, before dismissing a member of a Ward Committee in terms of this Clause, a fair hearing complying with the rules of natural justice shall be held in connection with the alleged misconduct.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1__para_11-1-3"><num>11.1.3</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1__para_11-1-3__p_1">Ceases to be a member of the organisation he/she represents.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1__para_11-1-4"><num>11.1.4</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1__para_11-1-4__p_1">Is insolvent or declared mentally incompetent.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1__para_11-1-5"><num>11.1.5</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1__para_11-1-5__p_1">Fails to attend three (3) consecutive meetings of a Ward Committee or any sub-committee of which he may be member.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1__para_11-1-6"><num>11.1.6</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1__para_11-1-6__p_1">Resigns.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1__para_11-1-7"><num>11.1.7</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1__para_11-1-7__p_1">Is no longer a resident of a particular Ward, the interests of which he or she was nominated to serve.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1__para_11-1-8"><num>11.1.8</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_11-1__para_11-1-8__p_1">Is elected/nominated as a Councillor.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="sec_11__subsec_11-2"><num>11.2</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_11-2__p_1">Whenever a vacancy in the Ward Committee arises, the Secretary of the relevant Ward Committee shall report the circumstances thereof to the relevant Ward Committee which shall, through its Chairperson report same to the Mayor.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_11__subsec_11-3"><num>11.3</num><content><p eId="sec_11__subsec_11-3__p_1">If a vacancy arises in the Committee, a by-election shall be held to fill such vacancy and the procedures referred to in Section 7 shall be followed with regard to the filling of such vacancy.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_12"><num>12.</num><heading>Dissolution</heading><subsection eId="sec_12__subsec_12-1"><num>12.1</num><intro><p eId="sec_12__subsec_12-1__intro__p_1">A Ward Committee may be dissolved by the Council under the following circumstances:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_12__subsec_12-1__para_12-1-1"><num>12.1.1</num><content><p eId="sec_12__subsec_12-1__para_12-1-1__p_1">When the Ward Councillor for the responsible ward dies or is disqualified in terms of any law to be a Councillor.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_12__subsec_12-1__para_12-1-2"><num>12.1.2</num><content><p eId="sec_12__subsec_12-1__para_12-1-2__p_1">When it has exceeded its authority or acted ultra vires its functions and powers.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_12__subsec_12-1__para_12-1-3"><num>12.1.3</num><content><p eId="sec_12__subsec_12-1__para_12-1-3__p_1">When it seeks to prescribe to a Ward Councillor how to perform his or her functions.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_12__subsec_12-1__para_12-1-4"><num>12.1.4</num><content><p eId="sec_12__subsec_12-1__para_12-1-4__p_1">When it fails to meet three (3) consecutive times.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_12__subsec_12-1__para_12-1-5"><num>12.1.5</num><content><p eId="sec_12__subsec_12-1__para_12-1-5__p_1">When members thereof decide to dissolve.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_12__subsec_12-1__para_12-1-6"><num>12.1.6</num><content><p eId="sec_12__subsec_12-1__para_12-1-6__p_1">When there are, on reasonable grounds, allegations of misrepresentation, corruption, and dishonesty against a Ward Committee which, if proven, will bring the Municipality in disrepute or is likely to bring the Municipality into disrepute and the Council decides, upon the recommendation of the Mayor and after consultation with the Ward Councillor, that it would be in the interests of the Council to dissolve such Committee.</p></content></paragraph></subsection></section><section eId="sec_13"><num>13.</num><heading>Remuneration</heading><subsection eId="sec_13__subsec_13-1"><num>13.1</num><content><p eId="sec_13__subsec_13-1__p_1">Subject to national legislation, no remuneration is payable to members of Ward Committee for the attendance by them of meeting of Ward Committees.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_13__subsec_13-2"><num>13.2</num><content><p eId="sec_13__subsec_13-2__p_1">The council may reimburse members of Ward Committees for travel costs and other out-of-pocket expenses incurred by them in connection with the performance of their duties and obligations provided that proof of such expenditure is submitted to the satisfaction of the Council.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_14"><num>14.</num><heading>Overall responsibility for Ward Committees</heading><subsection eId="sec_14__subsec_14-1"><num>14.1</num><content><p eId="sec_14__subsec_14-1__p_1">The Mayor shall be responsible for the overall functioning of Ward Committees and shall at least once per quarter hold a meeting with all Ward Councillors in order to discuss matters of common concern affecting Wards and the problems being experienced by Ward Committees.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_14__subsec_14-2"><num>14.2</num><content><p eId="sec_14__subsec_14-2__p_1">The Mayor shall on a 6 monthly basis submit a written report to the Council on the activities of Ward Committees, the general matters being considered by them, their recommendations concerning Council policies, any problems they are experiencing, recommendations to resolve such problems and any other incidental matters.</p></content></subsection></section></body></act></akomaNtoso>