<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><act name="act"><meta><identification source="#Laws-Africa"><FRBRWork><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-cpt/act/by-law/2021/nature-reserve/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-cpt/act/by-law/2021/nature-reserve"/><FRBRalias value="Nature Reserve By-law" name="title"/><FRBRdate date="2021" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/><FRBRcountry value="za-cpt"/><FRBRsubtype value="by-law"/><FRBRnumber value="nature-reserve"/></FRBRWork><FRBRExpression><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-cpt/act/by-law/2021/nature-reserve/eng@2021-02-18/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-cpt/act/by-law/2021/nature-reserve/eng@2021-02-18"/><FRBRdate date="2021-02-18" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/><FRBRlanguage language="eng"/></FRBRExpression><FRBRManifestation><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-cpt/act/by-law/2021/nature-reserve/eng@2021-02-18/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-cpt/act/by-law/2021/nature-reserve/eng@2021-02-18"/><FRBRdate date="2021-11-06" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/></FRBRManifestation></identification><publication showAs="Western Cape Provincial Gazette" name="Western Cape Provincial Gazette" date="2021-02-18" number="8387"/><references source="#Laws-Africa"><TLCOrganization eId="Laws-Africa" href="https://edit.laws.africa" showAs="Laws.Africa"/></references></meta><preface><longTitle eId="preface__longTitle_1"><p eId="preface__longTitle_1__p_1">To regulate the management, use, activities and access to nature reserves within the jurisdiction of the City of Cape Town; to engage user groups and stakeholders in a formalised manner; to provide for safe and environmentally sensitive recreation; and to provide for matters incidental thereto.</p></longTitle></preface><preamble><p eId="preamble__p_1">WHEREAS the City is the designated management authority, appointed by the MEC, for nature reserves declared in terms of Section 23 of the National Environmental Management: Protected Areas Act, 2003 (<ref href="/akn/za/act/2003/57" eId="preamble__p_1__ref_1">Act No. 57 of 2003</ref>).</p><p eId="preamble__p_2">AND WHEREAS section 156(2) and (5) of the <ref href="/akn/za/act/1996/constitution" eId="preamble__p_2__ref_1">Constitution of the Republic of South Africa, 1996</ref> provides that a municipality may make and administer By-laws for the effective administration of the matters which it has the right to administer, and to exercise any power concerning a matter reasonably necessary for, or incidental to, the effective performance of its functions;</p><p eId="preamble__p_3">WHEREAS Part B of Schedule 5 to the <ref href="/akn/za/act/1996/constitution" eId="preamble__p_3__ref_1">Constitution of the Republic of South Africa, 1996</ref> lists local amenities and municipal parks and recreation as local government matters to the extent set out in section 155(6) (a) and 155(7);</p><p eId="preamble__p_4">AND WHEREAS the City of Cape Town has a responsibility in terms of the <ref href="/akn/za/act/1996/constitution" eId="preamble__p_4__ref_1">Constitution of the Republic of South Africa, 1996</ref> and the National Environmental Management: Protected Areas Act, 2003 (<ref href="/akn/za/act/2003/57" eId="preamble__p_4__ref_2">Act No. 57 of 2003</ref>) to manage, and control the use of, nature reserves within the jurisdiction of the City of Cape Town for which the City is the designated management authority.</p><p eId="preamble__p_5">AND NOW THEREFORE, BE IT ENACTED by the Council of the City of Cape Town, as follows:—</p></preamble><body><chapter eId="chp_1"><num>1</num><heading>Introductory provisions</heading><section eId="chp_1__sec_1"><num>1.</num><heading>Definitions</heading><content><p eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_1">In this By-law, unless the context indicates otherwise—</p><p refersTo="#term-aircraft" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_2">“<def refersTo="#term-aircraft" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_2__def_1">aircraft</def>” means any object driven or propelled, or which glides on or over the surface of a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_2__term_1">nature reserve</term>, wholly or partly by mechanical or electrical power, in order to move through the airspace above a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_2__term_2">nature reserve</term>.</p><p refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_3">“<def refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_3__def_1">animal</def>” means any organism whose taxonomical classification belongs to the kingdom ANIMALIA.</p><p refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_4">“<def refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_4__def_1">authorised official</def>” means an employee of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_4__term_1">City</term> responsible for carrying out any duty or function or exercising any power in terms of this By-law and includes employees delegated to carry out or exercise such duties, functions or powers.</p><p refersTo="#term-the_Act" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_5">“<def refersTo="#term-the_Act" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_5__def_1">the Act</def>” means the National Environmental Management: Protected Areas Act, 2003 (<ref href="/akn/za/act/2003/57" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_5__ref_1">Act No. 57 of 2003</ref>).</p><blockList refersTo="#term-biological_resource" eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_1"><listIntroduction eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_1__intro_1">“<def refersTo="#term-biological_resource" eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_1__intro_1__def_1">biological resource</def>” means any resource consisting of;</listIntroduction><item eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_1__item_a"><num>(a)</num><p eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_1__item_a__p_1">a living or dead <term refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_1__item_a__p_1__term_1">animal</term>, plant or other organism of an indigenous <term refersTo="#term-species" eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_1__item_a__p_1__term_2">species</term>;</p></item><item eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_1__item_b"><num>(b)</num><p eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_1__item_b__p_1">a derivative of such an <term refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_1__item_b__p_1__term_1">animal</term>, plant or other organism, as defined in section 1 of the Biodiversity Act or</p></item><item eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_1__item_c"><num>(c)</num><p eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_1__item_c__p_1">any genetic material of such <term refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_1__item_c__p_1__term_1">animal</term>, plant or other organism, as defined in section 1 of the Biodiversity Act;</p></item></blockList><p refersTo="#term-bioprospecting" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_6">“<def refersTo="#term-bioprospecting" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_6__def_1">bioprospecting</def>” has the meaning assigned to it in section 1 of the Biodiversity Act;</p><p refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_7">“<def refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_7__def_1">City</def>” means the City of Cape Town, a municipality established by the City of Cape Town Establishment Notice No. 479 of 22 September 2000, issued in terms of the Local Government: Municipal Structures Act, 1998 (<ref href="/akn/za/act/1998/117" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_7__ref_1">Act No. 117 of 1998</ref>), or any structure or employee of the City acting in terms of delegated authority;</p><p refersTo="#term-code_of_conduct" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_8">“<def refersTo="#term-code_of_conduct" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_8__def_1">code of conduct</def>” means a written set of specific rules for the use of a specific <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_8__term_1">nature reserve</term> by users which are not contrary to this By-law;</p><p refersTo="#term-domestic_animal" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_9">“<def refersTo="#term-domestic_animal" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_9__def_1">domestic animal</def>” means any horse, pony, mule, donkey, cattle, pig, sheep, goat, camel, reptile, dog, cat, rabbit, and any other livestock, exotic <term refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_9__term_1">animal</term> or pet;</p><p refersTo="#term-management_plan" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_10">“<def refersTo="#term-management_plan" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_10__def_1">management plan</def>” means a plan drafted and submitted to the MEC in compliance with Section 39(2) of <term refersTo="#term-the_Act" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_10__term_1">the Act</term>.</p><p refersTo="#term-model_aircraft" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_11">“<def refersTo="#term-model_aircraft" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_11__def_1">model aircraft</def>” means any miniature <term refersTo="#term-aircraft" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_11__term_1">aircraft</term> not capable of or intended for the conveying of persons, which is controlled from a remote location and includes recreational/toy drones;</p><p refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_12">“<def refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_12__def_1">nature reserve</def>” means an area proclaimed, protected or published in any government or provincial gazette in terms of any law for the purposes of nature conservation in the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_12__term_1">City</term>, and which is managed by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_12__term_2">City</term> or designated management authority where there is a co-management agreement in place;</p><p refersTo="#term-nature_area" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_13">“<def refersTo="#term-nature_area" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_13__def_1">nature area</def>” means any area set aside, un-proclaimed, and managed as a nature area for nature conservation objectives by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_13__term_1">City</term> or landowner where there is a co-management agreement in place.</p><p refersTo="#term-NEMA" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_14">“<def refersTo="#term-NEMA" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_14__def_1">NEMA</def>” means the National Environmental Management Act, 1998 (<ref href="/akn/za/act/1998/107" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_14__ref_1">Act 107 of 1998</ref>).</p><p refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_15">“<def refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_15__def_1">notice</def>” includes a written notification or prohibition, determined by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_15__term_1">City</term>, being prominently displayed in writing, optionally combined with the use of pictograms, or a notice board erected at or near a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_15__term_2">nature reserve</term> point of entry or exit, and “notify” shall have a corresponding meaning;</p><p refersTo="#term-nuisance" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_16">“<def refersTo="#term-nuisance" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_16__def_1">nuisance</def>” means any act, omission or condition which is offensive, injurious or dangerous to health, or which materially interferes with the ordinary comfort, safety, convenience, peace or quiet of any user of a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_16__term_1">nature reserve</term> or amenity connected therewith;</p><p refersTo="#term-open_access_areas" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_17">“<def refersTo="#term-open_access_areas" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_17__def_1">open access areas</def>” means a portion of a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_17__term_1">nature reserve</term> which can be entered and traversed by any means where entry to such portion of the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_17__term_2">nature reserve</term> is not restricted or controlled by any access point or gate;</p><p refersTo="#term-operating_times" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_18">“<def refersTo="#term-operating_times" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_18__def_1">operating times</def>” means the period of time between and including the opening time and closing time of a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_18__term_1">nature reserve</term> as depicted on a <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_18__term_2">notice</term> board;</p><p refersTo="#term-overnight" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_19">“<def refersTo="#term-overnight" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_19__def_1">overnight</def>” means to be present and includes camping in designated areas in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_19__term_1">nature reserve</term> between sunset and sunrise;</p><p refersTo="#term-pick" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_20">“<def refersTo="#term-pick" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_20__def_1">pick</def>” includes cut, chop off, take, gather, pluck, uproot, break, damage or destroy;</p><p refersTo="#term-Protected_Area_Advisory_Committee" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_21">“<def refersTo="#term-Protected_Area_Advisory_Committee" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_21__def_1">Protected Area Advisory Committee</def>” (“PAAC”) means a committee established in terms of the Regulations for the Proper Administration of Nature Reserves (<i>Government Gazette</i> No. 35021, GNR. 99 of 8 February 2012) made in terms of <term refersTo="#term-the_Act" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_21__term_1">the Act</term>.</p><p refersTo="#term-recreational_area" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_22">“<def refersTo="#term-recreational_area" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_22__def_1">recreational area</def>” means any area set aside in terms of the <term refersTo="#term-management_plan" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_22__term_1">management plan</term> for general or specific recreational use by the public inside a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_22__term_2">nature reserve</term>;</p><p refersTo="#term-recreational_water" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_23">“<def refersTo="#term-recreational_water" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_23__def_1">recreational water</def>” means any inland water body, lake, river, stream, wetland, vlei, dam, estuary or portion thereof, which is owned or managed by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_23__term_1">City</term>, and includes the verges or banks of such areas, against which water may tidally, periodically or seasonally rise, and which is also owned or managed by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_23__term_2">City</term>;</p><p refersTo="#term-Remotely_piloted_aircraft_system" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_24">“<def refersTo="#term-Remotely_piloted_aircraft_system" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_24__def_1">Remotely piloted aircraft system</def>” (RPAS) means an unmanned <term refersTo="#term-aircraft" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_24__term_1">aircraft</term> which is piloted from a remote pilot station and includes the RPAS commonly referred to as drones.</p><p refersTo="#term-safety_officer" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_25">“<def refersTo="#term-safety_officer" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_25__def_1">safety officer</def>” means a person not employed by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_25__term_1">City</term>, who is nominated and appointed in terms of <ref href="#chp_2__sec_5" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_25__ref_1">section 5</ref> to perform certain functions on a voluntary basis;</p><p refersTo="#term-species" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_26">“<def refersTo="#term-species" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_26__def_1">species</def>” means a kind of <term refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_26__term_1">animal</term>, plant or other organism that does not normally interbreed with individuals of another kind, and includes any subspecies, cultivar, variety, geographic race, strain, hybrid or geographically separate population;</p><blockList refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2"><listIntroduction eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__intro_1">“<def refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__intro_1__def_1">specimen</def>” means—</listIntroduction><item eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_a"><num>(a)</num><p eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_a__p_1">any living or dead <term refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_a__p_1__term_1">animal</term>, plant or other organism;</p></item><item eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_b"><num>(b)</num><p eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_b__p_1">a seed, egg, gamete or propagule or part of an <term refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_b__p_1__term_1">animal</term>, plant or other organism capable of propagation or reproduction or in any way transferring genetic traits;</p></item><item eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_c"><num>(c)</num><p eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_c__p_1">any derivative of any <term refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_c__p_1__term_1">animal</term>, plant or other organism; or</p></item><item eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_d"><num>(d)</num><blockList eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_d__list_1"><listIntroduction eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_d__list_1__intro_1">any goods which—</listIntroduction><item eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_d__list_1__item_i"><num>(i)</num><p eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_d__list_1__item_i__p_1">contain a derivative of an <term refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_d__list_1__item_i__p_1__term_1">animal</term>, plant or other organism; or</p></item><item eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_d__list_1__item_ii"><num>(ii)</num><p eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_d__list_1__item_ii__p_1">from an accompanying document, from the packaging or mark or label, or from any other indications, appear to be or to contain a derivative of an <term refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_1__sec_1__list_2__item_d__list_1__item_ii__p_1__term_1">animal</term>, plant or other organism;</p></item></blockList></item></blockList><p refersTo="#term-stormwater_system" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_27">“<def refersTo="#term-stormwater_system" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_27__def_1">stormwater system</def>” means both the constructed and natural facilities, including pipes, culverts, watercourses and their associated floodplains, whether over or under public or privately owned land used or required for the management, collection, conveyance, temporary storage, control, monitoring, treatment, use and disposal of stormwater;</p><p refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_28">“<def refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_28__def_1">vehicle</def>” means anything defined as a motor vehicle in terms of the National Road Traffic Act, 1996 (<ref href="/akn/za/act/1996/93" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_28__ref_1">Act No. 93 of 1996</ref>); or any conveyance designed or adapted principally to travel on wheels or tracks.</p><p refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_29">“<def refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_29__def_1">vessel</def>” means a power boat, electrical boat, boat, sail boat, windsurfing board, kitesurfing board and any manner of canoe or paddle boat, including any flotation device that can be stood on, sat on or in, irrespective of whether it is powered by mechanical, electrical or manual means;</p><p refersTo="#term-water_area" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_30">“<def refersTo="#term-water_area" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_30__def_1">water area</def>” means the water and the bottom or floor of any tidal lagoon, natural lake, tidal river, river or stream, dam, impoundment or wetland or any part thereof, situated within a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_30__term_1">nature reserve</term>, and includes the water and the land between the lowest line and the highest line to which the water-level of such a tidal lagoon, natural lake, tidal river, river or stream, dam, impoundment or wetland or any part thereof may recede or rise at any time;</p><p refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_31">“<def refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_31__def_1">written authorisation</def>” means written consent issued by an <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_31__term_1">authorised official</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_31__term_2">City</term> in terms of this By-law, and includes any permit issued in terms of <ref href="#chp_4__sec_15" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_31__ref_1">Section 15</ref>(1) or identification card issued in terms of <ref href="#chp_2__sec_5" eId="chp_1__sec_1__p_31__ref_2">Section 5</ref> (5).</p></content></section><section eId="chp_1__sec_2"><num>2.</num><heading>Application</heading><intro><p eId="chp_1__sec_2__intro__p_1">This By-law applies to any area which is—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_1__sec_2__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_1__sec_2__para_a__p_1">proclaimed or recognised as a protected area in terms of <term refersTo="#term-the_Act" eId="chp_1__sec_2__para_a__p_1__term_1">the Act</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_1__sec_2__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_1__sec_2__para_b__p_1">managed as a <term refersTo="#term-nature_area" eId="chp_1__sec_2__para_b__p_1__term_1">nature area</term> with an <i>in perpetuity</i> agreement with the landowner and registered against the title deeds, or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_1__sec_2__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_1__sec_2__para_c__p_1">land acquired by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_1__sec_2__para_c__p_1__term_1">City</term> for the express purposes of nature conservation and where such intent is adopted through a Council resolution.</p></content></paragraph></section></chapter><chapter eId="chp_2"><num>2</num><heading>Powers and responsibilities of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__term_1">City</term></heading><section eId="chp_2__sec_3"><num>3.</num><heading>Functions</heading><intro><p eId="chp_2__sec_3__intro__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_3__intro__p_1__term_1">City</term> may in managing the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_3__intro__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term>—</p></intro><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_1__p_1">manage breeding and cultivation programmes, and may reserve areas in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> as breeding places and nurseries;</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_2__p_1">sell, exchange or donate any <term refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">animal</term>, plant or other organism occurring in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_2__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term>, or purchase, exchange or otherwise acquire any indigenous <term refersTo="#term-species" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_2__p_1__term_3">species</term> which it may consider desirable to re-introduce into a specific <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_2__p_1__term_4">nature reserve</term>;</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_3__p_1">undertake and promote research;</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_4"><num>(4)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_4__p_1">control, remove or eradicate any <term refersTo="#term-species" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_4__p_1__term_1">species</term> or specimens of <term refersTo="#term-species" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_4__p_1__term_2">species</term> which it considers undesirable to protect and conserve in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_4__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term> or that may negatively impact on the biodiversity of the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_4__p_1__term_4">nature reserve</term>;</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_5"><num>(5)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_5__p_1">carry out any development and construct or erect any infrastructure necessary for the management of a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_5__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>, subject to an environmental authorisation in terms of Section 24 of National Environmental Management Act, 1998 (<ref href="/akn/za/act/1998/107" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_5__p_1__ref_1">Act No. 107 of 1998</ref>), applicable By-laws and the management plan;</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_6"><num>(6)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_6__p_1">allow visitors to a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_6__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>;</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_7"><num>(7)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_7__p_1">take reasonable steps to ensure the security and well-being of visitors and staff;</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_8"><num>(8)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_8__p_1">provide accommodation and facilities for visitors and staff, including the provision of food and household supplies;</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_9"><num>(9)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_9__p_1">carry on any business or trade or provide other services for the convenience of visitors and staff, including the sale of liquor subject to applicable laws;</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_10"><num>(10)</num><intro><p eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_10__intro__p_1">authorise any person, subject to such conditions as it may determine, to—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_10__para_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_10__para_i__p_1">carry on any business or trade, or provide any service, which the management authority may carry on or provide in terms of this section; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_10__para_ii"><num>(ii)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_10__para_ii__p_1">provide the infrastructure for such business, trade or service;</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_11"><num>(11)</num><intro><p eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_11__intro__p_1">by agreement with—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_11__para_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_11__para_i__p_1">other <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_11__para_i__p_1__term_1">City</term> Departments, provide any service in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_11__para_i__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term> for the management of the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_11__para_i__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term>, which the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_11__para_i__p_1__term_4">City</term> may be mandated to provide in terms of legislation; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_11__para_ii"><num>(ii)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_11__para_ii__p_1">any other organ of state, perform a function in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_11__para_ii__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> which that organ of state may perform in terms of legislation; or</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_12"><num>(12)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_12__p_1">issue Notices in terms of <ref href="#chp_2__sec_6" eId="chp_2__sec_3__subsec_12__p_1__ref_1">section 6</ref>.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="chp_2__sec_4"><num>4.</num><heading>Commercial, community and visitor activities</heading><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_1__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">City</term> may, in terms of the <term refersTo="#term-management_plan" eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_1__p_1__term_2">management plan</term>, set aside a part of a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_1__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term>, as an area in which a particular activity may be undertaken by visitors to the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_1__p_1__term_4">nature reserve</term>, communities or interest groups, and must display a <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_1__p_1__term_5">notice</term> at the entrance to the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_1__p_1__term_6">nature reserve</term> in which such area is described: Provided that the activity does not compromise the purpose for which the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_1__p_1__term_7">nature reserve</term> was established.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_2__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">City</term> may, in terms of the <term refersTo="#term-management_plan" eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_2__p_1__term_2">management plan</term>, set aside a part of a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_2__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term>, as an area in which a commercial activity may be undertaken by an authorised vendor, and must display a <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_2__p_1__term_4">notice</term> at the entrance to the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_2__p_1__term_5">nature reserve</term> in which such area is described and at the place the commercial activity is undertaken;</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_3__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_3__p_1__term_1">City</term> may, in consultation with PAAC’s, user or interest groups and other interested and affected parties develop codes of conduct for specific activities authorised within a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_4__subsec_3__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term>.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="chp_2__sec_5"><num>5.</num><heading>Safety officers</heading><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_1__p_1">Any recognised organisation, club or representative body that has an interest in any <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> may nominate persons to the <term refersTo="#term-Protected_Area_Advisory_Committee" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_1__p_1__term_2">Protected Area Advisory Committee</term> or the reserve manager, for consideration as safety officers.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_2__p_1">A <term refersTo="#term-Protected_Area_Advisory_Committee" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">Protected Area Advisory Committee</term> may nominate safety officers to the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_2__p_1__term_2">City</term> for a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_2__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_3__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_3__p_1__term_1">City</term> may appoint safety officers for a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_3__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term> and set in writing any prerequisites, terms, conditions or restrictions on any such appointments.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_4"><num>(4)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_4__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_4__p_1__term_1">City</term> must inform the <term refersTo="#term-Protected_Area_Advisory_Committee" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_4__p_1__term_2">Protected Area Advisory Committee</term> of any safety officers that it appoints.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_5"><num>(5)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_5__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_5__p_1__term_1">City</term> must issue any duly appointed <term refersTo="#term-safety_officer" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_5__p_1__term_2">safety officer</term> with a <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_5__p_1__term_3">written authorisation</term> and an identification card.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_6"><num>(6)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_6__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-safety_officer" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_6__p_1__term_1">safety officer</term> must when performing any responsibility with regards to this By-law have in his/her possession their identification card or <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_6__p_1__term_2">written authorisation</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_7"><num>(7)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_7__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-safety_officer" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_7__p_1__term_1">safety officer</term> may issue verbal or written instructions to visitors relating to compliance with this By-law in terms of the conditions of their <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_7__p_1__term_2">written authorisation</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_8"><num>(8)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_8__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-safety_officer" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_8__p_1__term_1">safety officer</term> may make written recommendations to the management authority regarding compliance with this By-law by user groups and visitors for further action and enforcement.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_9"><num>(9)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_9__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_9__p_1__term_1">City</term> may, upon recommendation by the relevant <term refersTo="#term-Protected_Area_Advisory_Committee" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_9__p_1__term_2">Protected Area Advisory Committee</term> or of its own accord, cancel the appointment of any <term refersTo="#term-safety_officer" eId="chp_2__sec_5__subsec_9__p_1__term_3">safety officer</term>.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="chp_2__sec_6"><num>6.</num><heading>Notices</heading><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__intro__p_1">In relation to a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>, the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_2">City</term> may from time to time and by means of a Notice displayed at the entrance to or at, other relevant places of a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term>—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">set aside any land or <term refersTo="#term-water_area" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_a__p_1__term_1">water area</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">designate any land or <term refersTo="#term-water_area" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_1">water area</term> as a <term refersTo="#term-recreational_area" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_2">recreational area</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">designate any land or <term refersTo="#term-water_area" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_c__p_1__term_1">water area</term> for a purpose other than recreation;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">prohibit or restrict the use and access of any person, <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_1">vehicle</term>, <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_2">vessel</term>, <term refersTo="#term-domestic_animal" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_3">domestic animal</term>, <term refersTo="#term-species" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_4">species</term> or <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_5">specimen</term> to any land or <term refersTo="#term-water_area" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_6">water area</term> or part thereof; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_e__p_1">designate the times and conditions during which and subject to which any sports or other activities may be practised or performed on such land or <term refersTo="#term-water_area" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_1__para_e__p_1__term_1">water area</term>.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_2__p_1">A Notice may impose conditions in relation to the participation in or undertaking of any activity in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> and the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_2__p_1__term_2">City</term> may vary or revoke a Notice at any time by a subsequent Notice.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_3__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_3__p_1__term_1">City</term> may prescribe symbols or pictograms to be used on public <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_3__p_1__term_2">notice</term> boards and these shall have the meaning prescribed in the list of approved pictograms attached as Annexure A.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_4"><num>(4)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_4__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_4__p_1__term_1">City</term> may erect public <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_4__p_1__term_2">notice</term> boards within or near the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_4__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term> to notify interested and affected parties of permissible activities and prohibitions in terms of this By-law.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_5"><num>(5)</num><intro><p eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_5__intro__p_1">In addition, the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_5__intro__p_1__term_1">City</term> may—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_5__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_5__para_a__p_1">publish or broadcast the <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_5__para_a__p_1__term_1">notice</term> in a manner that is reasonably likely to bring it to the attention of interested and affected persons;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_5__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_5__para_b__p_1">distribute copies of the <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_5__para_b__p_1__term_1">notice</term> to persons owning or occupying land in the vicinity of the affected <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_5__para_b__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term>; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_5__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_6__subsec_5__para_c__p_1">use public meetings, protected area advisory committee meetings or other means of bringing information to the attention of interested and affected persons.</p></content></paragraph></subsection></section><section eId="chp_2__sec_7"><num>7.</num><heading>Recreational areas inside nature reserves</heading><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_7__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_7__subsec_1__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_7__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">City</term> may, within a <term refersTo="#term-recreational_area" eId="chp_2__sec_7__subsec_1__p_1__term_2">recreational area</term>, display any <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_2__sec_7__subsec_1__p_1__term_3">notice</term> required under this By-law.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_2__sec_7__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><intro><p eId="chp_2__sec_7__subsec_2__intro__p_1">In relation to recreational areas, the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_2__sec_7__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_1">City</term> may prominently display a <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_2__sec_7__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_2">notice</term> at an entrance to a <term refersTo="#term-recreational_area" eId="chp_2__sec_7__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_3">recreational area</term> indicating—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_2__sec_7__subsec_2__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_7__subsec_2__para_a__p_1">the opening and closing times of that <term refersTo="#term-recreational_area" eId="chp_2__sec_7__subsec_2__para_a__p_1__term_1">recreational area</term>; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_2__sec_7__subsec_2__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_2__sec_7__subsec_2__para_b__p_1">any rules made by the management authority in relation to that <term refersTo="#term-recreational_area" eId="chp_2__sec_7__subsec_2__para_b__p_1__term_1">recreational area</term>.</p></content></paragraph></subsection></section></chapter><chapter eId="chp_3"><num>3</num><heading>The use of biological resources in nature reserves</heading><section eId="chp_3__sec_8"><num>8.</num><heading>Use of biological resources</heading><content><p eId="chp_3__sec_8__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_3__sec_8__p_1__term_1">City</term> may, upon application and subject to the provisions of a <term refersTo="#term-management_plan" eId="chp_3__sec_8__p_1__term_2">management plan</term>, by means of the granting of a non-transferable <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_3__sec_8__p_1__term_3">written authorisation</term> or the entering into of a written agreement, with the conditions it deems necessary, grant to any person the right to the sustainable, monitored use of identified biological resources in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_3__sec_8__p_1__term_4">nature reserve</term>.</p></content></section><section eId="chp_3__sec_9"><num>9.</num><heading>Community based natural resource utilization</heading><content><p eId="chp_3__sec_9__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_3__sec_9__p_1__term_1">City</term> may upon application and subject to the provisions of a <term refersTo="#term-management_plan" eId="chp_3__sec_9__p_1__term_2">management plan</term>, by means of the granting of a <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_3__sec_9__p_1__term_3">written authorisation</term> or the entering into of a written agreement, and on the conditions it deems necessary, grant to any local community the right to the sustainable, monitored use of identified biological resources in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_3__sec_9__p_1__term_4">nature reserve</term>.</p></content></section><section eId="chp_3__sec_10"><num>10.</num><heading>Authorisation for use of biological resources</heading><subsection eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_1__intro__p_1">A <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> or written agreement as contemplated in sections <ref href="#chp_3__sec_8" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_1__intro__p_1__ref_1">8</ref> or <ref href="#chp_3__sec_9" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_1__intro__p_1__ref_2">9</ref>, must—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">not be in conflict with the purpose for which a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_1__para_a__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> was established;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">define the land or <term refersTo="#term-water_area" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_1">water area</term> within which the use of the biological resources is granted;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">indicate the period for which the right contemplated in sections <ref href="#chp_3__sec_8" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_1__para_c__p_1__ref_1">8</ref> and <ref href="#chp_3__sec_9" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_1__para_c__p_1__ref_2">9</ref> is granted; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">determine the limits to the use of the biological resources.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_2__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">City</term> must demarcate the land or <term refersTo="#term-water_area" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_2__p_1__term_2">water area</term> contemplated in subsection (1)(b) in a manner it deems fit.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_3__p_1">An authorisation granted in terms of sections <ref href="#chp_3__sec_8" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_3__p_1__ref_1">8</ref> or <ref href="#chp_3__sec_9" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_3__p_1__ref_2">9</ref> may not interfere with the exercise of any authorisation which has been granted to another person in respect of the area contemplated in subsection (1)(b).</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_4"><num>(4)</num><content><p eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_4__p_1">An authorisation granted in terms of sections <ref href="#chp_3__sec_8" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_4__p_1__ref_1">8</ref> or <ref href="#chp_3__sec_9" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_4__p_1__ref_2">9</ref> must include a stipulated notice period for cancellation of the right or amendment of the conditions granting the right.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_5"><num>(5)</num><content><p eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_5__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_5__p_1__term_1">City</term> may cancel an authorisation granted in terms of sections <ref href="#chp_3__sec_8" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_5__p_1__ref_1">8</ref> or <ref href="#chp_3__sec_9" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_5__p_1__ref_2">9</ref> in respect of the area or part thereof, if such area or part thereof is required for conservation purposes or for purposes approved by the City.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_6"><num>(6)</num><content><p eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_6__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_6__p_1__term_1">City</term> may cancel an authorisation granted in terms of sections <ref href="#chp_3__sec_8" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_6__p_1__ref_1">8</ref> or <ref href="#chp_3__sec_9" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_6__p_1__ref_2">9</ref> if the conditions set by the City are not complied with by the relevant person or local community, or if the resource or any other component of the nature reserve is threatened.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_7"><num>(7)</num><content><p eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_7__p_1">An <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_7__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> may instruct a holder of an authorisation contemplated in sections <ref href="#chp_3__sec_8" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_7__p_1__ref_1">8</ref> or <ref href="#chp_3__sec_9" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_7__p_1__ref_2">9</ref> to cease all activities immediately, and take any remedial action if the aforementioned holder of the written authorisation is found or deemed to be in contravention of any conditions stipulated in the written authorisation.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_8"><num>(8)</num><content><p eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_8__p_1">An <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_8__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> may at any time cancel or suspend such authorisation contemplated in sections <ref href="#chp_3__sec_8" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_8__p_1__ref_1">8</ref> &amp; <ref href="#chp_3__sec_9" eId="chp_3__sec_10__subsec_8__p_1__ref_2">9</ref> in the event of an emergency, disaster, threat to life or safety, threat to the environment, or in any circumstance where the authorised official deems the ongoing activity to be detrimental in any way to the nature reserve.</p></content></subsection></section></chapter><chapter eId="chp_4"><num>4</num><heading>Access to nature reserves</heading><section eId="chp_4__sec_11"><num>11.</num><heading>Access to <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_11__term_1">nature reserve</term> by user of biological resources</heading><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__intro__p_1">The holder of a <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> granted in terms of sections <ref href="#chp_3__sec_8" eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__intro__p_1__ref_1">8</ref> or <ref href="#chp_3__sec_9" eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__intro__p_1__ref_2">9</ref> above may, subject to any condition contained in the written authorisation, use a road or path identified by the City, for the reasonable exercise of a written authorisation to use biological resources: Provided that—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_a__p_1__term_1">City</term> may close any access road or limit the use thereof for management purposes;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">if a holder of a <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> fails to remove or repair any obstruction on an access road caused as a result of the exercise of a <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_2">written authorisation</term>, the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_3">City</term> may undertake such removal or repair, and recover the cost in this regard from the holder of the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_4">written authorisation</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_c__p_1__term_1">City</term> may impose restrictions on the type of <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_c__p_1__term_2">vehicle</term>, machinery or equipment which is permitted on an access road in order to prevent any environmental or other damage;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">the holder of a <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> must keep every access road used, reasonable wear excluded, in a good driving condition; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_e__p_1">a holder of a <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_e__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> may not create or construct any new access road for the removal of biological resources or for any other reason, without the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_e__p_1__term_2">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_11__subsec_1__para_e__p_1__term_3">City</term>.</p></content></paragraph></subsection></section><section eId="chp_4__sec_12"><num>12.</num><heading>Admission</heading><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_1__p_1">A person who has been granted entry into a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> may be allowed admission only to a specific area and at designated times as determined by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_1__p_1__term_2">City</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><intro><p eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__intro__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_1">City</term> may close a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term> or any part of a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term>—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_a"><num>(a)</num><intro><p eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_a__intro__p_1">if, in the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_a__intro__p_1__term_1">City</term>’s opinion—</p></intro><subparagraph eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_a__subpara_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_a__subpara_i__p_1">the closure is necessary or desirable for the proper management of the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_a__subpara_i__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_a__subpara_ii"><num>(ii)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_a__subpara_ii__p_1">the closure is necessary for the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_a__subpara_ii__p_1__term_1">City</term> to perform any of its functions in terms of <term refersTo="#term-the_Act" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_a__subpara_ii__p_1__term_2">the Act</term> or this By-law; or</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_a__subpara_iii"><num>(iii)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_a__subpara_iii__p_1">the safety of persons may be compromised;</p></content></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_b__p_1">if a fire-ban is in force in an area that includes all or part of the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_b__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_c__p_1">if the risk of uncontrolled fire in the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_c__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> is, in the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_c__p_1__term_2">City</term>’s opinion, extreme;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_d__p_1">if the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_d__p_1__term_1">City</term>’s staff necessary to patrol or secure the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_d__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term> are unavailable; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_e__p_1">if, in the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_e__p_1__term_1">City</term>’s opinion, it is in the interest of public safety to close the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_2__para_e__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term>.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_3__p_1">No person may, without the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_3__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_3__p_1__term_2">City</term>, enter or remain in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_12__subsec_3__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term>, or part thereof, that has been closed in terms of subsection (2).</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="chp_4__sec_13"><num>13.</num><heading>Entrance and accommodation in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_13__term_1">nature reserve</term></heading><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_13__p_1">Any person entering or staying in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_13__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> is subject to conditions of entry set by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_13__p_1__term_2">City</term>.</p></content></section><section eId="chp_4__sec_14"><num>14.</num><heading>Points of entry and exit</heading><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_1__p_1">No person may, other than in <term refersTo="#term-open_access_areas" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">open access areas</term> of a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_1__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term>, or subject to the provisions of <ref href="#chp_4__sec_11" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_1__p_1__ref_1">section 11</ref>, enter or leave a nature reserve at any place other than through the designated points of entry or exit, without the written authorisation of the City.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><intro><p eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_2__intro__p_1">Where a public road, pathway, cycle path, or railway line passes through a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_2__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_2__para_a__p_1">no <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_2__para_a__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> is required by a person to travel through the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_2__para_a__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term> on such public road, pathway, cycle path, or railway line to a destination outside the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_2__para_a__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term> in question; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_2__para_b"><num>(b)</num><intro><p eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_2__para_b__intro__p_1">no person may—</p></intro><subparagraph eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_2__para_b__subpara_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_2__para_b__subpara_i__p_1">leave such public road, pathway, cycle path, or railway line;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_2__para_b__subpara_ii"><num>(ii)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_2__para_b__subpara_ii__p_1">enter into a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_2__para_b__subpara_ii__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> from such public road, pathway, cycle path, or railway line other than in compliance with <ref href="#chp_4__sec_12" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_2__para_b__subpara_ii__p_1__ref_1">section 12</ref>(1).</p></content></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_3__p_1">No person may fly an <term refersTo="#term-aircraft" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_3__p_1__term_1">aircraft</term>, over a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_3__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term>, at a height below 1500ft above ground level without the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_3__p_1__term_3">written authorisation</term> from the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_3__p_1__term_4">City</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_4"><num>(4)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_4__p_1">No person may land, or attempt to land, an <term refersTo="#term-aircraft" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_4__p_1__term_1">aircraft</term> in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_4__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term> without the prior <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_4__p_1__term_3">written authorisation</term> from the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_4__p_1__term_4">City</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_5"><num>(5)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_5__p_1">No person may fly a remotely piloted <term refersTo="#term-aircraft" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_5__p_1__term_1">aircraft</term> system (RPAS) over a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_5__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term> or land such RPAS in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_5__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term> without the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_5__p_1__term_4">written authorisation</term> from the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_5__p_1__term_5">City</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_6"><num>(6)</num><intro><p eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_6__intro__p_1">Subsection (4) &amp; (5) does not apply—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_6__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_6__para_a__p_1">in the case of an emergency; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_6__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_6__para_b__p_1">to a person acting on the instructions of an <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_6__para_b__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term>.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_7"><num>(7)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_7__p_1">An <term refersTo="#term-aircraft" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_7__p_1__term_1">aircraft</term> performing an emergency landing as per subsection (6)(a) above, must report such emergency landing and the nature thereof, in writing, to the reserve manager, or his nominee before the <term refersTo="#term-aircraft" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_7__p_1__term_2">aircraft</term> is removed from the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_14__subsec_7__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term>, within a reasonable time, depending on the nature of the emergency.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="chp_4__sec_15"><num>15.</num><heading>Proof of entry</heading><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_1__p_1">Where a <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term>, or entry permit, is required for entry to a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_1__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term>, a person who enters the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_1__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term> in a <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_1__p_1__term_4">vehicle</term> or on foot, must ensure that the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_1__p_1__term_5">written authorisation</term> or entry permit is in his or her possession, and available for inspection at all times until he or she leaves the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_1__p_1__term_6">nature reserve</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_2__p_1">Where a <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> is issued for overnighting in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_2__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term>, the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_2__p_1__term_3">written authorisation</term> must be displayed at all times in the <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_2__p_1__term_4">vehicle</term> in accordance with subsection (3) while he or she is overnighting in or near the <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_2__p_1__term_5">vehicle</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><intro><p eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_3__intro__p_1">For purposes of this By-law a <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_3__intro__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> contemplated in subsection (2) is displayed in a <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_3__intro__p_1__term_2">vehicle</term> only if—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_3__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_3__para_a__p_1">the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_3__para_a__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> is displayed on the inside of the windscreen on the side of the <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_3__para_a__p_1__term_2">vehicle</term> opposite to the driver’s position; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_3__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_3__para_b__p_1">where, because of the design of the <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_3__para_b__p_1__term_1">vehicle</term>, it is not possible to comply with paragraph (a) the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_3__para_b__p_1__term_2">written authorisation</term> displayed in a permanent position in or on the <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_3__para_b__p_1__term_3">vehicle</term>, so that the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_3__para_b__p_1__term_4">written authorisation</term> is facing outwards from the <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_3__para_b__p_1__term_5">vehicle</term> and can be easily seen and read by a person outside the <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_4__sec_15__subsec_3__para_b__p_1__term_6">vehicle</term>.</p></content></paragraph></subsection></section><section eId="chp_4__sec_16"><num>16.</num><heading>Safe entering</heading><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_16__p_1">No person may enter or take a <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_4__sec_16__p_1__term_1">vehicle</term> or <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_4__sec_16__p_1__term_2">vessel</term> into a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_16__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term>, onto a place, road, river or <term refersTo="#term-water_area" eId="chp_4__sec_16__p_1__term_4">water area</term> in an unsafe, reckless or negligent manner.</p></content></section><section eId="chp_4__sec_17"><num>17.</num><heading>Staying <term refersTo="#term-overnight" eId="chp_4__sec_17__term_1">overnight</term></heading><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__intro__p_1">No person may stay <term refersTo="#term-overnight" eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_1">overnight</term> in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term>—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">without the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_a__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_a__p_1__term_2">City</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">without having first reported to the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> reception office in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term> or to an authorised person assigned by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_3">City</term> to perform escort duty;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">where no accommodation has been reserved or is available for that person;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">on a houseboat or any <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_1">vessel</term> without the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_2">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_3">City</term>; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_e__p_1">at any place other than a place designated for such activity by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_1__para_e__p_1__term_1">City</term>.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_2__p_1">No person may, without the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_2__p_1__term_2">City</term> contemplated in subsection (1), <term refersTo="#term-overnight" eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_2__p_1__term_3">overnight</term> in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_2__p_1__term_4">nature reserve</term> except in an area set aside by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_17__subsec_2__p_1__term_5">City</term> for that purpose.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="chp_4__sec_18"><num>18.</num><heading>Times of entry and travel</heading><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_18__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_18__subsec_1__p_1">Nature reserves are open from sunrise to sunset, unless indicated otherwise by means of a <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_4__sec_18__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">notice</term> at designated points of entry and at <term refersTo="#term-open_access_areas" eId="chp_4__sec_18__subsec_1__p_1__term_2">open access areas</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_4__sec_18__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_4__sec_18__subsec_2__p_1">No person may, without the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_4__sec_18__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_18__subsec_2__p_1__term_2">City</term>, enter, leave or travel in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_4__sec_18__subsec_2__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term> at any time other than the times determined by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_4__sec_18__subsec_2__p_1__term_4">City</term>, except in <term refersTo="#term-open_access_areas" eId="chp_4__sec_18__subsec_2__p_1__term_5">open access areas</term>.</p></content></subsection></section></chapter><chapter eId="chp_5"><num>5</num><heading>Restricted activities</heading><section eId="chp_5__sec_19"><num>19.</num><heading>Activities which may have an adverse effect in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_19__term_1">nature reserve</term></heading><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__intro__p_1">No person may without the written authority of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_1">City</term> in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term>—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">introduce any <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_a__p_1__term_1">specimen</term>, or part thereof to a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_a__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">convey, move or otherwise translocate any <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_1">specimen</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">intentionally disturb any <term refersTo="#term-species" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_c__p_1__term_1">species</term> or <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_c__p_1__term_2">specimen</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">feed any <term refersTo="#term-species" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_1">species</term> or <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_2">specimen</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_e__p_1">use any recording of any <term refersTo="#term-species" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_e__p_1__term_1">species</term> or <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_e__p_1__term_2">specimen</term> or the imagery or scent of a <term refersTo="#term-species" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_e__p_1__term_3">species</term> or <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_e__p_1__term_4">specimen</term> to attract animals;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_f__p_1">lure, bait or attract by any means or for any purpose or intention any <term refersTo="#term-species" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_f__p_1__term_1">species</term> or <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_f__p_1__term_2">specimen</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_g"><num>(g)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_g__p_1">cut, damage, remove or destroy or be in possession of any plant or any part thereof, including dry wood;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_h"><num>(h)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_h__p_1">hunt, capture or kill any living <term refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_h__p_1__term_1">animal</term> by any means, method or device whatsoever, including searching, pursuing, driving, lying in wait, luring, alluring, discharging a missile or projectile or injure with intent to hunt, catch, capture or kill any such <term refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_h__p_1__term_2">animal</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_i__p_1">gather, collect or pluck any <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_i__p_1__term_1">specimen</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_j"><num>(j)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_j__p_1"><term refersTo="#term-pick" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_j__p_1__term_1">pick</term> parts of, or cut, chop off, uproot, damage or destroy, any <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_j__p_1__term_2">specimen</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_k"><num>(k)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_k__p_1">possess or exercise physical control over any <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_k__p_1__term_1">specimen</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_l"><num>(l)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_l__p_1">grow, breed or in any other way propagate any <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_l__p_1__term_1">specimen</term> or cause it to multiply;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_m"><num>(m)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_m__p_1">sell or otherwise trade in, buy, receive, give, donate or accept as a gift, or in any way acquire or dispose of any <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_m__p_1__term_1">specimen</term>; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_n"><num>(n)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_1__para_n__p_1">angle, attempt to angle, catch or attempt to catch fish other than in an area designated for such purpose.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_2__p_1">Sub-section (19)(1)(c), (d), (e), (f), (h) does not apply to the use of fishing rods, bait or lures for the purpose of fishing where such activity is permitted in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><intro><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_3__intro__p_1">No person within a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_3__intro__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> may—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_3__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_3__para_a__p_1">intentionally or negligently cause pollution;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_3__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_3__para_b__p_1">deface cultural heritage resources; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_3__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_3__para_c__p_1">harm, or cause death to any individual <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_3__para_c__p_1__term_1">specimen</term> or population of any <term refersTo="#term-species" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_3__para_c__p_1__term_2">species</term> without the prior <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_3__para_c__p_1__term_3">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_3__para_c__p_1__term_4">City</term>.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_4"><num>(4)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_4__p_1">No person may, other than with prior <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_4__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_4__p_1__term_2">City</term> and subject to the <term refersTo="#term-management_plan" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_4__p_1__term_3">management plan</term> and <term refersTo="#term-NEMA" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_4__p_1__term_4">NEMA</term> regulations, open or close the mouth of a tidal lagoon or tidal river within a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_4__p_1__term_5">nature reserve</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_5"><num>(5)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_5__p_1">No person may, within a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_5__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> place, throw, dump, or release into the environment any refuse, rubbish, used containers, effluent, toilet waste, or any objectionable material in areas other than those designated fit for this purpose by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_19__subsec_5__p_1__term_2">City</term>.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="chp_5__sec_20"><num>20.</num><heading>Specified activities</heading><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__intro__p_1">No person may undertake any of the following activities in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> except with <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_2">written authorisation</term> from the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_3">City</term> and in accordance with an approved <term refersTo="#term-management_plan" eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_4">management plan</term> or environmental <term refersTo="#term-management_plan" eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_5">management plan</term> for the specified activity:</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">film and simultaneously transmit photographic images using a webcam or other image recording or transmitting device, including trail cams;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">conduct tours;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">conduct any kind of competition;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">sell or hire goods or the offering of goods for sale or hire;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_e__p_1">provide or offer to provide any service for a fee or reward;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_f__p_1">an activity of any kind for the purpose of fund raising, personal gain, making a profit, or advertising;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_g"><num>(g)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_g__p_1">an organised special event, including sporting or cultural events;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_h"><num>(h)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_h__p_1">record visual images of animals for any virtual hunting or other such activity;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_i__p_1">conduct any type of training, exercises or simulations; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_j"><num>(j)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_20__subsec_1__para_j__p_1">environmental education programmes and activities.</p></content></paragraph></subsection></section><section eId="chp_5__sec_21"><num>21.</num><heading>Research and monitoring</heading><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_1__p_1">No person may in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>, without <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_1__p_1__term_2">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_1__p_1__term_3">City</term>, carry out scientific or general research or undertake monitoring projects.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><intro><p eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2__intro__p_1">Any person undertaking scientific or general research or monitoring projects in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> must—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2__para_a__p_1">submit a written proposal to the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2__para_a__p_1__term_1">City</term> that describes the purpose and methodology of the research or monitoring;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2__para_b__p_1">be in possession of all required permits and authorisations in terms of any other law;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2__para_c__p_1">comply with all specified conditions in the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2__para_c__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2__para_d__p_1">submit all data and information gathered, to the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2__para_d__p_1__term_1">City</term>, in a format determined and at stages of the project specified by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2__para_d__p_1__term_2">City</term>; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2__para_e__p_1">submit copies of all reports and findings to the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_21__subsec_2__para_e__p_1__term_1">City</term> upon completion.</p></content></paragraph></subsection></section><section eId="chp_5__sec_22"><num>22.</num><heading>Interference with soil or substrate</heading><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__intro__p_1">No person may, except with the prior <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_2">City</term> and subject to any other applicable laws—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><intro><p eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_a__intro__p_1">remove from a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_a__intro__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> any—</p></intro><subparagraph eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_a__subpara_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_a__subpara_i__p_1">soil, sand, gravel, pebbles, stone, rock, shell grit or mineral or similar material;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_a__subpara_ii"><num>(ii)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_a__subpara_ii__p_1">wood, mulch or other dead vegetation;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_a__subpara_iii"><num>(iii)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_a__subpara_iii__p_1">fossil, archaeological remains or cultural artefacts;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_a__subpara_iv"><num>(iv)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_a__subpara_iv__p_1">coral or sea shells; or</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_a__subpara_v"><num>(v)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_a__subpara_v__p_1"><term refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_a__subpara_v__p_1__term_1">animal</term> faecal matter;</p></content></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">dig any soil or similar material in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><intro><p eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_c__intro__p_1">intentionally disturb in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_c__intro__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>—</p></intro><subparagraph eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_c__subpara_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_c__subpara_i__p_1">wood, mulch, peat or other dead vegetation or <term refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_c__subpara_i__p_1__term_1">animal</term>;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_c__subpara_ii"><num>(ii)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_c__subpara_ii__p_1">termite mounds, bees nests, spider webs, birds nests or <term refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_c__subpara_ii__p_1__term_1">animal</term> burrow;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_c__subpara_iii"><num>(iii)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_c__subpara_iii__p_1">fossil, shell midden, archaeological remains or paleontological specimens or meteorites;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_c__subpara_iv"><num>(iv)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_c__subpara_iv__p_1">any of the marine components contemplated in paragraph (a);</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_c__subpara_v"><num>(v)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_c__subpara_v__p_1">any object or material that is or was used for any ritual or other practice; or</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_c__subpara_vi"><num>(vi)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_22__subsec_1__para_c__subpara_vi__p_1">any object that has historical or cultural significance.</p></content></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section><section eId="chp_5__sec_23"><num>23.</num><heading>Bioprospecting</heading><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_23__p_1">No person may undertake any manner or form of <term refersTo="#term-bioprospecting" eId="chp_5__sec_23__p_1__term_1">bioprospecting</term> in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_23__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term> without the prior <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_5__sec_23__p_1__term_3">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_23__p_1__term_4">City</term> other than subject to such conditions as determined by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_23__p_1__term_5">City</term>.</p></content></section><section eId="chp_5__sec_24"><num>24.</num><heading>Buildings and improvements</heading><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_1__p_1">Building developments and improvements in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> are subject to prior approval and <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_1__p_1__term_2">written authorisation</term> from the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_1__p_1__term_3">City</term>, and any relevant legislation including but not limited to an environmental authorisation in terms of section 24 of the National Environmental Management Act, 1998 (<term refersTo="#term-NEMA" eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_1__p_1__term_4">NEMA</term>).</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_2__p_1">No person may in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>, without prior <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_2__p_1__term_2">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_2__p_1__term_3">City</term>, erect, construct or transform or cause to be erected, constructed or transformed any building, structure (temporary or permanent) or any other improvement, including but not limited to a building or structure of any kind, jetty, dock, pier, landing stage, landing float, anchor buoy, raft, fence or any obstruction, bridge, pontoon, road or crossing in respect of a building or immovable property.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><intro><p eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_3__intro__p_1">Any person who has applied in terms of subsection (2) for the erection of a building or any other improvement in respect of a building or other immovable property must, if required to do so by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_3__intro__p_1__term_1">City</term>—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_3__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_3__para_a__p_1">in the case where prior environmental authorisation in terms of section 24 of <term refersTo="#term-NEMA" eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_3__para_a__p_1__term_1">NEMA</term> is not required, in terms of any law employ an independent environmental consultant to conduct an assessment of the proposed erection or improvement in compliance with the minimum requirements set by the <term refersTo="#term-NEMA" eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_3__para_a__p_1__term_2">NEMA</term>, or other applicable legislation, and to submit the findings of the assessment to the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_3__para_a__p_1__term_3">City</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_3__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_3__para_b__p_1">in instances where prior environmental authorisation in terms of section 24 of <term refersTo="#term-NEMA" eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_3__para_b__p_1__term_1">NEMA</term> is compulsory, provide the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_3__para_b__p_1__term_2">City</term> with such environmental authorisation before the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_24__subsec_3__para_b__p_1__term_3">City</term> considers the application.</p></content></paragraph></subsection></section><section eId="chp_5__sec_25"><num>25.</num><heading>French drains, pit latrines and other sewerage disposal systems</heading><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_25__p_1">No person may, without the prior <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_5__sec_25__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_25__p_1__term_2">City</term>, accompanied by a site plan, construct or in any way alter, extend or enlarge any french drain system, pit latrine or any other sewerage disposal system on any land situated within a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_25__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term> or replace it with another french drain system, pit latrine or any other sewerage disposal system.</p></content></section><section eId="chp_5__sec_26"><num>26.</num><heading>Holiday resort, caravan park, camping or picnic site</heading><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_26__p_1">No person may erect, establish, transform, extend or enlarge any holiday resort, caravan park or camping or picnic site within a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_26__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> at which members of the public can stay, camp or picnic, upon payment of a fee or not, other than in accordance with the <term refersTo="#term-management_plan" eId="chp_5__sec_26__p_1__term_2">management plan</term> for the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_26__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term>.</p></content></section><section eId="chp_5__sec_27"><num>27.</num><heading>Land and airspace</heading><intro><p eId="chp_5__sec_27__intro__p_1">No person may in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_27__intro__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>, except with the prior <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_5__sec_27__intro__p_1__term_2">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_27__intro__p_1__term_3">City</term>—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_a__p_1">engage in the sport of climbing rock faces;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_b__p_1">engage in the sport of parachuting or abseiling;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_c__p_1">land or take off in, or attempt to land or take off in, any <term refersTo="#term-aircraft" eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_c__p_1__term_1">aircraft</term>, helicopter, glider, hang glider, paraglider or hot air balloon;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_d__p_1">launch or fly a hot air balloon;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_e__p_1">fly <term refersTo="#term-model_aircraft" eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_e__p_1__term_1">model aircraft</term>, RPAS or gliders;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_f__p_1">engage in the sport of any kind of boarding, including sandboarding, windsurfing, kitesurfing or sailboarding</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_g"><num>(g)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_g__p_1">operate any motorised <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_g__p_1__term_1">vehicle</term> for recreational purposes;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_h"><num>(h)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_h__p_1">launch or propel, a missile or flare into the airspace above a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_h__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> unless such activity is a <i>bona fide</i> emergency; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_27__para_i__p_1">possess, ignite or use any fireworks.</p></content></paragraph></section><section eId="chp_5__sec_28"><num>28.</num><heading>Water areas</heading><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_28__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_28__subsec_1__p_1">No person may, without the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_5__sec_28__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_28__subsec_1__p_1__term_2">City</term>, launch, or use a <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_5__sec_28__subsec_1__p_1__term_3">vessel</term> on a dam, reservoir, lake, river or other body of water in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_28__subsec_1__p_1__term_4">nature reserve</term> unless the water has been set aside by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_28__subsec_1__p_1__term_5">City</term> for the use of vessels.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_28__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_28__subsec_2__p_1">No person may carry out any repairs, servicing, testing, painting of any <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_5__sec_28__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">vessel</term> in a <term refersTo="#term-water_area" eId="chp_5__sec_28__subsec_2__p_1__term_2">water area</term> in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_28__subsec_2__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term> unless the prior <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_5__sec_28__subsec_2__p_1__term_4">written authorisation</term> by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_28__subsec_2__p_1__term_5">City</term> has been obtained.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="chp_5__sec_29"><num>29.</num><heading>Removal and dumping in water areas</heading><intro><p eId="chp_5__sec_29__intro__p_1">No persons may, without the prior <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_5__sec_29__intro__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_29__intro__p_1__term_2">City</term> and other than subject to the conditions imposed by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_29__intro__p_1__term_3">City</term>, in any manner in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_29__intro__p_1__term_4">nature reserve</term>—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_29__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_29__para_a__p_1">remove, dredge, pump or move any sand, soil or stones from a <term refersTo="#term-water_area" eId="chp_5__sec_29__para_a__p_1__term_1">water area</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_29__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_29__para_b__p_1">deposit, dump or throw sand, soil, stones or other material of any kind in a <term refersTo="#term-water_area" eId="chp_5__sec_29__para_b__p_1__term_1">water area</term>.</p></content></paragraph></section><section eId="chp_5__sec_30"><num>30.</num><heading>Domestic animals and livestock in nature reserves</heading><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_30__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_30__subsec_1__p_1">No person may, except on conditions determined by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_30__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">City</term> from time to time, allow any dog, cat or other <term refersTo="#term-domestic_animal" eId="chp_5__sec_30__subsec_1__p_1__term_2">domestic animal</term> or livestock belonging to or under the care of that person to enter or remain in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_30__subsec_1__p_1__term_3">nature reserve</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_30__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_30__subsec_2__p_1">Any dog, cat or other <term refersTo="#term-domestic_animal" eId="chp_5__sec_30__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">domestic animal</term>, including those contemplated in <ref href="#chp_5__sec_30" eId="chp_5__sec_30__subsec_2__p_1__ref_1">section 30</ref>(1) which is not in the care of any person, may be caught and removed, impounded or destroyed at the discretion of the City.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_30__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_30__subsec_3__p_1">Any dog, cat, other <term refersTo="#term-domestic_animal" eId="chp_5__sec_30__subsec_3__p_1__term_1">domestic animal</term> or livestock in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_30__subsec_3__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term>, including those contemplated in <ref href="#chp_5__sec_30" eId="chp_5__sec_30__subsec_3__p_1__ref_1">section 30</ref>(1), that is not in direct control by means of a leash or similar restraint, unless in a designated leash or constraint free area, may be caught and removed or impounded at the discretion of the City.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="chp_5__sec_31"><num>31.</num><heading>Firearms and dangerous weapons</heading><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_31__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_31__subsec_1__p_1">No person other than an <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_5__sec_31__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> or contractor with <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_5__sec_31__subsec_1__p_1__term_2">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_31__subsec_1__p_1__term_3">City</term>, who enters a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_31__subsec_1__p_1__term_4">nature reserve</term>, may be in possession of any firearm, dangerous weapon, explosive, trap or poison.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="chp_5__sec_32"><num>32.</num><heading>Commercial activities</heading><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_32__p_1">No person may undertake any activities of a commercial nature, including the operation of any entertainment device, the sale of any goods, the hire of any equipment, or any similar activity on any <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_32__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>, without <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_5__sec_32__p_1__term_2">written authorisation</term> from the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_32__p_1__term_3">City</term>.</p></content></section><section eId="chp_5__sec_33"><num>33.</num><heading>General restrictions</heading><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__intro__p_1">No person who is in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>, without the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_2">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_3">City</term>, may—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">offer any show or entertainment, conduct any business or trade, or collect any money from the public;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">carry on any agricultural or gardening activities except subject to the conditions which the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_1">City</term> may lay down from time to time;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">use or cause to be used, any loud speaker or similar device or other noisy equipment;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">construct or erect any booth, marquee or other structure;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__para_e__p_1">organise or cause to be organised or attend or participate in any public meeting, demonstration or gathering; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__para_f__p_1">tamper with, deface, damage, remove or in any other way interfere with a reserve boundary fence or object demarcating the boundary of a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_1__para_f__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><intro><p eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_2__intro__p_1">No person may—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_2__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_2__para_a__p_1">intentionally or negligently cause a fire or discard any burning object in any place where it may set fire to any other object or otherwise act in a manner likely to cause a fire, other than at a place where the making of a fire is permitted by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_2__para_a__p_1__term_1">City</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_2__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_2__para_b__p_1">smoke in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_2__para_b__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>, other than in areas designated for smoking; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_2__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_5__sec_33__subsec_2__para_c__p_1">discharge any firework.</p></content></paragraph></subsection></section></chapter><chapter eId="chp_6"><num>6</num><heading>Prohibited activities</heading><section eId="chp_6__sec_34"><num>34.</num><heading>Prohibitions relating to vehicles</heading><subsection eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__intro__p_1">No person driving a <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_1">vehicle</term> in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term> may—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">drive, park, or stop in such a manner that constitutes a <term refersTo="#term-nuisance" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_a__p_1__term_1">nuisance</term>, disturbance, inconvenience or danger to any other person or <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_a__p_1__term_2">vehicle</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">drive, park or stop in any manner that causes an obstruction;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">block the pathway of a management operation or emergency <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_c__p_1__term_1">vehicle</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">park a <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_1">vehicle</term> in a place other than in a place designated for that purpose by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_2">City</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_e__p_1">drive or park anywhere except on a designated road or designated parking area;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_f__p_1">drive or operate any <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_f__p_1__term_1">vehicle</term> in a reckless or negligent manner, or deliberately or intentionally disregard the safety of any person, <term refersTo="#term-species" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_f__p_1__term_2">species</term>, <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_f__p_1__term_3">specimen</term> or property of whatever nature;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_g"><num>(g)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_g__p_1">drive a <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_g__p_1__term_1">vehicle</term> off designated roads or tracks, except in an area set aside by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_g__p_1__term_2">City</term> for that purpose; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_h"><num>(h)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_h__p_1">drive a <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_1__para_h__p_1__term_1">vehicle</term> for recreational purposes, including, but not limited to, 4×4ing, off-roading, quad biking and motor biking in any area not demarcated for such recreational activity.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_2__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">City</term> may restrict or preclude the use of any <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_2__p_1__term_2">vehicle</term> or <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_2__p_1__term_3">vehicle</term> type within a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_2__p_1__term_4">nature reserve</term> or section of a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_2__p_1__term_5">nature reserve</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_3__p_1">No person may enter or travel in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_3__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> except in a <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_3__p_1__term_2">vehicle</term> that conforms to the dimensions and other requirements determined by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_6__sec_34__subsec_3__p_1__term_3">City</term>.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="chp_6__sec_35"><num>35.</num><heading>Littering and pollution</heading><subsection eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__intro__p_1">No person may, in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">deposit or leave any litter which is either industrial or domestic, regardless of whether that litter is biodegradable or non-biodegradable,     except in an area or receptacle provided for that purpose;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">deposit or leave any litter, bottle, broken glass, china, pottery, plastic article, rubbish, refuse, seeds, fruit or vegetable matter or other waste material, except in an area or receptacle provided for that purpose;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">deposit, discharge or leave any noxious, smelly, offensive or polluting substance, matter or thing;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">deposit or leave any offal, dead <term refersTo="#term-species" eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_1">species</term> or <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_2">specimen</term>, or dung;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_e__p_1">deposit, except in any receptacle provided for litter, any domestic garbage;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_f__p_1">intentionally break any article of glass, china, pottery, plastic or other brittle material;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_g"><num>(g)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_g__p_1">deposit, discharge or leave any mineral, mineral waste or other industrial waste or by-product thereof;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_h"><num>(h)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_h__p_1">discard or discharge any toxic chemical or substance, pharmaceutical substance, including biocides, or any other pollutant or harmful substance; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_35__subsec_1__para_i__p_1">dispose of aerosols containers or any other hazardous substance of such nature.</p></content></paragraph></subsection></section><section eId="chp_6__sec_36"><num>36.</num><heading>Pollution of water</heading><subsection eId="chp_6__sec_36__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_36__subsec_1__p_1">No person at any time or in any manner, including by the use of detergents, dispose of any solid or liquid waste, including engine oil, into any <term refersTo="#term-water_area" eId="chp_6__sec_36__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">water area</term>, wetland, spring, pan, well, borehole, groundwater, dam, reservoir or lake in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_6__sec_36__subsec_1__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_6__sec_36__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_36__subsec_2__p_1">No person may at any time or in any manner throw, place or dispose of any item, medium or object that may directly or indirectly cause any water pollution;</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="chp_6__sec_37"><num>37.</num><heading>General prohibitions</heading><subsection eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__intro__p_1">No person may, in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">unlawfully occupy, build on, erect, move into, inhabit, sell or use any land, building or structure to which he or she does not have lawful title;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">continue with the construction of an incomplete structure after a written <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_1">notice</term> to stop construction was issued by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_2">City</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">demarcate any piece of land with any form of material, including, but not restricted to string, rope, pegs, stones, pebbles, wire, wood or any other material or continue to demarcate after a written <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_c__p_1__term_1">notice</term> to stop any form of demarcation was issued by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_c__p_1__term_2">City</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">move or remove any demarcation or surveying pegs affixed in terms of any law;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_e__p_1">without the written consent of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_e__p_1__term_1">City</term> allow, encourage, motivate, organise or instigate the occupation of any land;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_f__p_1">at any time play any radio, compact disc player, music system, musical instrument or in any way whatsoever cause any noise in a manner that is likely to disturb any <term refersTo="#term-species" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_f__p_1__term_1">species</term> or <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_f__p_1__term_2">specimen</term> or other person;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_g"><num>(g)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_g__p_1">behave in an offensive, improper, indecent or disorderly manner;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_h"><num>(h)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_h__p_1">engage in sexual activity or solicit any person for the purpose of prostitution or immorality;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_i__p_1">except subject to <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_i__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> granted in <ref href="#chp_3" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_i__p_1__ref_1">chapter 3</ref>, cut, remove, dig up, fell, burn, pluck, break, climb up or upon or cause damage to timber or to any tree, shrub, brushwood, fencing post, pole, fern, turf, grass, fruit, flower, plant or vegetation; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_j"><num>(j)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_1__para_j__p_1">create or construct any new access roads, paths or tracks.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_2__p_1">No person may, in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>, intentionally obstruct, disturb, interrupt or annoy any other person utilising the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_2__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term> in compliance with this By-law.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><intro><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_3__intro__p_1">No person may discharge a firearm within a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_3__intro__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>, except—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_3__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_3__para_a__p_1">if that person is authorised by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_3__para_a__p_1__term_1">City</term> thereto;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_3__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_3__para_b__p_1">for the discharge of a blank by a life-guard during an organized competition or by any other person authorised by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_3__para_b__p_1__term_1">City</term>, during a sports meeting in a <term refersTo="#term-water_area" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_3__para_b__p_1__term_2">water area</term>; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_3__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_3__para_c__p_1">in connection with the collection of specimens for scientific purposes, subject to the <term refersTo="#term-written_authorisation" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_3__para_c__p_1__term_1">written authorisation</term> of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_3__para_c__p_1__term_2">City</term>;</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_4"><num>(4)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_4__p_1">No person may, in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_4__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>, throw, roll or discharge any stone, rock, boulder, substance, projectile or missile to endanger any person, <term refersTo="#term-species" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_4__p_1__term_2">species</term> or <term refersTo="#term-specimen" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_4__p_1__term_3">specimen</term> in the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_4__p_1__term_4">nature reserve</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_5"><num>(5)</num><content><p eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_5__p_1">No person may, in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_5__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>, prevent, hinder or obstruct an <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_6__sec_37__subsec_5__p_1__term_2">authorised official</term> in the exercise of his duties in terms of this By-law.</p></content></subsection></section></chapter><chapter eId="chp_7"><num>7</num><heading>Fees and tariffs</heading><section eId="chp_7__sec_38"><num>38.</num><heading>Fees and tariffs</heading><subsection eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_1__intro__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_1">City</term> shall annually determine the fees and tariffs applicable for—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">access to nature reserves;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">the use of any amenity, service, facility, entertainment venue, film show or performance presented or provided or rendered by or on behalf of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_1">City</term>, at or in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_1__para_b__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term>; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">the operation of any commercial activity;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">costs associated with any remedial action undertaken by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_1">City</term> due to non-compliance with the By-law.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_2__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">City</term> may recover costs associated with remedial action undertaken due to non-compliance with the By-law.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_3__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_7__sec_38__subsec_3__p_1__term_1">City</term> may suspend the payment of entrance fees on any specific day as it may deem fit.</p></content></subsection></section></chapter><chapter eId="chp_8"><num>8</num><heading>Compliance and enforcement</heading><section eId="chp_8__sec_39"><num>39.</num><heading>Authorised officials</heading><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_39__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_39__subsec_1__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_8__sec_39__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">City</term> may appoint any member of staff as an <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_39__subsec_1__p_1__term_2">authorised official</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_39__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_39__subsec_2__p_1">Any duly appointed <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_39__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> must be in possession of the prescribed staff identification card when exercising any power in terms of this By-law and must, upon request, produce such card.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_39__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_39__subsec_3__p_1">Should the <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_39__subsec_3__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> considered in subsection (2) fail to produce the staff identification card then no power granted in terms of this By-law can be exercised.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="chp_8__sec_40"><num>40.</num><heading>Powers and functions of authorised officials</heading><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_1__p_1">In this section, unless the context indicates otherwise, ‘<b>article</b>’ means anything, including a structure, object, document, book, record or electronic information or extract, part or sample therefrom that is reasonably suspected in the use of contravening this By-law.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><intro><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_2__intro__p_1">Without a warrant, an <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> may stop, enter, search and seize any <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_2">vessel</term>, <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_3">vehicle</term>, premises or person if the <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_4">authorised official</term> has reasonable grounds to believe that an offence in terms of this By-law has been or is being committed on or in such <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_5">vessel</term>, <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_6">vehicle</term> or premises if—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_2__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_2__para_a__p_1">the person in control of the <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_2__para_a__p_1__term_1">vessel</term>, <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_2__para_a__p_1__term_2">vehicle</term> or premises consents to such stop, entry, search or seizure; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_2__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_2__para_b__p_1">the <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_2__para_b__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> has reasonable grounds to believe that a warrant will be issued, if the <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_2__para_b__p_1__term_2">authorised official</term> applied for it, and the delay caused by the obtaining of such a warrant would defeat the object of the stop, entry, search or seizure.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_3__p_1">If subsection (2) does not apply, then an <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_3__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> may stop, enter and search any <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_3__p_1__term_2">vessel</term>, <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_3__p_1__term_3">vehicle</term>, premises or person and may seize an article contemplated in subsection (5)(h) only on the authority of a warrant.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_4"><num>(4)</num><intro><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_4__intro__p_1">A judge in chambers may issue a warrant contemplated in subsection (3) on written application by an <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_4__intro__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> if it appears from information under oath or affirmation that—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_4__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_4__para_a__p_1">there are reasonable grounds for believing that a contravention of this By-law has occurred;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_4__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_4__para_b__p_1">the search and seizure is likely to yield information pertaining to the contravention; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_4__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_4__para_c__p_1">the search and seizure is reasonably necessary for the purposes of this By-law.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5"><num>(5)</num><intro><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__intro__p_1">In enforcing or investigating compliance with this By-law, an <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__intro__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> may—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_a__p_1">be accompanied by an interpreter, a police official or any other person who may be able to assist with the inspection;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_b__p_1">inspect any article which may be relevant to the investigation;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_c__p_1">examine, analyse, measure or make a copy of an article and remove it for examination, analysis, measurement, copying or extraction;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_d__p_1">require a person to produce or to deliver at such time and place as may be determined by the <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_d__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term>, an article for inspection;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_e__p_1">take a photograph or make an audio visual recording of any person or anything for his or her investigation;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_f__p_1">question a person who, in the opinion of the <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_f__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term>, may be able to furnish information on a matter to which this By-law relates;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_g"><num>(g)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_g__p_1">direct a person to appear before him or her at such time and place as may be determined by the <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_g__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> and question such person either alone or in the presence of any other person on a matter to which this By-law relates; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_h"><num>(h)</num><intro><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_h__intro__p_1">seize an article—</p></intro><subparagraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_h__subpara_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_h__subpara_i__p_1">which is concerned in or is on reasonable grounds believed to be concerned in an offence in terms of this By-law;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_h__subpara_ii"><num>(ii)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_h__subpara_ii__p_1">which may afford evidence of an offence in terms of this By-law; or</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_h__subpara_iii"><num>(iii)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_5__para_h__subpara_iii__p_1">which is intended to be used or is on reasonable grounds believed to be intended to be used in the commission of an offence in terms of this By-law.</p></content></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_6"><num>(6)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_6__p_1">A person who so requests may, if possible, make a copy of an article to be removed or seized in terms of this section.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_7"><num>(7)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_7__p_1">When an <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_7__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> removes or seizes an article, the <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_7__p_1__term_2">authorised official</term> must issue a receipt to the owner or person in control thereof and, if possible, return the article as soon as practicable after achieving the purpose for which the article was removed or seized.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_8"><num>(8)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_8__p_1">An <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_8__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> must exercise their powers and functions with strict regard for decency and order, and with regard for each person’s right to dignity, freedom, security and privacy.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_9"><num>(9)</num><intro><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_9__intro__p_1">Notwithstanding the provisions of this By-law, and subject to any other applicable legislation, an <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_9__intro__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> may —</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_9__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_9__para_a__p_1">launch, operate or use any <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_9__para_a__p_1__term_1">vehicle</term> or <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_9__para_a__p_1__term_2">vessel</term> upon any <term refersTo="#term-recreational_water" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_9__para_a__p_1__term_3">recreational water</term> or in any <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_9__para_a__p_1__term_4">nature reserve</term> for the purpose of providing an emergency, rescue or transport service, to provide a municipal service, to ensure compliance with this By-law, or for the purpose of undertaking research, monitoring or conducting a survey;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_9__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_9__para_b__p_1">do anything in a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_9__para_b__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term> in the exercise of a lawful power or duty; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_9__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_9__para_c__p_1">in any <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_9__para_c__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>, use prohibited means of fishing, hunt any <term refersTo="#term-animal" eId="chp_8__sec_40__subsec_9__para_c__p_1__term_2">animal</term>, and collect biological specimens in order to eradicate, control, or collect information for the control, monitoring and research of such organisms in the course of their duties.</p></content></paragraph></subsection></section><section eId="chp_8__sec_41"><num>41.</num><heading>Compliance <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_8__sec_41__term_1">notice</term></heading><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__intro__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> may serve a written compliance <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__intro__p_1__term_2">notice</term> on a person if there are reasonable grounds for believing that the person is in contravention of this By-law.</p><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__intro__p_2">The compliance <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__intro__p_2__term_1">notice</term> must—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">describe the conduct constituting a contravention of this By-law;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">indicate which provision of this By-law or condition of approval is contravened;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">where relevant, state that the unlawful conduct constitutes an offence and indicate the penalty;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">where relevant, be issued together with a fine;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_e__p_1">instruct the person to cease the unlawful conduct;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_f__p_1">where relevant, impose conditions which must be complied with and specify the steps to be taken to comply;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_g"><num>(g)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_g__p_1">state that a failure to comply with the <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_g__p_1__term_1">notice</term> constitutes an offence and indicate the penalty; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_h"><num>(h)</num><intro><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_h__intro__p_1">state that, in the event of non-compliance with the <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_h__intro__p_1__term_1">notice</term>, the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_h__intro__p_1__term_2">City</term> may take one or more of the following measures—</p></intro><subparagraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_h__subpara_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_h__subpara_i__p_1">issue the person with a fine for not complying with the compliance <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_h__subpara_i__p_1__term_1">notice</term>;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_h__subpara_ii"><num>(ii)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_h__subpara_ii__p_1">take steps to remedy any adverse effect arising from the person’s actions and recover the costs from such person;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_h__subpara_iii"><num>(iii)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_h__subpara_iii__p_1">apply to a competent court for appropriate relief including the costs of the application; or</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_h__subpara_iv"><num>(iv)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_h__subpara_iv__p_1">institute a criminal prosecution.</p></content></subparagraph></paragraph><hcontainer name="hcontainer" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__hcontainer_1"><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__hcontainer_1__p_1">The compliance <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__hcontainer_1__p_1__term_1">notice</term> may—</p></content></hcontainer><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_i__p_1">instruct the person within a specified time to, in writing, inform the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_i__p_1__term_1">City</term> what steps have been taken to comply with the <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_i__p_1__term_2">notice</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_j"><num>(j)</num><intro><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_j__intro__p_1">instruct a person at their cost to take specified action to the satisfaction of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_j__intro__p_1__term_1">City</term> within a specified time to—</p></intro><subparagraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_j__subpara_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_j__subpara_i__p_1">cease, modify or control an activity causing, continuing or contributing to an adverse effect on a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_j__subpara_i__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>,</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_j__subpara_ii"><num>(ii)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_j__subpara_ii__p_1">investigate, evaluate and assess the impact of a specific situation or activity and report thereon;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_j__subpara_iii"><num>(iii)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_j__subpara_iii__p_1">undertake and complete specific measures;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_j__subpara_iv"><num>(iv)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_j__subpara_iv__p_1">eliminate or remove an encroachment or unauthorised structure;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_j__subpara_v"><num>(v)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_j__subpara_v__p_1">rehabilitate the affected environment; or</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_j__subpara_vi"><num>(vi)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_1__para_j__subpara_vi__p_1">any combination of the provisions listed in paragraphs (i) through (v).</p></content></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_2__p_1">Should the person on whom a compliance <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_2__p_1__term_1">notice</term> under subsection (1) was issued, fail to comply, or inadequately comply, with the compliance <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_2__p_1__term_2">notice</term> or authorisation, then the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_2__p_1__term_3">City</term> may take measures that the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_2__p_1__term_4">City</term> considers appropriate to remedy the situation and may authorise another person to take such measures.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_3__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_3__p_1__term_1">City</term> may recover costs to the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_3__p_1__term_2">City</term>, or an authorised person, for the measures to be undertaken under subsection (2), and all costs incurred as a result of acting under subsection (2), from any or all of the persons on whom the compliance <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_3__p_1__term_3">notice</term> or authorisation was issued in terms of its Credit Control and Debt Collection Policy and the <ref href="/akn/za-cpt/act/by-law/2006/credit-control-debt-collection" eId="chp_8__sec_41__subsec_3__p_1__ref_1">Credit Control and Debt Collection By-law</ref>.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="chp_8__sec_42"><num>42.</num><heading>Impounding of <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_42__term_1">vessel</term>, <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_42__term_2">vehicle</term>, items or goods</heading><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_1__p_1">An <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> may, without a warrant, seize and impound a <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_1__p_1__term_2">vessel</term>, <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_1__p_1__term_3">vehicle</term>, items or goods which is concerned, or is on reasonable grounds believed to be concerned, with the commission of an offence in terms of this By-law.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><intro><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__intro__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term>, at the time of the impoundment, must give the holder of the impounded <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_2">vessel</term>, <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_3">vehicle</term>, items or goods an impoundment <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__intro__p_1__term_4">notice</term> setting out—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__para_a__p_1">the reason for the impoundment;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__para_b__p_1">a description of the impounded <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__para_b__p_1__term_1">vessel</term> or <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__para_b__p_1__term_2">vehicle</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__para_c__p_1">the address and contact details of the designated pound;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__para_d__p_1">the impoundment fee; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__para_e__p_1">a warning that the impounded <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__para_e__p_1__term_1">vessel</term> or <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_2__para_e__p_1__term_2">vehicle</term> may be sold to recover the impoundment fee and any fine, costs or damages.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_3__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_3__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> must cause an impounded <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_3__p_1__term_2">vessel</term> or <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_3__p_1__term_3">vehicle</term> to be taken to a designated pound where it must be retained and dealt with in terms of this section.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_4"><num>(4)</num><intro><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_4__intro__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_4__intro__p_1__term_1">City</term> must release the impounded <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_4__intro__p_1__term_2">vessel</term>, <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_4__intro__p_1__term_3">vehicle</term>, items or goods to the owner upon presentation of proof of ownership if, in relation to the offence contemplated in subsection 1—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_4__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_4__para_a__p_1">a criminal charge is not laid, or a fine or a <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_4__para_a__p_1__term_1">notice</term> of intention to prosecute is not issued within 72 hours of the impoundment; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_4__para_b"><num>(b)</num><intro><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_4__para_b__intro__p_1">the criminal case against all accused persons is disposed of because—</p></intro><subparagraph eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_4__para_b__subpara_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_4__para_b__subpara_i__p_1">the charges are withdrawn;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_4__para_b__subpara_ii"><num>(ii)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_4__para_b__subpara_ii__p_1">the accused persons are acquitted; or</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_4__para_b__subpara_iii"><num>(iii)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_4__para_b__subpara_iii__p_1">the accused persons are convicted and either the impoundment fee and any fine, costs and damages are paid.</p></content></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_5"><num>(5)</num><intro><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_5__intro__p_1">An impounded <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_5__intro__p_1__term_1">vessel</term>, <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_5__intro__p_1__term_2">vehicle</term>, items or goods is forfeited to the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_5__intro__p_1__term_3">City</term> and becomes the property of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_5__intro__p_1__term_4">City</term> if—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_5__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_5__para_a__p_1">a court orders such forfeiture; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_5__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_5__para_b__p_1">the lawful owner of the <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_5__para_b__p_1__term_1">vessel</term>, <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_5__para_b__p_1__term_2">vehicle</term>, items or goods cannot be traced within 90 days of such impoundment after reasonable efforts to trace the owner have not been successful.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_6"><num>(6)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_6__p_1">If any payment contemplated in subsection (4)(b)(iii) is not made within such time as the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_6__p_1__term_1">City</term> may determine, and if no appeal has been lodged at the expiry of the time limit for an appeal, the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_6__p_1__term_2">City</term> may sell an impounded <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_6__p_1__term_3">vessel</term>, <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_6__p_1__term_4">vehicle</term>, items or goods and deal with any net proceeds in accordance with subsection 7.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_7"><num>(7)</num><intro><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_7__intro__p_1">Any net proceeds from the sale of an impounded <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_7__intro__p_1__term_1">vessel</term>, <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_7__intro__p_1__term_2">vehicle</term>, items or goods must be applied as follows and in this order:</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_7__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_7__para_a__p_1">the recovery of costs incurred by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_7__para_a__p_1__term_1">City</term> during forfeiture and impoundment;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_7__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_7__para_b__p_1">the payment of the impoundment fee, and any fine, costs or damages ordered by a court in relation to an offence contemplated in subsection 1; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_7__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_7__para_c__p_1">return to the person who lawfully owned the <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_7__para_c__p_1__term_1">vessel</term>, <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_7__para_c__p_1__term_2">vehicle</term>, items or goods at the time of the impoundment except where the <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_7__para_c__p_1__term_3">vessel</term>, <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_7__para_c__p_1__term_4">vehicle</term>, items or goods was forfeited to the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_7__para_c__p_1__term_5">City</term>.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_8"><num>(8)</num><content><p eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_8__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_8__sec_42__subsec_8__p_1__term_1">City</term> may determine an impoundment fee and designate a pound contemplated in this section.</p></content></subsection></section></chapter><chapter eId="chp_9"><num>9</num><heading>Offences and penalties</heading><section eId="chp_9__sec_43"><num>43.</num><heading>Offences</heading><subsection eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__intro__p_1">Any person who—</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">contravenes a provision of this By-law;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">contravenes any conditions, restrictions or prohibitions imposed in terms of this By-law;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">fails to comply with the terms of any <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_c__p_1__term_1">notice</term> or signage displayed in terms of this By-law;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_d__p_1">contravenes a lawful instruction given by an <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_d__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> in terms of this By-law;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_e__p_1">threatens, obstructs, hinders or uses abusive language to an <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_e__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> or a person lawfully accompanying the <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_e__p_1__term_2">authorised official</term> in the exercise of a power conferred in terms this By-law;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_f__p_1">when called upon by an <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_f__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> to furnish information, furnishes false or misleading information; or</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_g"><num>(g)</num><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_g__p_1">falsely holds himself or herself to be an <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_g__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> or a person authorised to act on behalf of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__para_g__p_1__term_2">City</term> in terms of this By-law;</p></content></paragraph><wrapUp><p eId="chp_9__sec_43__subsec_1__wrapup__p_1">commits an offence.</p></wrapUp></subsection></section><section eId="chp_9__sec_44"><num>44.</num><heading>Penalties</heading><subsection eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_1__p_1">Any person who commits an offence referred to in <ref href="#chp_9__sec_43" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_1__p_1__ref_1">section 43</ref> is liable to a fine or upon conviction to imprisonment for a period not exceeding 2 years or to such imprisonment without the option of a fine, or to both such fine and such imprisonment.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><intro><p eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_2__intro__p_1">In addition to imposing a fine or imprisonment, a court may order any person convicted of an offence in terms of this By-law —</p></intro><paragraph eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_2__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_2__para_a__p_1">to rectify the harm caused;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_2__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_2__para_b__p_1">to forfeit to the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_2__para_b__p_1__term_1">City</term> a <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_2__para_b__p_1__term_2">vessel</term> or <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_2__para_b__p_1__term_3">vehicle</term> impounded in terms of <ref href="#chp_8__sec_42" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_2__para_b__p_1__ref_1">section 42</ref>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_2__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_2__para_c__p_1">to pay the costs incurred by the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_2__para_c__p_1__term_1">City</term> as a consequence of the contravention; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_2__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_2__para_d__p_1">to pay damages for harm caused to another person or property within the <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_2__para_d__p_1__term_1">nature reserve</term>, which order shall have the force and effect of a civil judgment.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_3__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_3__p_1__term_1">City</term> may ban any person who fails to comply with any provisions of this By-law from entering any <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_3__p_1__term_2">nature reserve</term>(s) for a determined period of time.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_4"><num>(4)</num><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_4__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_4__p_1__term_1">City</term> may restrict access to a <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_4__p_1__term_2">vessel</term> or <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_4__p_1__term_3">vehicle</term> that fails to comply with any provisions of this By-law from entering a <term refersTo="#term-nature_reserve" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_4__p_1__term_4">nature reserve</term> for a determined period of time.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_5"><num>(5)</num><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_5__p_1">A ban imposed in terms of subsections (3) and (4) must be reduced to writing and served on the person or owner of the <term refersTo="#term-vessel" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_5__p_1__term_1">vessel</term> or <term refersTo="#term-vehicle" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_5__p_1__term_2">vehicle</term>.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_6"><num>(6)</num><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_6__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_6__p_1__term_1">City</term> must provide a person contemplated above with a written <term refersTo="#term-notice" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_6__p_1__term_2">notice</term> of its intention to ban such person in terms of <ref href="#chp_9__sec_44" eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_6__p_1__ref_1">section 44</ref> (3). Such a person has 7 days to provide reasons why the City should not ban such person.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_7"><num>(7)</num><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_44__subsec_7__p_1">A person who has been banned in terms of subsections (3) and (4) above may make written representations to the Director Environmental Management as to why the ban should be lifted or reduced in length within 48 hours of the receipt thereof.</p></content></subsection></section><section eId="chp_9__sec_45"><num>45.</num><heading>Appeals</heading><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_45__p_1">Any person may appeal against an administrative decision taken by an <term refersTo="#term-authorised_official" eId="chp_9__sec_45__p_1__term_1">authorised official</term> in terms of this By-law in accordance with the provisions of section 62 of the Local Government: Municipal Systems Act, 2000 (<ref href="/akn/za/act/2000/32" eId="chp_9__sec_45__p_1__ref_1">Act No. 32 of 2000</ref>).</p></content></section><section eId="chp_9__sec_46"><num>46.</num><heading>Delegation</heading><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_46__p_1">A function, power or duty conferred on the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_9__sec_46__p_1__term_1">City</term> in terms of this By-law may be delegated or sub-delegated to an employee of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_9__sec_46__p_1__term_2">City</term> in accordance with the system of delegation adopted by the Municipal Council of the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_9__sec_46__p_1__term_3">City</term> in accordance with section 59 of the Local Government: Municipal Systems Act, 2000. (<ref href="/akn/za/act/2000/32" eId="chp_9__sec_46__p_1__ref_1">Act 32 of 2000</ref>).</p></content></section><section eId="chp_9__sec_47"><num>47.</num><heading>Indemnity</heading><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_47__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_9__sec_47__p_1__term_1">City</term> and authorised officials are not liable for any loss sustained by or damage caused to a person by an act or omission in good faith relating to the performance of a duty under this By-law, unless gross negligence is proved.</p></content></section><section eId="chp_9__sec_48"><num>48.</num><heading>Short title and commencement</heading><content><p eId="chp_9__sec_48__p_1">This By-law is called the <term refersTo="#term-City" eId="chp_9__sec_48__p_1__term_1">City</term> of Cape Town: Nature Reserve By-law, 2020 and comes into operation on promulgation in the Provincial Gazette.</p></content></section></chapter></body><attachments><attachment eId="att_1"><heading>Annexure A</heading><doc name="schedule"><meta><identification source="#Laws-Africa"><FRBRWork><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-cpt/act/by-law/2021/nature-reserve/!schedule_1"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-cpt/act/by-law/2021/nature-reserve"/><FRBRalias value="Annexure A" name="title"/><FRBRdate date="2021" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/><FRBRcountry value="za-cpt"/><FRBRsubtype value="by-law"/><FRBRnumber value="nature-reserve"/></FRBRWork><FRBRExpression><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-cpt/act/by-law/2021/nature-reserve/eng@2021-02-18/!schedule_1"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-cpt/act/by-law/2021/nature-reserve/eng@2021-02-18"/><FRBRdate date="2021-02-18" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/><FRBRlanguage language="eng"/></FRBRExpression><FRBRManifestation><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-cpt/act/by-law/2021/nature-reserve/eng@2021-02-18/!schedule_1"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-cpt/act/by-law/2021/nature-reserve/eng@2021-02-18"/><FRBRdate date="2021-11-06" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/></FRBRManifestation></identification></meta><mainBody><p eId="att_1__p_1"><img src="media/Picture1.jpg"/></p><p eId="att_1__p_2"><img src="media/Picture2.jpg"/></p><table eId="att_1__table_1"><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_1"><b>No.</b></p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_2"><b>Interpretation of symbol</b></p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_3"><b>Betekenis van simbool</b></p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_4"><b>Intsingiselo yomqondiso</b></p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_5">1.</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_6">Stay on boardwalk</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_7">Bly of plankpad</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_8">Hamba kwibhulorho yabahambi ngeenyawo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_9">2</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_10">Stay on pathways</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_11">Bly op voetpaaie</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_12">Hamba kwiindledlana zenyawo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_13">3</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_14">Hiking / walking</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_15">Staproete</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_16">Kuyahayikwa/kuyahanjwa</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_17">4</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_18">Guided walk</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_19">Begeleide staproete</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_20">Uhambo olukhokhelwayo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_21">5</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_22">Trail running</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_23">Drafroete</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_24">Umzila wokubaleka</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_25">6</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_26">Scenic views</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_27">Mooi uitsig</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_28">Umbono obukekayo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_29">7</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_30">Pathway</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_31">Voetpad</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_32">Indlela yeenyawo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_33">8</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_34">Dog free-running area</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_35">Gebied vir loslopende honde</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_36">Ummandla wokubaleka izinja ezingabotshelelwanga</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_37">9</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_38">Dogs on leash</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_39">Honde aan leiband</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_40">Izinja ezibotshelelwayo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_41">10</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_42">No dogs allowed</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_43">Geen honde toegelaat nie</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_44">Azivumelekanga izinja</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_45">11</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_46">Poop scoop area</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_47">Bollieskoppie-gebied</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_48">Ummandla wokukha ilindle lezinj</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_49">12</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_50">No driftlines</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_51">Dryflyne verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_52">Azikho iintambo zokuloba</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_53">13</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_54">Bag limits</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_55">Sakbeperkings</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_56">Size limits Groottebeperkings Ubukhulu bomda</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_57">14</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_58">Size limits</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_59">Groottebeperkings</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_60">Ubukhulu bomda</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_61">15</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_62">Beware of falling branches</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_63">Pasop vir vallende takke</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_64">Lumkela amasebe awayo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_65">16</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_66">Restaurant</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_67">Restaurant</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_68">Irestyurenti</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_69">17</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_70">No camping</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_71">Kamp verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_72">Akuvumelekanga ukukhempisha</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_73">18</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_74">No hiking/walking</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_75">Stap verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_76">Akuhayikwa/akahanjwa</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_77">19</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_78">Fires in demarcated areas</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_79">Vuurmaak in afgebakende gebiede</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_80">Imililo kwimimandla ekhethiweyo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_81">20</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_82">Braais allowed</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_83">Braaiers toegelaat</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_84">Ukoja kuvumelekile</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_85">21</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_86">No fires</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_87">Vuurmaak verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_88">Akubaswa mililo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_89">22</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_90">No fires or gas braais</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_91">Vuurmaak en gasbraaiers verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_92">Akubaswa mililo okanye iizitovu zerhasi</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_93">23</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_94">No overnighting</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_95">Oornagverblyf verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_96">Akulalwa</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_97">24</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_98">No alcohol</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_99">Alkohol verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_100">Akuselwa tywala</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_101">25</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_102">No firearms</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_103">Vuurwapens verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_104">Imipu ayivumelekanga</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_105">26</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_106">No hunting</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_107">Jag verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_108">Akuzingelwa</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_109">27</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_110">No dumping</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_111">Afvalstorting verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_112">Akulahlwa nkunkuma</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_113">28</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_114">No sand-mining</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_115">Sandmynery verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_116">Akwembiwa santi</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_117">29</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_118">No music</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_119">Musiek verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_120">Awuvumelekanga umculo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_121">30</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_122">Playground</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_123">Speelgrond</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_124">Indawo yokudlala/ibala lokudlala</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_125">31</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_126">No smoking</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_127">Rook verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_128">Akutshaywa</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_129">32</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_130">Do not leave valuables in vehicle</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_131">Moenie kosbare items in voertuig los nie</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_132">Musa ukushiya izinto zexabiso emotweni</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_133">33</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_134">Safeguard valuables</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_135">Beveilig kosbare items</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_136">Zigade izinto ezixabisekileyo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_137">34</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_138">Café</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_139">Kafee</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_140">Ikhefi</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_141">35</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_142">Administration office</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_143">Administrasiekantoor</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_144">I-ofisi yolawu</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_145">36</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_146">No lighting matches / fires</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_147">Vuurmaak / aansteek van vuurhoutjies verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_148">Akulayitwa imatshisi / imililo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_149">37</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_150">Fishing</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_151">Hengel</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_152">Ukuloba</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_153">38</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_154">Fishing with permit only</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_155">Hengel slegs met permit</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_156">Kulotywa ngemvume kuphela</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_157">39</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_158">No fishing</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_159">Hengel verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_160">Akulotywa</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_161">40</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_162">No treble hooks</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_163">Drie-angelhoeke verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_164">Akukho magwegwe okuloba</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_165">41</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_166">No fishing off bridges</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_167">Hengel van brug af verbode Akulotywa ngakwiibhlorho</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_168">Akulotywa ngakwiibhlorho</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_169">42</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_170">No fishing at night</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_171">Hengel snags verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_172">Akulotywa ebusuku</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_173">43</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_174">No fishing with nets</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_175">Hengel met nette verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_176">Akulotywa ngeminatha</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_177">44</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_178">No prawn pumping</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_179">Pomp van garnale verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_180">Akuvumelekanga ukumpontshwa</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_181">45</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_182">No bait collection</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_183">Uithaal van aas verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_184">Akubheyithwa</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_185">46</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_186">No use of live bait</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_187">Gebruik van lewende aas verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_188">Akusetyenziswa izinto eziphilayo xa uloba</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_189">47</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_190">No lobster fishing</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_191">Uithaal van kreef verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_192">Akulotywa zilobster</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_193">48</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_194">Conservation office</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_195">Bewaringskantoor</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_196">I-ofisi yolondolozo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_197">49</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_198">Beach</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_199">Strand</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_200">Ulwandle</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_201">50</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_202">No boats of any kind allowed</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_203">Alle soorte bote verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_204">Akuvumelekanga naluphi na uhlobo lwesikhephe</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_205">51</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_206">Windsurfing</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_207">Seilplankry</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_208">Ukusefa</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_209">52</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_210">Coffee shop</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_211">Koffiewinkel</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_212">Ivenkile yekofu</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_213">53</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_214">Play area</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_215">Speelarea</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_216">Ummandla wokudlala</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_217">54</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_218">Safety boots</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_219">Veiligheidstewels</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_220">Iibhutsi zokhuseleko</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_221">55</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_222">Restrooms</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_223">Kleedkamers</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_224">Amagumbi angasese</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_225">56</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_226">Female restroom</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_227">Kleedkamer vir vroue</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_228">Igumbi langasese labasetyhini</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_229">57</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_230">Male restroom</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_231">Kleedkamer vir mans</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_232">Igumbi langasese lamadoda</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_233">58</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_234">Restaurant</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_235">Restaurant</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_236">Irestyurenti</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_237">59</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_238">Picnic area</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_239">Piekniekgebied</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_240">Ummandla wepiknikhi</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_241">60</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_242">Use litterbins</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_243">Gebruik vullisdromme</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_244">Sebenzisa imigqomo yenkunkuma</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_245">61</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_246">Bin free area. Do not litter</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_247">Dromlose gebied. Rommelstrooiery verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_248">Ummandla wemigqomo. Musa ukulahla phantsi inkunkuma</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_249">62</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_250">Education facilities</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_251">Opvoedingsfasiliteite</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_252">Amaziko emfundo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_253">63</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_254">Overnight education facilities</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_255">Oornag-opvoedingsfasiliteite</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_256">Amaziko emfundo asebusuku</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_257">64</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_258">Accommodation</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_259">Verblyf</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_260">Indawo yokuhlala</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_261">65</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_262">Permit needed</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_263">Permit benodig</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_264">Imvume iyafuneka</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_265">66</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_266">Beware of snakes</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_267">Pasop vir slange</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_268">Lumkela iinyoka</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_269">67</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_270">Kite surfing</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_271">Vlieërski</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_272">Ukubhajiswa kweekayiti</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_273">68</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_274">No kite surfing</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_275">Vlieërski verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_276">Akubhajiswa iikayiti</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_277">69</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_278">No mooring of vessels</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_279">Vasmeer van vaartuie verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_280">Akuvumelekanga ukubotshelelwa kweenqanawa</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_281">70</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_282">Gift shop</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_283">Geskenkwinkel</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_284">Ivenkile yezipho</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_285">71</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_286">Cannon</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_287">Kanon</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_288">Inkanunu</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_289">72</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_290">Safety gloves</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_291">Veiligheidshandskoene</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_292">Igloves zokuzikhusela</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_293">73</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_294">Wheelchair access</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_295">Rolstoeltoegang</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_296">Indawo yokungena abakhubazekileyo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_297">74</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_298">Parking</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_299">Parkering</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_300">Ipaki</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_301">75</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_302">Visitors parking</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_303">Besoekersparkering</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_304">Ipaki yendwendwe</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_305">76</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_306">No parking</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_307">Parkering verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_308">Akupakwa</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_309">77</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_310">Information</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_311">Inligting</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_312">Iinkcukacha</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_313">78</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_314">Speed limit</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_315">Spoedbeperking</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_316">Isantya somgaqo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_317">79</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_318">No access</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_319">Geen toegang nie</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_320">Akungenwa</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_321">80</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_322">No vehicles</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_323">Voertuie verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_324">Azivumelekanga izithuthi</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_325">81</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_326">No off-road vehicles</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_327">Veldvoertuie verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_328">Azivumelekanga izithuthi ezinkulu (offroad vehicles)</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_329">82</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_330">No mountain bikes</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_331">Bergfietse verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_332">Azivumelekanga iibhayisekile ezihamba ezintabeni</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_333">83</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_334">No driving on sand dunes</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_335">Bestuur op sandduine verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_336">Akuqhutywa kwiingqumba zesanti</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_337">84</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_338">Canoeing allowed</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_339">Kanovaart toegelaat</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_340">Kuvumelekile ukuhamba ngephenyane</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_341">85</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_342">No canoeing</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_343">Kanovaart verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_344">Akuvumelekanga ukuhamba ngephenyane</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_345">86</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_346">Jet skis prohibited</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_347">Waterponies verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_348">Azivumelekanga izithuthuthu zokudlala emanzini</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_349">87</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_350">No water skiing</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_351">Waterski verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_352">Akuvumelekanga ukutyibiliza emanzini</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_353">88</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_354">No defecating</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_355">Ontlasting verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_356">Akuvumelekanga ukuzithuma</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_357">89</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_358">Nature garden</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_359">Natuurtuin</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_360">Igadi yotyani</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_361">90</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_362">Unique flora and fauna</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_363">Unieke flora en fauna</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_364">Izityalo kunye nezilwanyana ezizodwa</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_365">91</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_366">Swimming allowed</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_367">Swem toegelaat</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_368">Kuvumelekile ukuqubha</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_369">92</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_370">Swimming is dangerous</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_371">Gevaarlike swemgebied</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_372">Kuyingozi ukuqubha</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_373">93</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_374">No swimming</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_375">Swem verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_376">Akuqujwa</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_377">94</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_378">Windsurfing</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_379">Seilplankry</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_380">Ukusefa</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_381">95</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_382">Water skiing</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_383">Waterski</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_384">Umdlalo wokutyibiliza emanzini</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_385">96</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_386">Boat launch</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_387">Boot-tewaterlating</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_388">Ukuphehlelelwa kwezikhephe</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_389">97</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_390">Motor boating</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_391">Motorbootry</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_392">Ukuqhuba isikhephe</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_393">98</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_394">Sailing</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_395">Seiljagry</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_396">Ukuhamba ngenqanawa</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_397">99</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_398">No sailing</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_399">Seiljagry verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_400">Akuhanjwa ngenqanawa</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_401">100</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_402">Natural pool</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_403">Natuurpoel</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_404">Ipuli eyenziwe ngendalo yokusingqongileyo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_405">101</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_406">Boma</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_407">Boma</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_408">Ibhoma</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_409">102</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_410">Power boats allowed</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_411">Kragbote toegelaat</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_412">Izikhephe ezinesantya esiphezulu zivumelekile</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_413">103</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_414">No power boats</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_415">Kragbote verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_416">Azivumelekanga izikhephe ezinesantya esiphezulu</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_417">104</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_418">Electric boats allowed</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_419">Elektriese bote toegelaat</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_420">Zivumelekile izikhephe zombane</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_421">105</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_422">No electric boats</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_423">Elektriese bote verbode</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_424">Azivumelekanga izikhephe zombane</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_425">106</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_426">Water bottle</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_427">Waterbottel</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_428">Ibhotile yamanzi</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_429">107</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_430">Sun hat</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_431">Sonhoed</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_432">Isigqoko selanga</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_433">108</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_434">Tortoises</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_435">Skilpaaie</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_436">Ufudo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_437">109</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_438">Do not pick flora</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_439">Moenie flora pluk nie</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_440">Musa ukuzithatha izityalo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_441">110</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_442">Useful plants</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_443">Nuttige plante</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_444">Izityalo ezibalulekileyo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_445">111</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_446">Unique vegetation</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_447">Unieke plantegroei</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_448">Izityalo ezahlukileyo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_449">112</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_450">Nature appreciation</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_451">Natuurwaardering</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_452">Ukuxabisa indalo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_453">113</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_454">Do not damage fauna or flora</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_455">Moenie fauna of flora beskadig nie</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_456">Musa ukuzimosha izilwanyana okanye izityalo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_457">114</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_458">General fauna</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_459">Algemene fauna</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_460">Izilwanyana ezizintlobo zonke</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_461">115</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_462">Bird viewing</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_463">Voëlkyk</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_464">Ukubukela iintaka</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_465">116</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_466">Bird hide</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_467">Voëlskuiling</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_468">Indlwana yokubukela iintaka</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_469">117</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_470">Do not feed the animals</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_471">Moenie diere voer nie</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_472">Musa ukutyisa izilwanyana</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_473">118</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_474">Photos allowed</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_475">Foto’s toegelaat</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_476">Ifoto zivumelekile</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_477">119</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_478">Discovery trail</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_479">Ontdekkingsroete</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_480">Ukufunyanwa komkhondo</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_481">120</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_482">Whale watching</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_483">Walviskyk</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_484">Ukubukela umnenga</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_485">121</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_486">Horse riding</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_487">Perdry</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_488">Ukukhwela ihashe</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_489">122</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_490">Camping</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_491">Kampering</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_492">Ukumisa inkampu</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_493">123</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_494">4×4</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_495">4×4</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_496">4×4</p></td></tr><tr><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_497">124</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_498">Cellphone</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_499">Selfoon</p></td><td><p eId="att_1__table_1__p_500">Iselula</p></td></tr></table></mainBody></doc></attachment></attachments></act></akomaNtoso>