<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><act name="act"><meta><identification source="#Laws-Africa"><FRBRWork><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/indigent-support/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/indigent-support"/><FRBRalias value="Indigent Support" name="title"/><FRBRdate date="2017" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/><FRBRcountry value="za-ec443"/><FRBRsubtype value="by-law"/><FRBRnumber value="indigent-support"/></FRBRWork><FRBRExpression><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/indigent-support/eng@2017-04-24/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/indigent-support/eng@2017-04-24"/><FRBRdate date="2017-04-24" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/><FRBRlanguage language="eng"/></FRBRExpression><FRBRManifestation><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/indigent-support/eng@2017-04-24/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/indigent-support/eng@2017-04-24"/><FRBRdate date="2022-08-08" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/></FRBRManifestation></identification><publication showAs="Eastern Cape Provincial Gazette" name="Eastern Cape Provincial Gazette" date="2017-04-24" number="3830"/><references source="#Laws-Africa"><TLCOrganization eId="Laws-Africa" href="https://edit.laws.africa" showAs="Laws.Africa"/></references></meta><preface><p eId="preface__p_1">The Municipal Manager of Mbizana Local Municipality hereby publishes in terms of Section 13 of the Local Government Municipal Systems Act, 2000 (<ref href="/akn/za/act/2000/32" eId="preface__p_1__ref_1">Act 32 of 2000</ref>) read with Section 162 of the <ref href="/akn/za/act/1996/constitution" eId="preface__p_1__ref_2">Constitution of the Republic of South Africa, 1996</ref> (<ref href="/akn/za/act/1996/constitution" eId="preface__p_1__ref_3">Act 108 of 1996</ref>) the Indigent Support By-Law which shall come into operation on the date of publication hereof.</p></preface><preamble><p eId="preamble__p_1">AND WHEREAS National Government has a constitutional duty to provide an equitable share of nationally raised revenue to municipalities.</p><p eId="preamble__p_2">AND WHEREAS the aforesaid equitable share enables municipalities to provide basic services to poorer communities in an affordable manner and administrative capacity to ensure democratic governance at the local level.</p><p eId="preamble__p_3">AND WHEREAS Section 74 of the Local Government: Municipal Systems Act 2000 requires a Municipal Council to adopt and implement a Tariff Policy which must, inter alia, take into consideration the extent of subsidisation of tariffs for poor households.</p><p eId="preamble__p_4">The Council hereby publishes the following by-laws:</p></preamble><body><section xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0" eId="sec_1"><num>1.</num><heading>Definitions</heading><content><p eId="sec_1__p_1">For the purposes of these by-laws:</p><p refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_1__p_2">"<def refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_1__p_2__def_1">Council</def>" means the Council of the <term refersTo="#term-Municipality" eId="sec_1__p_2__term_1">Municipality</term> of Mbizana and includes any duly authorised political structure or office bearer as defined in the Local Government: Municipal Finance Management <ref href="/akn/za/act/2003/56" eId="sec_1__p_2__ref_1">Act 56 of 2003</ref> and/or any duly authorised official of the Council;</p><p refersTo="#term-Gender" eId="sec_1__p_3">"<def refersTo="#term-Gender" eId="sec_1__p_3__def_1">Gender</def>" any reference to the one gender shall include reference to the other</p><p refersTo="#term-Household_Income" eId="sec_1__p_4">"<def refersTo="#term-Household_Income" eId="sec_1__p_4__def_1">Household Income</def>" means all sources of income being formal and/ or informal of nature including, but not restricted to, salaries, revenue generated, pensions, fixed deposits, investments, state subsidies and or grants, private financial support/contributions from outside the indigent household;</p><p refersTo="#term-Indigent" eId="sec_1__p_5">"<def refersTo="#term-Indigent" eId="sec_1__p_5__def_1">Indigent</def>" means an indigent household whose total household income is as determined by <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_1__p_5__term_1">Council</term> annually during the budget process</p><blockList refersTo="#term-Indigent_debtor" eId="sec_1__list_1"><listIntroduction eId="sec_1__list_1__intro_1">"<def refersTo="#term-Indigent_debtor" eId="sec_1__list_1__intro_1__def_1">Indigent debtor</def>" means the head of an indigent household, inclusive of destitute indigents and indigents, being old age pensioners, the unemployed and households with a total monthly income as determined in the <term refersTo="#term-Indigent_Support_Policy" eId="sec_1__list_1__intro_1__term_1">Indigent Support Policy</term>:</listIntroduction><item eId="sec_1__list_1__item_a"><num>(a)</num><p eId="sec_1__list_1__item_a__p_1">Who applies for the provision of services from the municipality; and</p></item><item eId="sec_1__list_1__item_b"><num>(b)</num><p eId="sec_1__list_1__item_b__p_1">Who makes application for indigent support in terms of these by-laws; and</p></item><item eId="sec_1__list_1__item_c"><num>(c)</num><p eId="sec_1__list_1__item_c__p_1">Who shall be regarded as the representative of all members of his/her household</p></item></blockList><p refersTo="#term-Indigent_Households" eId="sec_1__p_6">"<def refersTo="#term-Indigent_Households" eId="sec_1__p_6__def_1">Indigent Households</def>" shall include all individual residing at the residential premises of the indigent debtor, inclusive of destitute indigent and indigents, by whom and for which application is made, which premises has access to municipal services;</p><blockList refersTo="#term-Indigent_Support_Policy" eId="sec_1__list_2"><listIntroduction eId="sec_1__list_2__intro_1">"<def refersTo="#term-Indigent_Support_Policy" eId="sec_1__list_2__intro_1__def_1">Indigent Support Policy</def>" means the policy for the provision of indigent subsidies to qualifying indigent debtors in terms of the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_1__list_2__intro_1__term_1">Council</term>’s policy relating to the following:</listIntroduction><item eId="sec_1__list_2__item_a"><num>(a)</num><p eId="sec_1__list_2__item_a__p_1">Free basic electrify</p></item><item eId="sec_1__list_2__item_b"><num>(b)</num><p eId="sec_1__list_2__item_b__p_1">Free basic water</p></item><item eId="sec_1__list_2__item_c"><num>(c)</num><p eId="sec_1__list_2__item_c__p_1">Subsidised sewerage rates and refuse</p></item><item eId="sec_1__list_2__item_d"><num>(d)</num><p eId="sec_1__list_2__item_d__p_1">Assisted arrear debt recovery programme</p></item><listWrapUp eId="sec_1__list_2__wrapup_1">as determined by <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_1__list_2__wrapup_1__term_1">Council</term> annually during the budget process, in line with National norm and guidelines;</listWrapUp></blockList><p refersTo="#term-Municipality" eId="sec_1__p_7">"<def refersTo="#term-Municipality" eId="sec_1__p_7__def_1">Municipality</def>" means the Municipality of Mbizana, a local municipality established in terms of Section 12 of the Local Government: Municipal Structures Act 1998;</p><p refersTo="#term-Municipal_Manager" eId="sec_1__p_8">"<def refersTo="#term-Municipal_Manager" eId="sec_1__p_8__def_1">Municipal Manager</def>" means the Municipal Manager of the Mbizana Local <term refersTo="#term-Municipality" eId="sec_1__p_8__term_1">Municipality</term> or his/her nominee acting in terms of power delegated to him/her by the said Municipal Manager with the concurrence of the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_1__p_8__term_2">Council</term>;</p></content></section><section eId="sec_2"><num>2.</num><heading>Indigent Support Policy</heading><content><p eId="sec_2__p_1">The Council shall adopt an Indigent Support By-Law which shall embody an indigent support programme providing procedures and guidelines for the subsidisation of basic services and tariff charges to indigent households in its municipal area.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_3"><num>3.</num><intro><p eId="sec_3__intro__p_1">The object of the <term refersTo="#term-Indigent_Support_Policy" eId="sec_3__intro__p_1__term_1">Indigent Support Policy</term> will be to ensure:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_3__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_3__para_a__p_1">The provision of basic services to the community in a sustainable manner within the financial and administrative capacity of the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_3__para_a__p_1__term_1">Council</term>; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_3__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_3__para_b__p_1">The provision of procedures and guidelines for the subsidisation of basic service charges to indigent households.</p></content></paragraph></section><section eId="sec_4"><num>4.</num><heading>Guiding Principles</heading><intro><p eId="sec_4__intro__p_1">The following guiding principles shall be contained in the Indigent Support By-Law referred to in Section (1):</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_a__p_1">Relief will be provided by the Council to registered residential consumers of services who are declared indigent by the Council but subject to the condition that such consumers make a financial contribution towards the cost of the services provided by the Council to them on the basis determined by the Council.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_b__p_1">The Council shall, wherever possible, ensure that any relief provided to indigent consumers is constitutional, practical, fair, equitable and justifiable in order to avoid the alienation of any group of households.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_c__p_1">Differentiation between residential consumers shall, in accordance with the Tariff Policy of the Council, be permitted.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_d__p_1">Differentiation shall also be permitted in respect of the level of service provided to or to be provided to indigent households.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_e__p_1">The application of the indigent support subsidy for minimum service levels should not result in the creation of a massive bureaucratic administration that would not be cost effective to implement.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_f__p_1">A differentiation shall be made between those households who cannot afford to pay for basic services and those households who refuse to pay for such services.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_g"><num>(g)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_g__p_1">The payment for services rendered should be affordable for the indigent.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_h"><num>(h)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_h__p_1">The indigent support subsidy programme will apply during a predetermined period or financial year.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_i__p_1">Financial support to the indigent will be dependant upon the availability of funds to enable the Council to provide such support.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_j"><num>(j)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_j__p_1">The Council may, from time to time, review and amend the qualification criteria for indigent support provided by it.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_k"><num>(k)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_k__p_1">The collective or joint gross income of members of indigent households will always be taken into account to determine the level of financial support to be granted to indigent households gross income.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_l"><num>(l)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_l__p_1">Indigent households must formally apply on the prescribed application form for indigent support and will qualify for such support according to prescribed criteria/principles to be laid down by the Council.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_m"><num>(m)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_m__p_1">The household income must be correctly reflected on the application form requesting indigent support.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_n"><num>(n)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_n__p_1">The debtor who signs the prescribed application form shall be regarded, for accounting purposes, as the indigent debtor and the representative of the indigent household.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_o"><num>(o)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_o__p_1">After the application form for indigent support has been completed by an indigent debtor, an effective and efficient evaluation system should be used in order to obtain the result of such application within a reasonable time as determined by the Council.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_p"><num>(p)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_p__p_1">All approved indigent debtors should be registered on a database linked to the main debtors system of the Municipality.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_q"><num>(q)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_q__p_1">The onus will be on the approved indigent debtor to inform the Council of any change in his/her status or personal household circumstances.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_r"><num>(r)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_r__p_1">All indigent households should be re-evaluated after a period of six months or such period as the Council may determine to assess the provision of continued basic services and indigent support to them.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_s"><num>(s)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_s__p_1">Disciplinary measures decided by the Council, should be imposed on indigent debtors who misuse the indigent support programme of the Council and/or provide incorrect information to the Municipality.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_t"><num>(t)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_t__p_1">An approved community communications programme, embodying the principles of transparency and fairness, must be implemented in respect of the indigent support programme.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_u"><num>(u)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_u__p_1">Skills Training and other education related programmes must be introduced to develop the indigent to become self - sufficient and thereby reduce the rate of indigence.</p></content></paragraph></section><section eId="sec_5"><num>5.</num><heading>Qualification, Acceptance and Registration Criteria</heading><intro><p eId="sec_5__intro__p_1">The qualification, acceptance and registration criteria for indigent support and the services qualifying for such support shall be determined by resolution of the Council from time to time provided that, until the Council determines otherwise, registered residential consumers of services delivered by the Council shall qualify for indigent support, subject to the following conditions:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_5__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__para_a__p_1">the combined or joint gross income of all occupants/residents/dependants over the age of 18 years in a single household receiving services from the Council not exceeding R2 200 per month;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_5__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__para_b__p_1">the Council being satisfied that the single household referred to in sub-section (a) cannot, due to its indigent status, afford to pay for the services provided to it by the Council;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_5__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__para_c__p_1">the single household referred to in sub-section (a) being registered in the municipal data base of households receiving indigent support from the Council;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_5__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__para_d__p_1">any occupant/resident/dependant of the household referred to in sub-section (a) not owning any property in addition to the property in respect of which indigent support is provided in terms of Council’s indigent support programme;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_5__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__para_e__p_1">any occupant, resident or dependent in the household referred to in sub-section (a) not receiving any significant monetary benefit or regular monetary payment from any source whatsoever.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_5__para_f"><num>(f)</num><intro><p eId="sec_5__para_f__intro__p_1">The extent of the monthly indigent support granted to the Council to indigent households in its municipal area will be determined by resolution of the Council regard being had to its budgetary provisions and/or the amount received by it from Central Government divided by the number of recipients and a maximum of an average monthly service account in respect of the following services, fees or charges:</p></intro><subparagraph eId="sec_5__para_f__subpara_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__para_f__subpara_i__p_1">Water;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="sec_5__para_f__subpara_ii"><num>(ii)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__para_f__subpara_ii__p_1">Refuse collection;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="sec_5__para_f__subpara_iii"><num>(iii)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__para_f__subpara_iii__p_1">Electricity;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="sec_5__para_f__subpara_iv"><num>(iv)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__para_f__subpara_iv__p_1">Sewerage; and</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="sec_5__para_f__subpara_v"><num>(v)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__para_f__subpara_v__p_1">Housing Rentals</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="sec_5__para_f__subpara_vi"><num>(vi)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__para_f__subpara_vi__p_1">Assessment Rates on a residential property.</p></content></subparagraph></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_5__para_g"><num>(g)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__para_g__p_1">The Council will, on a six-monthly basis, assess the level of support to indigent households in its municipal area depending on the number of applicants qualifying for indigent support and its general financial position.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_5__para_h"><num>(h)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__para_h__p_1">The level of indigent support granted by the Council shall not exceed the monthly billings to the accounts of indigent debtors.</p></content></paragraph></section><section eId="sec_6"><num>6.</num><heading>Distribution of <term refersTo="#term-Indigent" eId="sec_6__term_1">Indigent</term> Support Subsidies</heading><intro><p eId="sec_6__intro__p_1"><term refersTo="#term-Indigent" eId="sec_6__intro__p_1__term_1">Indigent</term> Support Subsidies will be distributed by the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_6__intro__p_1__term_2">Council</term> on the following basis:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_6__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_6__para_a__p_1">Relief will only be distributed to those indigent households who apply and qualify therefor.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_6__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_6__para_b__p_1">The relief must be significant so as to relieve the recipient of an indigent subsidy from the financial hardship of paying fully for services received from the <term refersTo="#term-Municipality" eId="sec_6__para_b__p_1__term_1">Municipality</term> for a specific period.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_6__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_6__para_c__p_1">All registered indigent households will be charged the determined economical tariff or charge for a service.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_6__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_6__para_d__p_1">The recipient’s monthly account will be credited with the amount of the indigent subsidy as determined by the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_6__para_d__p_1__term_1">Council</term> on a monthly basis.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_6__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="sec_6__para_e__p_1"><term refersTo="#term-Indigent" eId="sec_6__para_e__p_1__term_1">Indigent</term> relief will initially be applied for a period of 6 months as determined by the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_6__para_e__p_1__term_2">Council</term>.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_6__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="sec_6__para_f__p_1"><term refersTo="#term-Indigent" eId="sec_6__para_f__p_1__term_1">Indigent</term> households may apply for continuation of the indigent relief granted by the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_6__para_f__p_1__term_2">Council</term> depending on their circumstances.</p></content></paragraph></section><section eId="sec_7"><num>7.</num><heading>Applications for <term refersTo="#term-Indigent" eId="sec_7__term_1">Indigent</term> Support</heading><intro><p eId="sec_7__intro__p_1">Applications for indigent support in terms of these by-laws must be made on the prescribed form which will, inter alia, contain the under-mentioned information which must be certified as being correct by the indigent debtor:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_7__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_7__para_a__p_1">Details of the indigent debtor’s service account or accounts;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_7__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_7__para_b__p_1">Proof of income;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_7__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_7__para_c__p_1">Proof of residence;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_7__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_7__para_d__p_1">Identity number of indigent debtor; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_7__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="sec_7__para_e__p_1">Number, names and identity numbers, where applicable, of dependants in an indigent household.</p></content></paragraph><wrapUp><p eId="sec_7__wrapup__p_1">The onus at all times to re-apply for continued relief or submit proof of change in circumstances rests on the indigent debtor.</p></wrapUp></section><section eId="sec_8"><num>8.</num><heading>Indigent Support Committee</heading><intro><p eId="sec_8__intro__p_1">The Council shall appoint a Committee to be known as the Indigent Support Committee for the purpose of administering its indigent support programme and such Committee shall:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_8__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_8__para_a__p_1">scrutinise with the aid of Ward Councillors, all applications received for indigent support in terms of the Council’s indigent support programme;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_8__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_8__para_b__p_1">recommend to the Council that applications received in terms of sub-section (a) either be approved or disapproved;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_8__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_8__para_c__p_1">monitor, in conjunction with Ward Councillors, Ward Committees and other persons or organisations it may appoint, the implementation of indigent support programme, subject to the policy directions of the Council and in consultation with the Municipal Manager;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_8__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_8__para_d__p_1">take suitable action against debtors in terms of Section 15 of these by-laws;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_8__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="sec_8__para_e__p_1">recommend to the Council amendments, additions or altered procedures in respect of the application of the Council’s indigent support programme;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_8__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="sec_8__para_f__p_1">undertake such inspections and issue such instructions as it may deem necessary in order to verify the information provided by any indigent debtor;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_8__para_g"><num>(g)</num><content><p eId="sec_8__para_g__p_1">perform such other duties as the Council may direct-</p></content></paragraph><wrapUp><p eId="sec_8__wrapup__p_1">provided that the Council may delegate any of its responsibilities in terms of these by-laws and it’s indigent support programme to the Committee either wholly or in part and subject to such conditions as it may determine.</p></wrapUp></section><section eId="sec_9"><num>9.</num><heading>Balance on service charges, tariffs and fees</heading><content><p eId="sec_9__p_1">Any balance owing by an indigent debtor, after deduction of the indigent support subsidy, shall be recovered from him/her in accordance with the Credit Control Policy of the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_9__p_1__term_1">Council</term>.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_10"><num>10.</num><heading>Advertising of <term refersTo="#term-Indigent" eId="sec_10__term_1">Indigent</term> Subsidies</heading><intro><p eId="sec_10__intro__p_1">For the purposes of transparency, the following key information on the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_10__intro__p_1__term_1">Council</term>’s indigent support programme should, where possible, and on a monthly basis, be displayed on the notice board at the cashier’s offices of the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_10__intro__p_1__term_2">Council</term>:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_10__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_10__para_a__p_1">Names of indigent debtors receiving indigent relief for a prescribed period;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_10__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_10__para_b__p_1">Stand numbers where services are rendered to recipient indigent debtors;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_10__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_10__para_c__p_1">Total household income of recipient indigent debtors; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_10__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_10__para_d__p_1">Number of dependants residing on the property of the recipient indigent debtor.</p></content></paragraph></section><section eId="sec_11"><num>11.</num><heading>Queries with regard to <term refersTo="#term-Indigent" eId="sec_11__term_1">Indigent</term> Subsidies</heading><content><p eId="sec_11__p_1">Any resident of the municipality may, in writing, addressed to the <term refersTo="#term-Municipal_Manager" eId="sec_11__p_1__term_1">Municipal Manager</term>, query the qualification of a recipient indigent debtor within 14 days from the date of publication of the notice referred to in Section 13 of these by-laws.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_12"><num>12.</num><intro><p eId="sec_12__intro__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-Municipal_Manager" eId="sec_12__intro__p_1__term_1">Municipal Manager</term> may refer queries referred to in Section 14 to the Committee for <term refersTo="#term-Indigent" eId="sec_12__intro__p_1__term_2">Indigent</term> Support which may take the following action:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_12__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_12__para_a__p_1">Request the indigent debtor against whom a query has been raised to provide full proof of his/her banking account and income details as well as pension registration;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_12__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_12__para_b__p_1">Undertake an inspection at the indigent debtor’s place of residence to determine his/her social conditions;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_12__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_12__para_c__p_1">Request a social welfare worker’s report on the indigent debtor’s household; and</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_12__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_12__para_d__p_1">Recommend to the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_12__para_d__p_1__term_1">Council</term> that the indigent status of the debtor be withdrawn.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_12__para_e"><num>(e)</num><intro><p eId="sec_12__para_e__intro__p_1">Such action as it may deem appropriate in the circumstances including a recommendation to the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_12__para_e__intro__p_1__term_1">Council</term> -</p></intro><subparagraph eId="sec_12__para_e__subpara_i"><num>(i)</num><content><p eId="sec_12__para_e__subpara_i__p_1">that the indigent status of the debtor be suspended for a defined period and subject to such conditions as it may determine;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="sec_12__para_e__subpara_ii"><num>(ii)</num><content><p eId="sec_12__para_e__subpara_ii__p_1">that irregular or excess payments of indigent subsidies be recovered from the indigent debtor by way of debiting such indigent debtor’s services account or accounts with such payments;</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="sec_12__para_e__subpara_iii"><num>(iii)</num><content><p eId="sec_12__para_e__subpara_iii__p_1">that normal credit control measures be applied to the indigent debtor in accordance with the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_12__para_e__subpara_iii__p_1__term_1">Council</term>’s Credit Control Policy; and</p></content></subparagraph><subparagraph eId="sec_12__para_e__subpara_iv"><num>(iv)</num><content><p eId="sec_12__para_e__subpara_iv__p_1">that criminal charges of theft or fraud be instituted against the indigent debtor.</p></content></subparagraph></paragraph></section><section eId="sec_13"><num>13.</num><content><p eId="sec_13__p_1">The Municipal Manager must, in writing, advise a complainant who lodges a query against an indigent debtor in terms of Section 14 of these by-laws of the result of such query.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_14"><num>14.</num><heading>Withdrawal of <term refersTo="#term-Indigent" eId="sec_14__term_1">Indigent</term> Status</heading><content><p eId="sec_14__p_1">The indigent status of a debtor shall not be withdrawn, suspended or altered in terms of these by-laws until and unless such debtor has been given an opportunity to be heard and make representations on the contemplated against him or her.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_15"><num>15.</num><heading>Special Tariff for services, amenities and properties</heading><intro><p eId="sec_15__intro__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_15__intro__p_1__term_1">Council</term> may determine special tariffs for the use by indigent residents, communities and organisations of the following services, amenities and properties, subject to the availability of funds and compliance with prescribed criteria which shall be determined by resolution of the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_15__intro__p_1__term_2">Council</term>:</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_15__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_15__para_a__p_1">Sports Grounds, Pools;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_15__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_15__para_b__p_1">Fire Protection;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_15__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_15__para_c__p_1">Transport;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_15__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_15__para_d__p_1">Museums;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_15__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="sec_15__para_e__p_1">Markets;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_15__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="sec_15__para_f__p_1">Agricultural Properties;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_15__para_g"><num>(g)</num><content><p eId="sec_15__para_g__p_1">Hiring of Halls;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_15__para_h"><num>(h)</num><content><p eId="sec_15__para_h__p_1">Cemeteries and Crematoria.</p></content></paragraph></section><section eId="sec_16"><num>16.</num><heading>Mayor’s Relief Fund</heading><content><p eId="sec_16__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_16__p_1__term_1">Council</term> shall annually make provision on its budget for an allocation of funds to be administered by the Mayor for the grant of special ad-hoc amounts to indigent households or residents of the municipality for the purchase of essential foodstuffs and household items subject to such conditions as the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_16__p_1__term_2">Council</term> may determine.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_17"><num>17.</num><heading>Responsibilities of <term refersTo="#term-Municipal_Manager" eId="sec_17__term_1">Municipal Manager</term></heading><intro><p eId="sec_17__intro__p_1">It shall be the responsibility of the <term refersTo="#term-Municipal_Manager" eId="sec_17__intro__p_1__term_1">Municipal Manager</term></p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_17__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_17__para_a__p_1">to create, maintain and update a register of all debtors receiving indigent support subsidies from the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_17__para_a__p_1__term_1">Council</term> in terms of these by-laws;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_17__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_17__para_b__p_1">to reflect the indigent status of debtors in the accounting records of the <term refersTo="#term-Municipality" eId="sec_17__para_b__p_1__term_1">Municipality</term>;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_17__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_17__para_c__p_1">to advise and keep indigent debtors informed of the approval, amendment, suspension or withdrawal of an application for indigent support in terms of these by-laws and the conditions under which such support will be granted, including the renewal of indigent support applications;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_17__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_17__para_d__p_1">to report any instances of misuse of the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_17__para_d__p_1__term_1">Council</term>’s <term refersTo="#term-Indigent" eId="sec_17__para_d__p_1__term_2">Indigent</term> Support Programme to the <term refersTo="#term-Indigent" eId="sec_17__para_d__p_1__term_3">Indigent</term> Support Committee for attention in terms of these by-laws;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_17__para_e"><num>(e)</num><content><p eId="sec_17__para_e__p_1">To report at regular intervals as may be required by the <term refersTo="#term-Indigent" eId="sec_17__para_e__p_1__term_1">Indigent</term> Support Committee on the progress or otherwise of the implementation of the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_17__para_e__p_1__term_2">Council</term>’s <term refersTo="#term-Indigent" eId="sec_17__para_e__p_1__term_3">Indigent</term> Support Programme.</p></content></paragraph></section><section eId="sec_18"><num>18.</num><heading>Budgeting for <term refersTo="#term-Indigent" eId="sec_18__term_1">Indigent</term> Support</heading><content><p eId="sec_18__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_18__p_1__term_1">Council</term> shall annually budget for the total indigent subsidy to be granted to indigent debtors in terms of these by-laws and such amount shall, upon approval of the budget of the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_18__p_1__term_2">Council</term>, be deposited in a special banking account in the name of the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_18__p_1__term_3">Council</term> and from which total monthly indigent subsidies will be withdrawn for crediting to the monthly services account or accounts of approved indigent debtors.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_19"><num>19.</num><heading>Amendment of <term refersTo="#term-Indigent_Support_Policy" eId="sec_19__term_1">Indigent Support Policy</term></heading><content><p eId="sec_19__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_19__p_1__term_1">Council</term> has the discretionary power to amend any clause, stipulation or tariff embodied in its <term refersTo="#term-Indigent_Support_Policy" eId="sec_19__p_1__term_2">Indigent Support Policy</term> in the interest of all the parties concerned.</p></content></section></body></act></akomaNtoso>