<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><act name="act"><meta><identification source="#Laws-Africa"><FRBRWork><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-eth/act/by-law/1957/parking-meter/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-eth/act/by-law/1957/parking-meter"/><FRBRalias value="Parking Meter" name="title"/><FRBRdate date="1957" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/><FRBRcountry value="za-eth"/><FRBRsubtype value="by-law"/><FRBRnumber value="parking-meter"/></FRBRWork><FRBRExpression><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-eth/act/by-law/1957/parking-meter/eng@1957-01-17/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-eth/act/by-law/1957/parking-meter/eng@1957-01-17"/><FRBRdate date="1957-01-17" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/><FRBRlanguage language="eng"/></FRBRExpression><FRBRManifestation><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-eth/act/by-law/1957/parking-meter/eng@1957-01-17/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-eth/act/by-law/1957/parking-meter/eng@1957-01-17"/><FRBRdate date="2020-10-14" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/></FRBRManifestation></identification><publication number="2749" name="KwaZulu-Natal Provincial Gazette" showAs="KwaZulu-Natal Provincial Gazette" date="1957-01-17"/><references source="#Laws-Africa"><TLCOrganization showAs="Laws.Africa" eId="Laws-Africa" href="https://edit.laws.africa"/><TLCTerm showAs="Council" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.Council" eId="term-Council"/><TLCTerm showAs="Metered Parking Bay" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.Metered_Parking_Bay" eId="term-Metered_Parking_Bay"/><TLCTerm showAs="Parking" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.Parking" eId="term-Parking"/><TLCTerm showAs="Parking Bay" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.Parking_Bay" eId="term-Parking_Bay"/><TLCTerm showAs="Parking Meter" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.Parking_Meter" eId="term-Parking_Meter"/><TLCTerm showAs="Prescribed Coin" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.Prescribed_Coin" eId="term-Prescribed_Coin"/><TLCTerm showAs="Vehicle" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.Vehicle" eId="term-Vehicle"/></references></meta><body><section eId="sec_1"><num>1.</num><heading>Application</heading><content><p eId="sec_1__p_1">The By-laws shall apply to the public streets and public places or portions thereof specified in terms of these By-laws; provided that any other By-laws of the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_1__p_1__term_1">Council</term> for the time being in force regulating and controlling the parking of vehicles in public streets or places shall continue to apply to a metered zone, except to the extent to which such By-laws are inconsistent or in conflict with any of the provisions of these By-laws.</p><p eId="sec_1__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[R. 1 amended by r. 1 of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1974/422" eId="sec_1__p_2__ref_1">PN 422 of 1974</ref>.]</remark></p></content></section><section eId="sec_1A"><num>1A.</num><heading>Nondiscrimination</heading><subsection eId="sec_1A__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="sec_1A__subsec_1__p_1">Subject to the provision of subsection (2) hereof, no provision of these By-laws shall be applied so as to discriminate between persons on the grounds of race, religion or gender nor shall it be so construed as to have the effect of authorising such discrimination.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_1A__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="sec_1A__subsec_2__p_1">Notwithstanding the provisions of subsection (1) hereof, discrimination on the grounds of gender may expressly be authorised in terms of any provisions of these Bylaws which prescribes the wearing of appropriate apparel in a public place or imposes a restriction upon the entry of persons into public ablution, toilet and change room facilities or prescribes different standards for such facilities.</p><p eId="sec_1A__subsec_2__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[R1A. inserted by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/mn/1992/43" eId="sec_1A__subsec_2__p_2__ref_1">MN 43 of 1992</ref>.]</remark></p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_2"><num>2.</num><heading>Definitions</heading><subsection eId="sec_2__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_1">For the purposes of these By-laws, unless the context otherwise requires:</p><p eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[Sub-r. (1) previously r. 2 amended by r. 1 of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1975/238" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_2__ref_1">PN 238 of 1975</ref>.]</remark></p><p refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_3">"<def refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_3__def_1">Council</def>" means the City Council of the City of Durban;</p><p refersTo="#term-Metered_Parking_Bay" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_4">"<def refersTo="#term-Metered_Parking_Bay" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_4__def_1">Metered Parking Bay</def>" means a parking bay in respect of which a parking meter has been installed;</p><p refersTo="#term-Parking" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_5">"<def refersTo="#term-Parking" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_5__def_1">Parking</def>" means the standing or waiting of a vehicle, whether occupied or not, in a public street or place and “park” and “parked” shall have a corresponding meaning;</p><p refersTo="#term-Parking_Bay" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_6">"<def refersTo="#term-Parking_Bay" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_6__def_1">Parking Bay</def>" means an area or space demarcated by means of parking lines, marked in accordance with the relevant provisions of Regulation 166 (1) of the Road Traffic Regulations published under <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1966/681" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_6__ref_1">Provincial Notice No. 681 of 1966</ref>, as amended from time to time.</p><p eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_7"><remark status="editorial">[Definition of “Parking Bay” substituted by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1961/45" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_7__ref_1">PN 45 of 1961</ref> and amended by para. (a) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1967/362" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_7__ref_2">PN 362 of 1967</ref> and by r. 2 of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1974/422" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_7__ref_3">PN 422 of 1974</ref>.]</remark></p><p refersTo="#term-Parking_Meter" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_8">"<def refersTo="#term-Parking_Meter" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_8__def_1">Parking Meter</def>" means any mechanical appliance or device designed for the purpose of automatically measuring and indicating the time within which a vehicle is or may be parked in a metered parking bay and includes the standard to which the meter is or may be affixed;</p><p refersTo="#term-Prescribed_Coin" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_9">"<def refersTo="#term-Prescribed_Coin" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_9__def_1">Prescribed Coin</def>" shall mean a coin of the Republic of South Africa being legal tender in terms of the South African Mint and Coinage Act, 1964 (<ref href="/akn/za/act/1964/78" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_9__ref_1">Act No. 78 of 1964</ref>) of the denomination indicated on the parking meter concerned.</p><p eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_10"><remark status="editorial">[Definition of “Prescribed Coin” amended by para (a) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1966/389" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_10__ref_1">PN 389 of 1966</ref> and substituted by r. 1 of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1972/290" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_10__ref_2">PN 290 of 1972</ref>]</remark></p><p refersTo="#term-Vehicle" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_11">"<def refersTo="#term-Vehicle" eId="sec_2__subsec_1__p_11__def_1">Vehicle</def>" means a contrivance that is equipped with wheels or revolving runners on which it moves or is moved, but shall not include a bicycle propelled by human power.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_2__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="sec_2__subsec_2__p_1">The words and phrases defined in the Road Traffic Ordinance, 1966 (Natal) (<ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/ord/1966/21" eId="sec_2__subsec_2__p_1__ref_1">Ordinance No. 21 of 1966</ref>) as amended and in Regulations made thereunder shall, when used in these By-laws have the same meanings unless inconsistent with the context.</p><p eId="sec_2__subsec_2__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[Sub-r. (2) inserted by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1975/238" eId="sec_2__subsec_2__p_2__ref_1">PN 238 of 1975</ref>.]</remark></p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_3"><num>3.</num><heading>Installation of parking meters</heading><subsection eId="sec_3__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="sec_3__subsec_1__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_3__subsec_1__p_1__term_1">Council</term> may by resolution install or cause to be installed a parking meter or meters at any demarcated parking bay or bays in any public street or place in the City.</p><p eId="sec_3__subsec_1__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[Sub-r. (1) substituted by r. 2 of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1972/290" eId="sec_3__subsec_1__p_2__ref_1">PN 290 of 1972</ref>.]</remark></p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_3__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><intro><p eId="sec_3__subsec_2__intro__p_1">Every such meter shall be placed upon and fastened to the kerb, footpath or sidewalk adjoining the parking bay or bays in respect of which it is installed, and each such meter shall—</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_3__subsec_2__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_3__subsec_2__para_a__p_1">clearly indicate the time allowed for parking in such metered parking bay and the prescribed coin or coins which may be inserted and shall clearly display a notice indicating that no parking shall take place in such metered parking if the meter is out of order, provided that where a meter is out of order, a hood may be securely place over the meter by an officer authorised by the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_3__subsec_2__para_a__p_1__term_1">Council</term> to enforce the provisions of these By-laws, such hood bearing a road traffic sign R9 (on a scale reduced to one-sixth of that prescribed in regulation 161 (1) of the Road Traffic Regulations published under <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1966/681" eId="sec_3__subsec_2__para_a__p_1__ref_1">Provincial Notice 681 of 1966</ref>.</p><p eId="sec_3__subsec_2__para_a__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[Para. (a) amended by r. 1 (i) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1977/36" eId="sec_3__subsec_2__para_a__p_2__ref_1">PN 36 of 1977</ref> and by r. 1 of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1982/376" eId="sec_3__subsec_2__para_a__p_2__ref_2">PN 376 of 1982</ref>.]</remark></p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_3__subsec_2__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_3__subsec_2__para_b__p_1">be fitted with an easily visible device (hereinafter referred to as an indicator) which shall indicate clearly that the time allowed for parking has expired or that the parking meter has not been set in operation, as the case may be.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_3__subsec_2__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_3__subsec_2__para_c__p_1">where the meter is not automatically activated by the insertion of a prescribed coin, shall clearly indicate the action to be taken in order to set the meter in operation once the prescribed coin has been inserted.</p><p eId="sec_3__subsec_2__para_c__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[Para. (c) inserted by r. (i) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1965/270" eId="sec_3__subsec_2__para_c__p_2__ref_1">PN 270 of 1965</ref> and deleted by r. 2 of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1975/238" eId="sec_3__subsec_2__para_c__p_2__ref_2">PN 238 of 1975</ref> and inserted by r. 1 (ii) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1977/36" eId="sec_3__subsec_2__para_c__p_2__ref_3">PN 36 of 1977</ref>.]</remark></p></content></paragraph></subsection></section><section eId="sec_4"><num>4.</num><heading>Method of parking</heading><intro><p eId="sec_4__intro__p_1">No driver or person in charge of a vehicle shall park such vehicle—</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_a__p_1">in a metered parking bay across any painted line marking the bay or in such a position that the said vehicle shall not be entirely within the area demarcated as a metered parking bay;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_b__p_1">in a metered parking bay which is already occupied by another vehicle;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_c__p_1">in a metered parking bay in contravention of any road traffic sign prohibiting the parking or stopping of vehicles in the street or portion of the street concerned.</p></content></paragraph><wrapUp><p eId="sec_4__wrapup__p_1"><remark status="editorial">[R. 4 amended by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1958/344" eId="sec_4__wrapup__p_1__ref_1">PN 344 of 1958</ref> and by r. (ii) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1965/270" eId="sec_4__wrapup__p_1__ref_2">PN 270 of 1965</ref> and substituted by r. 3 of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1975/238" eId="sec_4__wrapup__p_1__ref_3">PN 238 of 1975</ref>.]</remark></p></wrapUp></section><section eId="sec_5"><num>5.</num><heading>Payment of fees for parking</heading><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_1__p_1">When any vehicle shall be parked in a metered parking bay, the driver or person in charge of such vehicle shall forthwith deposit or cause to be deposited in the parking meter installed at such bay the prescribed coin or coins as indicated on such meter for the period of time during which he desires to park his vehicle in such bay and shall set the meter in operation, either by the insertion of the prescribed coin in where applicable, with the instructions appearing thereon. Thereupon the metered parking bay may be lawfully occupied by the vehicle during the period indicated on the parking meter, but no longer; provided that the driver or person in charge of such vehicle, may without payment, park the same during such time (if any) as may be indicated on the parking meter as being unexpired from its previous use.</p><p eId="sec_5__subsec_1__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[Sub-r. 1 amended by r. 2 (i) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1977/36" eId="sec_5__subsec_1__p_2__ref_1">PN 36 of 1977</ref>.]</remark></p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_2__p_1">Subject to the provisions of Subsection (3) hereof, the driver or person in charge of a vehicle may, immediately upon the expiration of any authorised period of parking, again deposit or cause to be deposited the prescribed coin or coins in the appropriate slot of the parking meter, and after the said meter has been set in operation, either by the insertion of the prescribed coin, or where applicable, in accordance with the instructions appearing thereon the said vehicle may lawfully occupy the metered parking bay for the further period indicated on the parking meter.</p><p eId="sec_5__subsec_2__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[Sub-r. (2) amended by r. (i) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1959/215" eId="sec_5__subsec_2__p_2__ref_1">PN 215 of 1959</ref> and by r. 2 (ii) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1977/36" eId="sec_5__subsec_2__p_2__ref_2">PN 36 of 1977</ref> and by r. 2 (i) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1982/376" eId="sec_5__subsec_2__p_2__ref_3">PN 376 of 1982</ref>.]</remark></p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_3__p_1">No person shall, either with or without the insertion of a fresh coin in the parking meter, leave a vehicle parked in a metered parking bay for a continuous period exceeding the maximum permissible parking time as indicated on the meter or return his vehicle to the same parking bay within 30 minutes calculated from the time the vehicle was moved therefrom.</p><p eId="sec_5__subsec_3__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[Sub-r. (3) previously sub-r. (4) inserted by r. (ii) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1959/215" eId="sec_5__subsec_3__p_2__ref_1">PN 215 of 1959</ref> and substituted by para (b) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1966/389" eId="sec_5__subsec_3__p_2__ref_2">PN 389 of 1966</ref> and by r. 3 of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1972/290" eId="sec_5__subsec_3__p_2__ref_3">PN 290 of 1972</ref> and amended by r. 2 (iii) in <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1977/36" eId="sec_5__subsec_3__p_2__ref_4">PN 36 of 1977</ref> and amended by r. 2 (ii) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1982/376" eId="sec_5__subsec_3__p_2__ref_5">PN 376 of 1982</ref>.]</remark></p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_4"><num>(4)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_4__p_1">Subject to the provisions of By-law 12, no driver or person in charge of any vehicle shall cause, allow, permit or suffer such vehicle to be or remain parked in a metered parking bay while the indicator of the parking meter installed thereat shows that the time has expired or that the parking meter has not been set in operation either by the insertion of the prescribed coin or, where applicable in accordance with the instructions appearing thereon.</p><p eId="sec_5__subsec_4__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[Sub-r. (4) previously sub-r. (3) amended by r. 2 (ii) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1982/376" eId="sec_5__subsec_4__p_2__ref_1">PN 376 of 1982</ref>.]</remark></p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_5__subsec_5"><num>(5)</num><content><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5__p_1">Where a parking meter cannot be set in operation despite compliance or attempted compliance with the procedure prescribed in subsection (1), no driver or person in charge of any vehicle shall cause, allow, permit or suffer such vehicle to be or remain parked in the metered parking bay at which the said parking meter is installed for a continuous period exceeding the period which was indicated by the indicator of the parking meter when such vehicle was parked in the said parking bay; provided that if the said indicator shows that the time has expired or that the parking meter has not been set in operation, or if a hood has been placed over the parking meter as envisaged in <ref href="#sec_3" eId="sec_5__subsec_5__p_1__ref_1">section 3</ref> (2) (a), no such driver or person shall cause, allow, permit or suffer such vehicle to be or remain parked in the said metered parking bay.</p><p eId="sec_5__subsec_5__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[R. (5) inserted by r. 2 (iii) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1982/376" eId="sec_5__subsec_5__p_2__ref_1">PN 376 of 1982</ref>.]</remark></p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_6"><num>6.</num><heading>Discontinuance of metered parking bay</heading><content><p eId="sec_6__p_1">The City Engineer or any other officer authorised by the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_6__p_1__term_1">Council</term> to display road traffic signs may, whenever he deems it necessary or expedient to do so in the interests of the movement or control of traffic, place or erect a traffic sign or signs indicating “No Stopping” or “No <term refersTo="#term-Parking" eId="sec_6__p_1__term_2">Parking</term>” at any metered parking bay or bays, and it shall be unlawful for any person to stop or park a vehicle or to cause or permit a vehicle to be stopped or parked in such parking bay or bays while such sign or signs is so place or erected or during any period when the stopping or parking of a vehicle in the street or portion of the street concerned is prohibited in terms of any such traffic sign.</p><p eId="sec_6__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[R. 6 substituted by r. (iii) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1965/270" eId="sec_6__p_2__ref_1">PN 270 of 1965</ref> and amended by r. 4 of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1975/238" eId="sec_6__p_2__ref_2">PN 238 of 1975</ref>.]</remark></p></content></section><section eId="sec_7"><num>7.</num><heading>Interference with parking meters</heading><content><p eId="sec_7__p_1">No person shall misuse any parking meter or interfere or tamper or attempt to interfere or tamper with the working operation or mechanism of any parking meter, and no person shall, without authority from the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_7__p_1__term_1">Council</term>, affix or attempt to affix or place any placard, advertisement, notice, list, document board or thing on or paint, write upon or disfigure any parking meter.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_8"><num>8.</num><heading>Prescribed coins only to be deposited</heading><content><p eId="sec_8__p_1">No person shall deposit or cause to be deposited in any parking meter anything whatever other than the prescribed coin or coins.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_9"><num>9.</num><heading>Unlawful operation of parking meter</heading><content><p eId="sec_9__p_1">No person shall operate or attempt to operate any parking meter by any means other than as prescribed in these By-laws.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_10"><num>10.</num><heading>...</heading><content><p eId="sec_10__p_1"><remark status="editorial">[R. 10 deleted by r. 4 of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1972/290" eId="sec_10__p_1__ref_1">PN 290 of 1972</ref>.]</remark></p></content></section><section eId="sec_11"><num>11.</num><heading>Unlawful parking</heading><content><p eId="sec_11__p_1">It shall be unlawful for any person to cause, allow, permit or suffer any vehicle to be parked in any metered parking bay, except as permitted by the provisions of these By-laws.</p><p eId="sec_11__p_2">Where any vehicle is found to have been parked in contravention of the By-laws, it shall be deemed to have been or caused or allowed to have been parked by the person in whose name such vehicle is registered unless and until he shall prove to the contrary.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_12"><num>12.</num><heading>Exemption</heading><subsection eId="sec_12__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><intro><p eId="sec_12__subsec_1__intro__p_1">Notwithstanding anything in these By-laws contained, the driver or person in charge of the following vehicles may, subject to the provisions of this By-law, park in a metered parking bay without payment of the prescribed fee—</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_12__subsec_1__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_12__subsec_1__para_a__p_1">A vehicle used as an ambulance and being at the time used on urgent ambulance service.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_12__subsec_1__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_12__subsec_1__para_b__p_1">A vehicle used by a fire brigade for attendance at fires and being at the time used by the brigade in carrying out its duties of preventing or suppressing fires.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_12__subsec_1__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_12__subsec_1__para_c__p_1">A vehicle used by a member of any Police Force and being at the time used in connection with the execution of urgent police duties.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="sec_12__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="sec_12__subsec_2__p_1">Subject to any time limits or restrictions regarding the stopping or parking of vehicles as are prescribed by the Road Traffic Ordinance, 1966, or regulations or By-laws made thereunder every metered parking bay may be occupied without charge on Sundays and Public Holidays and also on any other days during the period from 5 p.m. to 8 a.m. on the following day; provided that on Saturdays such bays may be occupied without charge after 1 p.m..</p><p eId="sec_12__subsec_2__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[Sub-r. (2) amended by para (c) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1966/389" eId="sec_12__subsec_2__p_2__ref_1">PN 389 of 1966</ref> and substituted by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1985/463" eId="sec_12__subsec_2__p_2__ref_2">PN 463 of 1985</ref> and amended by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1987/387" eId="sec_12__subsec_2__p_2__ref_3">PN 387 of 1987</ref>.]</remark></p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_12A"><num>12A.</num><heading>Special provisions for disabled persons’ vehicles</heading><subsection eId="sec_12A__subsec_1"><num>(1)</num><content><p eId="sec_12A__subsec_1__p_1">The Chief Constable may, on application on a form approved by him, issue a hood to a licensed driver who produces a certificate by a registered medical practitioner or, if deemed necessary by the Chief Constable, by a medical specialist certifying that due to a permanent disability such person has substantial difficulty in walking.</p><p eId="sec_12A__subsec_1__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[Sub-r. (1) amended by r. 5 of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1975/238" eId="sec_12A__subsec_1__p_2__ref_1">PN 238 of 1975</ref>.]</remark></p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_12A__subsec_2"><num>(2)</num><content><p eId="sec_12A__subsec_2__p_1">Notwithstanding anything in the By-laws contained, a hood issued in terms of Subsection (1) shall, when placed over a parking meter, authorise the person to whom it was issued, subject to compliance with the provisions of Subsection (3), to park a motor car in the parking bay to which such meter relates without the need for depositing a coin in the meter, for a continuous period not exceeding three hours during any period other than that during which the stopping or parking of a motor car in the street or portion of the street concerned is prohibited.</p><p eId="sec_12A__subsec_2__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[Sub-r. (2) amended by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1986/217" eId="sec_12A__subsec_2__p_2__ref_1">PN 217 of 1986</ref>.]</remark></p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_12A__subsec_3"><num>(3)</num><intro><p eId="sec_12A__subsec_3__intro__p_1">The hood shall only be—</p></intro><paragraph eId="sec_12A__subsec_3__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_12A__subsec_3__para_a__p_1">used in connection with the motor car the registration number of which appears on such hood.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_12A__subsec_3__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_12A__subsec_3__para_b__p_1">placed upon a parking meter if such motor car was, when it was parked in the metered parking bay, being operated by the person to whom it was issued, and will when such hood is removed from the parking meter, again be operated by such person;</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_12A__subsec_3__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_12A__subsec_3__para_c__p_1">left upon a parking meter during such time as the motor car, the registration number whereof appears on such hood, is lawfully parked in the metered parking bay relating to such meter.</p></content></paragraph></subsection><subsection eId="sec_12A__subsec_4"><num>(4)</num><content><p eId="sec_12A__subsec_4__p_1">The Chief Constable may require the person to whom the hood has been issued who fails to comply with the provisions of subsection (3) to return such hood and it shall not be lawful for such hood to be used pending its return.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_12A__subsec_5"><num>(5)</num><content><p eId="sec_12A__subsec_5__p_1">Any person who is aggrieved by any refusal by the Chief Constable of his application or by any action taken by him in terms of subsection (4) may appeal within 14 days of being notified of the Chief Constable’s decision, to the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_12A__subsec_5__p_1__term_1">Council</term> or to any committee thereof to whom this function has been delegated whose decision shall be final.</p></content></subsection><subsection eId="sec_12A__subsec_6"><num>(6)</num><content><p eId="sec_12A__subsec_6__p_1">Any person to whom a hood is issued shall be responsible for its maintenance and safekeeping and will be liable for the cost of its replacement or repair.</p><p eId="sec_12A__subsec_6__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[R. 12A inserted by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1974/615" eId="sec_12A__subsec_6__p_2__ref_1">PN 615 of 1974</ref>.]</remark></p></content></subsection></section><section eId="sec_13"><num>13.</num><heading>Offences</heading><content><p eId="sec_13__p_1">Any person who contravenes any of the provisions of these By-laws shall be guilty of an offence and shall be liable on conviction to a fine not exceeding R200 in the case of a first conviction or in the case of a second or subsequent conviction, for the same offence, a fine not exceeding R400, or in default of payment of any fine imposed in either case, imprisonment for any period not exceeding three months.</p><p eId="sec_13__p_2"><remark status="editorial">[R. 13 substituted by para (d) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1966/389" eId="sec_13__p_2__ref_1">PN 389 of 1966</ref>.]</remark></p></content></section></body><attachments><attachment eId="att_1"><heading>First Schedule (By-Laws 1 and 10)</heading><subheading>Metered zones and tariff of parking fees</subheading><doc name="schedule"><meta><identification source="#Laws-Africa"><FRBRWork><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-eth/act/by-law/1957/parking-meter/!schedule_1"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-eth/act/by-law/1957/parking-meter"/><FRBRalias value="First Schedule (By-Laws 1 and 10)" name="title"/><FRBRdate date="1957" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/><FRBRcountry value="za-eth"/><FRBRsubtype value="by-law"/><FRBRnumber value="parking-meter"/></FRBRWork><FRBRExpression><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-eth/act/by-law/1957/parking-meter/eng@1957-01-17/!schedule_1"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-eth/act/by-law/1957/parking-meter/eng@1957-01-17"/><FRBRdate date="1957-01-17" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/><FRBRlanguage language="eng"/></FRBRExpression><FRBRManifestation><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-eth/act/by-law/1957/parking-meter/eng@1957-01-17/!schedule_1"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-eth/act/by-law/1957/parking-meter/eng@1957-01-17"/><FRBRdate date="2020-02-06" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/></FRBRManifestation></identification></meta><mainBody><p eId="att_1__p_1"><remark status="editorial">[First Schedule amended by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1958/343" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_1">PN 343 of 1958</ref>, by r. (iii) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1959/215" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_2">PN 215 of 1959</ref>, by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1960/266" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_3">PN 266 of 1960</ref>, by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1961/419" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_4">PN 419 of 1961</ref>, substituted by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1962/90" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_5">PN 90 of 1962</ref>, amended by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1963/346" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_6">PN 346 of 1963</ref>, by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/mn/1965/7" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_7">MN 7 of 1965</ref>, amended by para. (e) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1966/389" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_8">PN 389 of 1966</ref>, substituted by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1966/44" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_9">PN 44 of 1966</ref>, amended by para. (b) of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1967/362" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_10">PN 362 of 1967</ref>, by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1968/154" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_11">PN 154 of 1968</ref>, by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1969/526" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_12">PN 526 of 1969</ref>, by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1969/292" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_13">PN 292 of 1969</ref>, by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1970/99" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_14">PN 99 of 1970</ref>, by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1970/324" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_15">PN 324 of 1970</ref>, by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1970/353" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_16">PN 353 of 1970</ref>, by <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1972/84" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_17">PN 84 of 1972</ref> and deleted by r. 4 of <ref href="/akn/za-eth/act/pn/1972/290" eId="att_1__p_1__ref_18">PN 290 of 1972</ref>.]</remark></p></mainBody></doc></attachment></attachments></act></akomaNtoso>