<akomaNtoso xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0"><act name="act"><meta><identification source="#Laws-Africa"><FRBRWork><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/disposal-contaminated-infectious-waste/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/disposal-contaminated-infectious-waste"/><FRBRalias value="Disposal of Contaminated and/or Infectious Waste" name="title"/><FRBRdate date="2017" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/><FRBRcountry value="za-ec443"/><FRBRsubtype value="by-law"/><FRBRnumber value="disposal-contaminated-infectious-waste"/></FRBRWork><FRBRExpression><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/disposal-contaminated-infectious-waste/eng@2017-04-24/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/disposal-contaminated-infectious-waste/eng@2017-04-24"/><FRBRdate date="2017-04-24" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/><FRBRlanguage language="eng"/></FRBRExpression><FRBRManifestation><FRBRthis value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/disposal-contaminated-infectious-waste/eng@2017-04-24/!main"/><FRBRuri value="/akn/za-ec443/act/by-law/2017/disposal-contaminated-infectious-waste/eng@2017-04-24"/><FRBRdate date="2020-01-27" name="Generation"/><FRBRauthor href=""/></FRBRManifestation></identification><publication number="3830" name="Eastern Cape Provincial Gazette" showAs="Eastern Cape Provincial Gazette" date="2017-04-24"/><references source="#Laws-Africa"><TLCOrganization showAs="Laws.Africa" eId="Laws-Africa" href="https://edit.laws.africa"/><TLCTerm showAs="Isolation waste" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.Isolation_waste" eId="term-Isolation_waste"/><TLCTerm showAs="Contaminated animal carcasses, body parts and bedding" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.Contaminated_animal_carcasses__body_parts_and_bedding" eId="term-Contaminated_animal_carcasses__body_parts_and_bedding"/><TLCTerm showAs="Human blood and blood products" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.Human_blood_and_blood_products" eId="term-Human_blood_and_blood_products"/><TLCTerm showAs="Miscellaneous contaminated wastes" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.Miscellaneous_contaminated_wastes" eId="term-Miscellaneous_contaminated_wastes"/><TLCTerm showAs="Pathological waste" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.Pathological_waste" eId="term-Pathological_waste"/><TLCTerm showAs="Contaminated sharps" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.Contaminated_sharps" eId="term-Contaminated_sharps"/><TLCTerm showAs="Infectious waste" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.Infectious_waste" eId="term-Infectious_waste"/><TLCTerm showAs="Council" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.Council" eId="term-Council"/><TLCTerm showAs="Municipality" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.Municipality" eId="term-Municipality"/><TLCTerm showAs="Cultures and stocks of infectious agents and associated biologicals" href="/ontology/term/this.eng.Cultures_and_stocks_of_infectious_agents_and_associated_biologicals" eId="term-Cultures_and_stocks_of_infectious_agents_and_associated_biologicals"/></references></meta><preface><p eId="preface__p_1">The Municipal Manager of Mbizana Local Municipality hereby publishes, in terms of Section 13 of the Local Government Municipal Systems Act, 2000 (<ref href="/akn/za/act/2000/32" eId="preface__p_1__ref_1">Act 32 of 2000</ref>) read with Section 162 of the <ref href="/akn/za/act/1996/constitution" eId="preface__p_1__ref_2">Constitution of the Republic of South Africa Act 1996</ref> (<ref href="/akn/za/act/1996/constitution" eId="preface__p_1__ref_3">Act 108 of 1996</ref>) the By-Law Relating to the Disposal of Contaminated and or Infectious Waste which shall come into operation on the date of publication thereof.</p></preface><body><section eId="sec_1"><num>1.</num><heading>Definitions</heading><content><p eId="sec_1__p_1">In these by-laws unless the context indicates otherwise:</p><p refersTo="#term-Contaminated_animal_carcasses__body_parts_and_bedding" eId="sec_1__p_2">"<def refersTo="#term-Contaminated_animal_carcasses__body_parts_and_bedding" eId="sec_1__p_2__def_1">Contaminated animal carcasses, body parts and bedding</def>" means contaminated carcasses, body parts and bedding of animals that were intentionally exposed to pathogens in research, in the production of biologicals, or the in vivo testing of pharmaceuticals.</p><p refersTo="#term-Contaminated_sharps" eId="sec_1__p_3">"<def refersTo="#term-Contaminated_sharps" eId="sec_1__p_3__def_1">Contaminated sharps</def>" means discarded sharps (e.g. hypodermic needles, syringes, pasteur pipettes, broken glass, scalpel blades) which have come into contact with infectious agents during use in patient care or in medical, research or industrial laboratories.</p><p refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_1__p_4">"<def refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_1__p_4__def_1">Council</def>" means the Council of the <term refersTo="#term-Municipality" eId="sec_1__p_4__term_1">Municipality</term> or any duly authorised Committee or official of the Council.</p><p refersTo="#term-Cultures_and_stocks_of_infectious_agents_and_associated_biologicals" eId="sec_1__p_5">"<def refersTo="#term-Cultures_and_stocks_of_infectious_agents_and_associated_biologicals" eId="sec_1__p_5__def_1">Cultures and stocks of infectious agents and associated biologicals</def>" means specimen cultures from medical and pathological laboratories, cultures and stocks of infectious agents from research and industrial laboratories, wastes from the production of biologicals and live or attenuated vaccines and culture dishes and devices used to transfer, innoculate and mix cultures.</p><p refersTo="#term-Human_blood_and_blood_products" eId="sec_1__p_6">"<def refersTo="#term-Human_blood_and_blood_products" eId="sec_1__p_6__def_1">Human blood and blood products</def>" means waste such as serum, plasma and other blood components.</p><p refersTo="#term-Infectious_waste" eId="sec_1__p_7">"<def refersTo="#term-Infectious_waste" eId="sec_1__p_7__def_1">Infectious waste</def>" means waste capable of producing an infectious disease.</p><p refersTo="#term-Isolation_waste" eId="sec_1__p_8">"<def refersTo="#term-Isolation_waste" eId="sec_1__p_8__def_1">Isolation waste</def>" means waste generated by hospitalised patients isolated to protect others from communicable diseases.</p><p refersTo="#term-Miscellaneous_contaminated_wastes" eId="sec_1__p_9">"<def refersTo="#term-Miscellaneous_contaminated_wastes" eId="sec_1__p_9__def_1">Miscellaneous contaminated wastes</def>" means wastes from surgery and autopsy (e.g. soiled dressings. sponges, drapes, lavage tubes, drainage sets, under-pads and gloves), contaminated laboratory wastes (e.g. specimen containers, slides and cover slips, disposal gloves, laboratory coats and aprons), dialysis unit waste (e.g. tubing filters, disposable sheets, towels, gloves, aprons and laboratory coats), and contaminated equipment (e.g. equipment used in patient care, medical and industrial laboratories, research and in the production and testing of certain pharmaceuticals).</p><p refersTo="#term-Municipality" eId="sec_1__p_10">"<def refersTo="#term-Municipality" eId="sec_1__p_10__def_1">Municipality</def>" means the Municipality of Mbizana.</p><p refersTo="#term-Pathological_waste" eId="sec_1__p_11">"<def refersTo="#term-Pathological_waste" eId="sec_1__p_11__def_1">Pathological waste</def>" means waste consisting of tissues, organs, body parts and body fluids that are removed during surgery and autopsy.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_2"><num>2.</num><heading>Storage of infectious waste</heading><paragraph eId="sec_2__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_2__para_a__p_1">All infectious waste must be placed at the point of generation into a container approved by the Council.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_2__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_2__para_b__p_1">The container used for the storage of sharp objects must be constructed of such a material that the object cannot pierce the container. The container must also be fitted with a safe and hygienic lid which must be sealed after use.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_2__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_2__para_c__p_1">The container used for the disposal of other infectious waste must be constructed of a suitable material preventing the leakage of the contents. The container must also be fitted with a safe and hygienic lid which must be sealed after use.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_2__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_2__para_d__p_1">All containers must be adequately labelled and marked with the universal bio-hazardous waste symbol.</p></content></paragraph></section><section eId="sec_3"><num>3.</num><heading>Transport of <term refersTo="#term-Infectious_waste" eId="sec_3__term_1">Infectious waste</term></heading><paragraph eId="sec_3__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_3__para_a__p_1">All containers of infectious waste must be sealed intact at the point of generation.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_3__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_3__para_b__p_1">The vehicle transporting infectious waste must be clearly marked indicating infectious waste in transit.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_3__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_3__para_c__p_1">The vehicle used for the transport of infectious waste must be so designed that the driver’s cab is separated from the load area. The load area must be enclosed with suitable sealable, lockable doors.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_3__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_3__para_d__p_1">All infectious loads being carried or conveyed for disposal must be invoiced by the person or institution from which such waste is generated and the invoice must contain details of the premises from which the infectious waste was generated and the premises where the waste will be disposed of.</p></content></paragraph></section><section eId="sec_4"><num>4.</num><heading>Removal and disposal of infectious waste</heading><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_a"><num>(a)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_a__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_4__para_a__p_1__term_1">Council</term> may remove infectious waste from the premises of generation and dispose thereof in a safe, sanitary and supervised manner, and the owner of such premises or the owner of the waste as determined by the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_4__para_a__p_1__term_2">Council</term> shall be liable to the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_4__para_a__p_1__term_3">Council</term> for payment of the tariff charges in respect of the aforesaid removal services.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_b"><num>(b)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_b__p_1">Private contractors may, with the written consent of the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_4__para_b__p_1__term_1">Council</term> and subject to such terms and conditions as it may determine, remove and dispose of infectious waste.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_c"><num>(c)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_c__p_1"><term refersTo="#term-Infectious_waste" eId="sec_4__para_c__p_1__term_1">Infectious waste</term> may, with the written consent of the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_4__para_c__p_1__term_2">Council</term> and subject to compliance with such terms and conditions as it may determine, be disposed of in an approved high temperature pollution free incinerator on the premises of origin of such waste.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_d"><num>(d)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_d__p_1">Unless otherwise determined by the <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_4__para_d__p_1__term_1">Council</term>, the burning temperatures in the primary and secondary chambers of the incinerator shall, at all times, exceed 800 degrees C and 1000 degrees C respectively and also have rapid cooling to prevent carcinogenic chemicals from entering the atmosphere.</p></content></paragraph><paragraph eId="sec_4__para_f"><num>(f)</num><content><p eId="sec_4__para_f__p_1">The <term refersTo="#term-Council" eId="sec_4__para_f__p_1__term_1">Council</term> may by resolution determine additional conditions pertaining to the storage, placement, removal and conveyance of contaminated and or infectious waste including conditions pertaining to vehicles used for the removal and transportation of such waste and such additional conditions shall apply in addition to the conditions contained in these by-laws.</p></content></paragraph></section><section eId="sec_4_2"><num>4.</num><heading><term refersTo="#term-Infectious_waste" eId="sec_4_2__term_1">Infectious waste</term></heading><content><p eId="sec_4_2__p_1">For the purpose of these by-laws, infectious waste shall include all the wastes referred to in section 1 hereof as well as contaminated animal carcasses, body parts, bedding, sharps, cultures and stocks of infectious agents and associated biologicals, human blood and blood products.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_5"><num>5.</num><heading>Penalties</heading><content><p eId="sec_5__p_1">Any person who contravenes or fails to comply with any provision of these by-laws or any instruction or permit issued thereunder shall be guilty of an offence and be liable on conviction to a fine not exceeding R1000 or such higher amount as is determined from time to time by the Minister of Justice as contemplated in section 1(1)(a) of the Adjustment of Fines Act 1991 (<ref href="/akn/za/act/1991/101" eId="sec_5__p_1__ref_1">Act No. 101 of 1991</ref>) or to imprisonment for a period not exceeding six months or to both such fine and such imprisonment.</p></content></section><section eId="sec_6"><num>6.</num><heading>Repeal of By-Laws</heading><content><p eId="sec_6__p_1">Any by-law relating to the disposal of contaminated and or infectious waste adopted by the municipality or any municipality now comprising an administrative unit of the municipality is repealed from the date of promulgation of these by-laws.</p></content></section></body></act></akomaNtoso>